<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The table of the Lord whereof, 1. The vvhole seruice, is the liuing bread. 2. The guests, any man. 3. The mouth to eate, faith onely. By Gilbert Primerose, Doctour of Divinitie, one of his Maiesties chaplaines in ordinary, and pastour of the French church at London.</title>
            <author>Primrose, Gilbert, ca. 1580-1642.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1626</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 206 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 119 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10135</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20392</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114083</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849311</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849311</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14451</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10135)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14451)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1493:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The table of the Lord whereof, 1. The vvhole seruice, is the liuing bread. 2. The guests, any man. 3. The mouth to eate, faith onely. By Gilbert Primerose, Doctour of Divinitie, one of his Maiesties chaplaines in ordinary, and pastour of the French church at London.</title>
                  <author>Primrose, Gilbert, ca. 1580-1642.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22], 213, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I. D[awson] for Nicholas Bourne, and are to be sold at his shop at the Royall Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1626.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Consists of two sermons preached to the King in July, 1625.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14451:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14451:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE TABLE OF THE LORD: <hi>WHEREOF</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>1. THE VVHOLE SERVICE, IS THE LIVING BREAD.</item>
                  <item>2. THE GVESTS, ANY MAN.</item>
                  <item>3. THE MOVTH TO Eate, FAITH ONELY.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> GILBERT PRIMEROSE, <hi>Doctour of Divinitie, one of his</hi> Maieſties <hi>Chaplaines in Ordinary, and Paſtour of the French Church at</hi> London.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>I. D.</hi> for <hi>Nicholas Bourne,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the <hi>Royall Exchange.</hi> 1626.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:14451:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14451:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14451:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14451:3"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, S<hi rend="sup">ir</hi> IAMES FOVVLERTON, Firſt Gentleman of his MAIESTIES Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chamber, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>RIGHT HONOVRABLE,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ooner ſhall the heaven be without ſtars, the ſtars without light, the fire without heat, the aire without moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, the Sea without agitation, a faire med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow without graſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:14451:4"/>then the Church with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the poiſonous tares, and noyſome weeds of helliſh hereſies, which ſpringing vp with the wholeſome and ſoule-feeding wheat the Lord Ieſus hath ſowed in the heavenly field of his Church, haſt to ſmoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it, ere it grow to any beautiful and fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full perfection. For<note n="a" place="margin">1 Cor. 11.19.</note> 
               <hi>there muſt be hereſies, that they which are approved may be made manifeſt.</hi> Therefore, as God foretelling that<note n="b" place="margin">Zach. 1.18.19.20.21.</note> 
               <hi>foure hornes</hi> ſhould ariſe to ſcatter <hi>Iudah, Iſrael,</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:14451:4"/>
               <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> foretold alſo that he had appointed <hi>foure Carpenters</hi> to fray them, even ſo foreſeing that by the ever-wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching craft of the ever-waking divell, the vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous ſeed of deadly er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors ſhould grow with the good corne of the Goſpell to choake it, he ordained diligent and faithfull<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.9.</note> 
               <hi>Labourers</hi> to weed and plucke them out by the roote.</p>
            <p>Theſe Labourers are the Paſtours of the Church, who ſhould be, not onely<note n="d" place="margin">1 Tim. 3 2. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>apt to teach</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:14451:5"/>good and ſound doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, but alſo<note n="e" place="margin">Tit. 1.9. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>apt to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince the gaineſayers.</hi> And certainely, if it be the dutie of all Chriſtians, not onely<note n="f" place="margin">Athenag. in legat. pro Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianis. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>to ſpeake of the truth,</hi> but alſo <hi>to diſpute for the truth:</hi> How much more ſhould the man of God, the Doctour of the Church be<note n="g" place="margin">Aug. de Doc. Chri. lib. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eritatis propugna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor &amp; er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roris ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnator.</note> 
               <hi>defender of the truth, and over-commer of errour:</hi> Never was there in the Church greater need of both, then now that the <hi>Whoore</hi> of <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> giues to the Kings and great men of the earth, great bowles of
<pb facs="tcp:14451:5"/>her phyltres to drinke, farre more dangerous then the waters of <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiopia;</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <note n="i" place="margin">Ovid. <hi>15.</hi> Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morphoſ.</note> Quos ſi quis faucibus hauſit,</l>
                  <l>Aut furit, aut patitur mirum gravitate ſoporem.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>For aſſoone as they haue ſet that golden cup to their heads, they are poſſeſſed with a dizzi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and, as if they had drunke a worſe <hi>Nepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thé</hi> then that which<note n="k" place="margin">Homer. Odyſ. lib. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Helena</hi> gaue to <hi>Telema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus,</hi> they forget their owne name of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and never ſpeake
<pb facs="tcp:14451:6"/>of Ieſus Chriſt, but to ſeeke vnder a Herodian colour of worſhipping him, to kill him againe in his members.</p>
            <p>Of what peſtilent herbes that loue-drinke is made, who knowes not? How all thoſe that call themſelues <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques</hi> are bewitched with it, who ſees not? Where theſe miſhapen and ougly plants, whoſe bane-giving liquor ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhes the wiſeſt men from their beſt wits, doe grow, who hath read in the ſeventeenth
<pb facs="tcp:14451:6"/>chapter of the <hi>Revelation</hi> of S. <hi>Iohn</hi> what is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of the woman ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rayed in purple &amp; ſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let, of the golden cup in her hand full of abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, and filthineſſe of her fornications, of the name written on her forehead in capitall Letters, MYSTERY, BABYLON THE GREAT, THE MO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THER OF HAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LOTS, AND ABO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MINATIONS OF THE EARTH, of the blood of the Saints wherewith ſhe is drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken,
<pb facs="tcp:14451:7"/>of the beaſt with ſeaven heads ſhe ſits vpon, of many waters ſhe rules over, and will not affirme boldly, that S. <hi>Hierome</hi> ſtrayed not from the Truth, when he ſaid it is<note n="l" place="margin">Hierony. ad Marcel linam vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duam.</note> 
               <hi>Rupes Turpeia,</hi> the Towne builded on <hi>ſeaven Mountaines, Rome,</hi> even that <hi>Rome</hi> where in <hi>Hieromes</hi> dayes <hi>was the true Church, the Trophies of the Apoſtles and Martyrs, the true confeſsion of Christ,</hi> and was then decaying, then beginning to be<note n="m" place="margin">Rev. 18.</note> 
               <hi>the habitation of devils, the hold of every foule Spirit, and
<pb facs="tcp:14451:7"/>a cage of every vncleane and hatefull bird?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is <hi>the devils gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> and <hi>his Gardener</hi> the man of ſinne, the Sonne of perdition, whoſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſaries runne abroad ſowing every where the aconit of his moſt venemous doctrine, the only Marchandiſe theſe Mountebankes of the fourth vow fetch from that dungeon of infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal fiends, which being<note n="n" place="margin">Rev. 11.8.</note> 
               <hi>ſpiritually Sodom and Egypt,</hi> hath nothing but faire ſhewes of rotten and ſtinking drugges, like
<pb facs="tcp:14451:8"/>
               <hi>the</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Ioſeph. de bello Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daico. lib. <hi>5</hi> cap. <hi>5.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>apples of Sodom,</hi> which at the firſt touching va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh away in ſmoake and aſhes, and worſe then <hi>Egypt,</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">Odyſſ. lib. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>Abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds in evill weeds, &amp; hath few or no good hearbes. Of theſe loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and infectious hearbs, the beſt where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is but Swines-graſſe, at my attendance at Court in <hi>Iuly</hi> laſt, I la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured to grubbe vp with the hooke-weed of the word of GOD
<pb facs="tcp:14451:8"/>that poyſonous Toad-ſtoole, called <hi>Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation,</hi> the laſt and the fouleſt maſter-piece of work of the divels huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry, and wherein he delights moſt, becauſe it is moſt like vnto himſelfe: For by it <hi>Ceres</hi> &amp; <hi>Bacchus</hi> are worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped vnder the name of Chriſt, poore Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans blind-folded by the <hi>Corybantes</hi> of <hi>Babylon,</hi> are holden in hand, that a round and thin cruſt of the breadth of a ſhilling is Chriſts owne ſelfe, as big, as tall, as perfect a
<pb facs="tcp:14451:9"/>man as he was on the Croſſe, that at the Maſſe they ſee him, that at Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter they eate with the mouths of their bodies his fleſh, bones, blood, and whole body, that therefore they muſt worſhip that cruſt with the worſhip of <hi>Latria</hi> due to none but God: So he makes them the greateſt, or at leaſt as great idolaters as ever were in the world: This ſeemed ſo barbarous to the Ambaſſadours of <hi>the Towpinambauts</hi> in <hi>Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</hi> not long ſince, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb facs="tcp:14451:9"/>they be the moſt barbarous people of the world, and eaters of mens fleſh, yet to the naturall light that hath remained in their bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh minds, this went beyond all brutiſhneſs, that <hi>reaſonable men ſhould eate that which they worſhip, or worſhip that which they eate:</hi> And <hi>certainely,</hi> ſaid they, <hi>if Our God were as beneficiall to vs, as your Chriſt is to you, we would honour him the beſt we could, but we would not eate him.</hi> And one of them made a <hi>Proſelyte</hi> by the Capuchin Friars
<pb facs="tcp:14451:10"/>of <hi>Paris,</hi> being asked if he was now a good Chriſtian, <hi>Yes,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>for every day for my breake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt I eate one of your Chriſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What I then preached in two Sermons, both for the truth, &amp; againſt this moſt abominable errour. I haue ſet down in this little Booke, which I dare to ſend abroad cloathed with the livery of your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable &amp; moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Name, that appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to the common view with ſuch a good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly face, it may be well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comer
<pb facs="tcp:14451:10"/>to the Readers, and as it ſhall pleaſe God to giue a bleſſing vnto it, helpe to recall and reclaime thoſe that goe a whooring with the works of their own hands, or at leaſt to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect ſuch of our owne, who deſirous to wind the ſpole-fuls of wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed and intricate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies, for not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving their ſences exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in ſuch a weariſom and painefull labour, cannot finde the right ende of the thread, and being once entred
<pb facs="tcp:14451:11"/>into the vnknowne crookes of that turning labyrinth, cannot goe thorow them without a more aſſured and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible guide, then the thread of Ariadné.</p>
            <p>Your Honour having as great acquaintance with all kinde of true learning, and namely with true divinitie, as many of the learnedeſt, I confeſſe this Booke can haue no ſuch vſe to you-ward: Neither was that my intentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> when I honoured it with your worthy Name: My one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:14451:11"/>deſire being to make it a true and publicke witneſſe that ſince that time you vouchſafed me the honour of your loue, I could conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, conſidering know, knowing acknowledg, acknowledging reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence your manifold &amp; rare gifts, quite voide of all oſtentatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which the holy Ghoſt, as moſt precious ſtones, hath ſet in a heart of true god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, and which as they haue beene the happy and godly direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours of our then moſt
<pb facs="tcp:14451:12"/>hopefull Prince, ſo are they now the true and faithfull Counſellours of our maieſticall, he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roicall, and religious King, who ſo long as his royall eares ſhall hang at the wiſe tongs of ſo moderate &amp; godly Senatours, neither ſhall the diſtreſſed Church want protection, nor his Subiects iuſtice in him, nor he bleſſe-brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging prayers and true obedience in them.</p>
            <p>If any ſay a greater worke was due to ſo excellent a perſonage:
<pb facs="tcp:14451:12"/>your Honour will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere for me, that<note n="q" place="margin">Demoſt. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>not great, but good things are beſt;</hi> that good is this little worke in the matter, that it is handled, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though not exquiſitly in words, yet ſoundly. Moreover, I anſwer for my ſelfe, that by your meanes I came to the Kings knowledge, and by your recommenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was named by his Maieſty to be one of his Chaplaines: Therefore to you are due the firſt fruits of that harveſt, which ſuch as they are
<pb facs="tcp:14451:13"/>I conſecrate to your <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,</hi> and my ſelfe to the continuance of your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, offering my hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty prayers to <hi>God</hi> for the increaſing of his merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full &amp; favourable bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings on your graue and old age, <hi>on your right re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious and honourable Lady,</hi> and all her moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and godly Family, till they come to their ful meaſure in <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> in whom I remaine for ever,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours moſt humble and affectionate ſervant, <hi>G. PRIMEROSE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:14451:13"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Of the living Bread which came downe from Heaven.</hi> Preached at <hi>Whitehall</hi> to the KINGS houſe on the Communion day the 3. of <hi>Iuly.</hi> 1625.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>IOHN. VI.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="51">
                     <hi>51.</hi> I am the living Bread which came downe from Heaven.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>FIRST CHAPTER.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>I.</hi> The whole Chriſtian Religion may be reduced to two heads: The firſt, concerning the Saviour: The ſecond, concerning them which are ſaved. God alone teacheth the one and the other.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>II.</hi> By his Sonne Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>III.</hi> Who ſetteth downe theſe two heads in this Verſe.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>IV.</hi> Foure parts of the firſt part of this Verſe.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LL the Chriſtian Religion may be reduced to two heads: The firſt
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:14451:14"/>is concerning the Saviour of the world: The ſecond is concerning them which are ſaved. It is written in the third <hi>Pſalme,</hi> that<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 3.8.</note> 
                  <hi>Salvation is the Lords:</hi> Salvation is the Lords gift; Salvation is the Lords worke; Salvation is the Lord himſelfe. Who then can more truely, Who can more clearly ſpeake of ſalvatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and of thoſe which are ſaved, then the Lord who is the ſalvation of all them which are ſaved? As we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee the Sunne but by the light of the Sunne; ſo we cannot know God, nor the ſalvation which is of GOD, but by the revelatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God,<note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>6.9.</note> 
                  <hi>in whoſe light we ſee light.</hi> And<note n="c" place="margin">Iob. 36.22.</note> 
                  <hi>who teacheth like him?</hi> The ſonnes of men may be deceived in that which they
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:14451:14"/>know, by reaſon of their ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance: or deceiue by that which they teach, and like vnto the wild fire, called by the Latines <hi>Ignis fatuus,</hi> lead many a man into the quag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mires, pits, and gulfes of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall perdition, by reaſon of their vanitie: For<note n="d" place="margin">Pſal. 116.11.</note> 
                  <hi>all men are lyers.</hi> But God cannot be deceived in that which he knoweth, becauſe he is <hi>All-wiſe:</hi> Nor deceiue in that which he teacheth, becauſe he is <hi>All-good.</hi> He is alwayes true: True in his knowledge, True in his teaching.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> He teacheth vs by his Son: His Sonne who is<note n="e" place="margin">Ioh. 1.1.</note> 
                  <hi>his Word:</hi> Not<note n="f" place="margin">Ignat. epiſt. ad Magneſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>a vocall</hi> Word formed by the tongue, not a found in the aire, beating the eares: For <hi>hee was in the beginning</hi> before there was aire or
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14451:15"/>eares: But <hi>a ſubſtantiall word,</hi> but Gods own mind,<note n="g" place="margin">Cyril. l. <hi>1.</hi> Theſauric. <hi>5</hi> Quia ex ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo eſt filius vocatur: quia vero in ipſo, ſapientia &amp; verbum.</note> 
                  <hi>called the Sonne, becauſe he is of the Father: and the Wiſedome and Word, becauſe he is in the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:</hi> becauſe alſo God hath from the beginning revealed his Word to the Church by him<note n="h" place="margin">Ioh. 1.18.</note> 
                  <hi>For no man hath ſeene God at any time: The onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Sonne, which is in the boſome of the Father, he hath declared him:</hi> He he onely<note n="i" place="margin">Ioh. 14.16</note> 
                  <hi>is the way, the truth, and the life: The way</hi> wherein, <hi>The truth</hi> whereby, <hi>The life</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto we walke. And as <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> ſaith;<note n="k" place="margin">Bernard. de caena domini. ſerm. <hi>7.</hi> Ego ſum via ſine errore, veri tas fine falſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, vita ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne morte.</note> 
                  <hi>The way without errour, the truth without falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, the life without death.</hi> Even<note n="l" place="margin">1 Ioh. 5.20.</note> 
                  <hi>the true God, and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life: The true God,</hi> and therefore our Saviour: <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life,</hi> and therefore our
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:14451:15"/>ſalvation. Wherefore let vs now and for ever liſten vnto Chriſt, who beſt of all can tell vs who is the Author, who the giver, who the Prince of eternall life: As likewiſe which be they on whom this moſt wonderfull gift, this bleſſed and preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous iewell is vouchſafed: For<note n="m" place="margin">Ioh. 3.32.33.</note> 
                  <hi>he that is of the earth, is earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſpeaketh of the earth: He that commeth from heaven, is aboue all: and what he hath ſeene and heard, that he teſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,</hi> and<note n="n" place="margin">Ioh. 8.14.</note> 
                  <hi>his record is true.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> As in all this Chapter moſt largely, ſo in this verſe of the Chapter ſummarily and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinctly he beareth Record both of the Saviour, and of them which are ſaved Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Saviour he ſaith; <hi>I am the living bread which
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:14451:16"/>came downe from heaven.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning them which are ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved he ſaith alſo in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond part of this Verſe, <hi>If any man eate of this bread, he ſhall liue for ever.</hi> The one and the other are vttered in Metaphoricall words, or in two ſimilitudes contracted each of them to one word: The ſence of the firſt is that which God ſaid vnto Chriſt by the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi>
                  <note n="o" place="margin">Iſa. 49.6.</note> 
                  <hi>I will giue thee for a light to the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, that thou mayeſt be my ſalvation vnto the end of the world.</hi> The ſence of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond is ſet downe in this ſame Chapter, <hi>verſ.</hi> 47. where Chriſt ſaith; <hi>He that beleeveth on me hath euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IV"/> The firſt part of the verſe, is the foundation wherevp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:14451:16"/>with the aſſiſtance of the Spirit of God I am to build this exhortatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, conſidering in it, firſt, <hi>the ſubiect</hi> of this enunciation, <hi>I am the living bread,</hi> and next, <hi>the attribute</hi> thereof. <hi>The ſubiect</hi> is Chriſt, in the Word. I. <hi>The attribute,</hi> is <hi>the living bread which came downe from heaven.</hi> Theſe two are coupled together by the coupling word, <hi>Am:</hi> But becauſe this diviſion will ſeeme too ſcholaſticall and harſh to popular &amp; vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned eares, we ſhall follow the words of the Text, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding them into foure parts conſider, 1. To whom Chriſt doth aſcribe this glory to be the living bread: Even to his owne ſelfe, ſaying, <hi>I am.</hi> 2. Why he calleth himſelfe <hi>bread:</hi> for he ſaith. <hi>I am bread.</hi>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:14451:17"/>3. The excellency and vſe of this bread, in that he calleth it <hi>living,</hi> I am, ſaith he, <hi>the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving bread.</hi> 4. The ſpring from whence this excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy doth flow; in the words following, <hi>which came downe from heaven.</hi> Let vs then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, and our beginning and<note n="p" place="margin">Pſal. 115.8.</note> 
                  <hi>helpe be in the Name of the Lord, who made heaven and earth.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>SECOND CHAPTER.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>I.</hi> Chriſt ſheweth that he alone is the living bread which came downe from heaven.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>II.</hi> In all matters of faith and of manners, arguments taken from the Scriptures negatiuely are neceſſary.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>III.</hi> An eaſie way how to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere to the Sophiſticall inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogations
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:14451:17"/>of the Ieſuits concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Scriptures.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>IV.</hi> Angels and Saints are no part of the living bread. <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>WHEN wee ſpeake of titles of digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or of any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent qualitie, it is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to know before all things the perſons which are capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of them, and to whom they belong. Becauſe all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are not capable of all titles, and all dignities are not fit for all. For all men are not of one ſiſe: yea as one little diamond is more to be valued then a thouſand big ſtones; So one man is often more to be eſteemed then ten thouſand others, as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> Captaines ſaid vnto
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:14451:18"/>him,<note n="q" place="margin">2 Sam. 18 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou art worth ten thouſand of vs.</hi> For this cauſe<note n="r" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. lib. <hi>1.</hi> Tit. <hi>5.</hi> de ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu homirum l. <hi>2.</hi> Cum igi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Inſtit. lib <hi>1.</hi> Tit. <hi>2.</hi> de iurenat. Gent. &amp; Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vili. §. vlt. Parum eſt ius noſse, fi perſona, qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum cauſa conſtitutum eſt, ignoran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tior.</note> in the civill Law the firſt queſtion is of the ſufficiency and abilitie of the perſons the next is of their rights, prerogatiues, &amp; other things which they challenge and take vpon them: It is ſo in Divinitie, and particularly in this part thereof concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Saviour of the world. The <hi>Iewes</hi> deſiring that Chriſt would feed them more delicately then he had done, alleaged vnto him <hi>verſ.</hi> 31. the example of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> ſaying, that <hi>he gaue to their Fathers bread from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to eate:</hi> Wherevpon ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a new occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſpeake to them of a more excellent bread, he anſwered, <hi>verſ.</hi> 32. <hi>Verily, verily, I ſay vnto you,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:14451:18"/>Moſes gaue you not that bread from heaven: But my Father giueth you the true bread from heaven. Moſes</hi> is excluded as inſufficient to giue from heaven the bread of heaven. And the Father alone is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorned with that glory. For who can giue the bread of heaven but the Father of lights which is in heaven? 2. He deſcribeth vnto them the excellency and vertue of that bread, ſaying, <hi>verſ.</hi> 33. <hi>for the bread of God is he which commeth downe from heaven, and giueth life vnto the world.</hi> See the excellencie of it. <hi>It is come downe from heaven:</hi> See the vertue and vſe of it, <hi>It giueth life vnto the world.</hi> 3. He telleth them who is that bread, and claiming that glory to himſelfe; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14451:19"/>
                  <hi>verſ.</hi> 35. <hi>I am the bread of life.</hi> Then the <hi>Iewes,</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting the miracle of the fiue loaues and of the two fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes, <hi>murmured at him, becauſe he ſaid, I am the bread which came downe from heauen.</hi> verſ. 41. But he notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their murmuring gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth glory to God, and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to overcome their ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacie and ſtubborneneſſe, affirmeth againe, <hi>Verſe</hi> 48. <hi>I am that bread of life,</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 51. in this Text, <hi>I am the liuing bread which came downe from heaven,</hi> and ſo often in the verſes follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. That as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ſaid, that<note n="ſ" place="margin">Gen. 41.32.</note> 
                  <hi>the dreame was doubled vnto Pharao twiſe, becauſe the thing was eſtabliſhed by God, and God would ſhortly bring it to paſſe;</hi> ſo from this frequent repeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14451:19"/>we may conclude, that Chriſt indeed is the living bread, that he alone &amp; none other with him, none other beſides him is that bread. Yea, although he had ſaid but once, <hi>I am the liuing bread,</hi> this concluſion would be true. For no ſuch thing is ſaid of any other. Not of Cherubims, of Seraphims, of Thrones, of Dominions, of Principalities, of Powers, of Angels. Not of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> not of <hi>Peter,</hi> not of <hi>Paul,</hi> not of any other Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle. Not of any Martyr, not of any Saint. As when God ſaid to his people,<note n="t" place="margin">Pſal. 50.7.</note> 
                  <hi>I am God, euen thy God,</hi> the ſence is; I am God, and beſides me there is no other God: I am thy God, and thou haſt no other God but me. So when
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:14451:20"/>Chriſt ſaith, <hi>I am the living bread,</hi>
                  <note n="u" place="margin">Cyrill. in Ioh. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>34.</hi> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuum eſſe arbitror, non aliumpanem, neque aliud alimentum praeter filium dei rationa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libus intelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctualibuſque ſubſtantijs propoſitam eſſe: Ipſe eſt Manna verum: Ipſe inquam eſt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis de caeio qui omni rationali creaturae a Deo Patre prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betur.</note> 
                  <hi>it is manifeſt,</hi> ſaith <hi>Cyrillus, that no other bread, no other food, ſaue the Sonne of God, is appointed to reaſonable and intellectuall creatures: He is the true Manna: He is the bread from heaven, which God the Father giueth to all reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable creatures.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> WHAT? Can an argument framed from authoritie ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiuely be currant &amp; good? From the authoritie of men it cannot, becauſe neither doe they know all things, neither doe they ſpeake al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes according to their knowledge: From the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of God revealed in the Scripture it is good in all
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:14451:20"/>things belonging to ſaith and manners. Becauſe, as S.<note n="x" place="margin">Auguſt de Doctr. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiana. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>9.</hi> In ijs quae apertèin Scriptura poſita ſunt, inueniuntur illa omnia quae contine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t fidem moreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que viuendi.</note> 
                  <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith, <hi>in that which is clearly ſet downe in the Scripture, are to be found all theſe things which concerne faith and manners.</hi> This is manifeſt by theſe words of God to his people. <hi>Deut.</hi> 12.32. <hi>Whatſoever I command you obſerue to doe it: Thou ſhalt not adde thereto, nor diminiſh from it.</hi> Whatſoever things God commanded, thoſe <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> writ in a booke,<note n="y" place="margin">Deut. 31.24.</note> 
                  <hi>vntill they were finiſhed:</hi> And of that booke <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid,<note n="a" place="margin">Deut. 27.26. Gal. 3.10.</note> 
                  <hi>Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed is euery one that continueth not in all things which are written in the book of the Law to doe them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Vpon this ground God condemned whatſoever his people did vndertake be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:14451:21"/>his Word in things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to his ſervice: <hi>Dauid</hi> having a purpoſe to build an houſe to God, <hi>Nathan</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved it, but God ſaid vnto him,<note n="b" place="margin">1. Chron. 17.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Whereſoeuer I haue wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with all Iſrael, ſpake I a word to any of the Iudges of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, ſaying, Why haue yee not built me an houſe of Cedars?</hi> All things amongſt that peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were<note n="c" place="margin">1. Cor. 10.11. Heb. 10.1.</note> 
                  <hi>types</hi> and <hi>ſhadowes</hi> of good things to come. The Temple was to be<note n="d" place="margin">Ioh. 2.19.21.</note> a type of Chriſt, as<note n="e" place="margin">Heb. 9.11 12.</note> 
                  <hi>the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle</hi> was. Who then in the houſe of God was to be ſo bold as to eſtabliſh a figure of the things of God, a type of the Sonne of God, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſpeciall command and direction from God?</p>
               <p>When the people did ſet vp ſuch Will-worſhip, did
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:14451:21"/>not God hew it downe with this ſharpe and heavie Axe,<note n="f" place="margin">Eſa. 1.12.</note> 
                  <hi>Who hath required this at your hand?</hi> When the <hi>Iewes</hi> through a moſt fervent zeale vnto God built the high pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>Tophet,</hi> to offer vp their ſonnes and their daughters to God in a burnt ſacrifice, this was a good reaſon to God, why ſuch places ſhould be throwne downe, and that vnnaturall devotion aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, that<note n="g" place="margin">Iere. 7.31.</note> 
                  <hi>he commanded not any ſuch thing, neither came it into his heart.</hi> Commanded it not, I ſay, in the booke of the Law:<note n="h" place="margin">Hil. in Pſ. <hi>132.</hi> Quae in libro legis no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> continentur, ea nec noſſe debemus.</note> 
                  <hi>For the things which are not contained in the booke of the Law, we ſhould not ſo much as know them,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Hilarie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For this cauſe the Apoſtle after he had declared to the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:14451:22"/>Church<note n="i" place="margin">Act. 20.27</note> 
                  <hi>all the counſel of God,</hi> averred that<note n="k" place="margin">Act. 26.22</note> 
                  <hi>he had taught none other things then thoſe which the Prophets and Moſes did ſay ſhould come,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore condemned all<note n="l" place="margin">Col. 2.23.</note> 
                  <hi>Will-worſhip,</hi> though it had a faire ſhew <hi>of wiſdome and humility.</hi> Thus co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paring Chriſt with the Angels, he asketh,<note n="m" place="margin">Heb. 1.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Vnto which of the Angels ſaid he at any time, Thou art my Sonne, This day haue I begotten thee?</hi> And againe,<note place="margin">13.</note> 
                  <hi>To which of the Angels ſaid he at any time: Sit on my right hand, vntil I make thine enemies thy footſtoole?</hi> Reaſoning not onely <hi>affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiuely</hi> for Chriſt, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that he is the Sonne of God, and ſitteth at his right hand, becauſe the Scripture hath ſaid it; but alſo <hi>nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuely</hi> againſt the Angels, &amp;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:14451:22"/>proving that no ſuch glory belongeth vnto them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Scripture ſaith not any ſuch thing of them. This is a perpetuall &amp; moſt forcible manner of reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in all ſubſtantial points of Religion. God hath ſaid it in the Scriptures, therfore we muſt beleeue it: God hath ſpoken nothing of it: Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we ſhould not beleeue it.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="n" place="margin">Athanaſ. in epiſt. ad Marcellinum de interpret. Pſal. Divina Scriptura eſt magiſtra virtutis &amp; verae fidei.</note> 
                  <hi>The holy Scripture is the miſtreſſe of vertue, and of true faith,</hi> which are the ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall points of our Religion. For circumſtances of time, place, and perſons, haue all this generall rule:<note n="o" place="margin">1 Cor. 14.30.</note> 
                  <hi>Let all things be done decently and in order,</hi> the particulars where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of are committed to the wiſdome of the Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:14451:23"/>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> OBSERVE this well againſt Papiſts, who are now taught by Ieſuites to aske of you Doe ye not beleeue that Purgatorie is a fable, that the body of Chriſt is not in the Euchariſt, that the Maſſe is not a propitiatorie ſacrifice, that it is not lawfull to pray to the Saints which are in heaven, that the Pope is not the head of the Church, that there are but two Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts? If ye anſwer that ye beleeue ſo, they intangle you with new queſtions, asking where is it written; There is no Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorie, The Maſſe is not a propitiatorie ſacrifice, &amp;c? For the obiect of your faith is not the written Word of God: Neither doe ye, or ſhould ye beleeue that wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of God hath not ſpoken.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:14451:23"/>If then God hath not ſaid that there is no Purgatorie, how can yee ſay yee beleeue that there is none? So they fetter you with ſophiſticall interrogations, and make you to confeſſe againſt your owne profeſſion, that ye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue many things which are not written in the holy Scriptures.</p>
               <p>Therefore ye muſt anſwer farre other-wayes, and ſay, What God hath ſaid in the Scriptures, that I beleeue: What he hath not ſaid, that I beleeue not.<note n="p" place="margin">Orig in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa cap. <hi>8.</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mil. <hi>12.</hi> Non eſt verbum poſt verbum Moſi, poſt verbum Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetarum, multo magis poſt verbum Ieſu Chriſti, &amp; Apoſtolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum eius.</note> 
                  <hi>There is no word to be beleeved after the word of Moſes, after the word of the Prophets, much more af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the word of Ieſus Chriſt, and of his Apoſtles.</hi> God hath not ſaid, that there is no Purgatorie, that the Maſſe is
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:14451:24"/>a propitatorie ſacrifice, that the Pope is the head of the Church: Therefore I will not ſay, <hi>I beleeue ſuch things are not:</hi> But contrariwiſe, <hi>I doe not beleeue ſuch things are:</hi> For where God hath not a mouth to ſpeake, I haue not an eare to heare, nor a heart to beleeue, nor a tongue to confeſſe: What he hath not ſaid in things belonging to the ſaluation of my ſoule, my ſoule hath nothing to do with it.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IV"/> AS IN this matter which we haue in hand, I beleeue that Ieſus Chriſt <hi>is the living bread which came downe from heaven,</hi> becauſe the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſaith ſo: I beleeue not that the Saints are this bread, I beleeue not that they are the leaſt crumme of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:14451:24"/>it. For where the Scripture is dumbe, who ſhall accuſe me if I be deafe? Where there is no word, can I haue any faith, ſeeing<note n="q" place="margin">Rom. 10.17.</note> 
                  <hi>faith is by hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and hearing by the Word of God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As S. <hi>Iohn</hi> the Evangeliſt ſaid of S. <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptiſt,<note n="r" place="margin">Ioh. 1.8.</note> 
                  <hi>He was not that light, but was ſent to beare witneſſe of that light,</hi> and as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid of <hi>David,</hi> that<note n="ſ" place="margin">Act. 13.36</note> 
                  <hi>in his owne age he ſerved the will of God:</hi> So may we ſay of all the Saints that are now in heaven: They were not that bread, but they did eate of that bread: They were ſent to beare witneſſe of that bread, but they were no part of that bread. In their age they ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the counſell of God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving, preaching, confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:14451:25"/>that Chriſt Chriſt onely is the living bread. If any man aſcribe more vnto them then this,<note n="t" place="margin">Iren. lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>43.</hi>
                  </note> he bringeth ſtrange fire to the Altar of God, which God comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him not, and the fire of heaven ſhall devoure him, as it did<note n="u" place="margin">Leuit. 10.1.2.</note> 
                  <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu.</hi> And to ſuch a man yee muſt ſay with <hi>Tertullian,</hi>
                  <note n="x" place="margin">Tertull. de Carne Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti. cap. <hi>7.</hi> Non recipio quod extra Scripturam de tuo infers.</note> 
                  <hi>I receiue not that which thou bringeſt of thine owne invention beſides the Scripture.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yea as S. <hi>Iohn</hi> when he was in the world, being asked who he was, confeſſed, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,<note n="y" place="margin">Ioh. 1.20. Ioh. 3.28.</note> 
                  <hi>I am not the Chriſt, I am ſent before him:</hi> So the bleſſed ſoules which are now in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, if they were asked, Who they are, would anſwere, We are not the living bread, we are not Saviours: We are
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:14451:25"/>come after the Saviour, and are ſaved by him: And as S. <hi>Iohn</hi> to draw away mens eyes from gazing vpon him, pointed out <hi>Ieſus</hi> vnto them, and ſaid,<note n="a" place="margin">Ioh. 1.29.</note> 
                  <hi>Behold the Lambe of God which taketh away the ſin of the world:</hi> So they would point at Chriſt ſitting at the right hand of the Father, and ſay, Behold the living bread, Behold the Saviour of the world: And taking their harpes in their hands, would joyntly fall downe before the Lambe, and ſing to his glory the new ſong, which I exhort you all to ſing vnto him in your hearts for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of this firſt part of my Text,<note n="b" place="margin">Rev. 4.11.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou art worthy, O Lord, to receiue glory, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and power:</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Rev. 5.8.9.10.11.</note> 
                  <hi>For thou waſt ſlaine, and haſt redeemed
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:14451:26"/>vs to God by thy bloud out of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very kindred, and tongue, and people, and nation, and haſt made vs vnto our God Kings and Prieſts.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>THIRD CHAPTER.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>I.</hi> Bread in the Scripture hath divers ſignifications.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>II.</hi> In all theſe ſignifications Chriſt is our bread.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>III.</hi> Similitudes moſt frequent in the Scripture.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>IV.</hi> Chriſt did delight in ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litudes.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>V.</hi> The occaſion which moved him to call himſelfe Bread.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>VI.</hi> Exhortation to an earneſt deſire of this Bread.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> IT is then Chriſt Chriſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone to whom the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture beareth Record that he is <hi>the living bread:</hi> We are
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:14451:26"/>now to ſearch in the ſecond part of this Diſcourſe the cauſes why he called him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe <hi>bread:</hi> For in all Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phores which are Epitomes and Abridgements of Simi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litudes, we muſt not ſo much regard whence they are ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, (as thoſe doe which tie their eares to the leaues of the words) as dig with our minds into the root of the reaſon wherefore they are v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bread</hi> in the Scripture hath divers literall ſignifications. When <hi>David</hi> ſaith, that<note n="d" place="margin">Pſal. 104.14.15.</note> 
                  <hi>God bringeth forth bread out of the earth, and wine that maketh glad the heart of man,</hi> it is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in a vulgar ſence, which is common to all languages, &amp; ſo is it taken in the words of the inſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Lords
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:14451:27"/>Supper. Wherein it is ſaid, that<note n="e" place="margin">Mat. 26.26.</note> 
                  <hi>Ieſus tooke bread.</hi> When<note n="f" place="margin">2 King. 6.22.</note> 
                  <hi>Eliſha</hi> counſelled the King of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to <hi>ſet bread and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> before the Armie of the King of <hi>Syria, bread</hi> is taken for meate without drinke. When <hi>Iacob</hi> called his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren<note n="g" place="margin">Gen. 31.54.</note> 
                  <hi>to eate bread, and they did eat bread,</hi> he called them to a feaſt wherein there was both meate and drinke, and both are ſignified by the word <hi>Bread:</hi> When <hi>Salomon</hi> prayed to God<note n="h" place="margin">Pro. 30.8.</note> 
                  <hi>to feed him with bread convenient for him:</hi> When he ſaith, that<note n="i" place="margin">Pro. 31.14.</note> 
                  <hi>the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous woman, is like the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants ſhip, ſhee bringeth her bread from a farre off:</hi> When <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath taught vs to pray, <hi>Giue vs this day our daily bread,</hi> bread ſignifieth all things needfull for the ſuſtenance
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:14451:27"/>of this our mortall life.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> THAT which bread in all theſe literall ſences is to our bodies, the ſame in a ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſence is Ieſus Chriſt vnto our ſoules. The <hi>Iewes</hi> magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied much the <hi>Manna</hi> which <hi>Moſes</hi> gaue to their Fathers in the Deſert. But although it was bread, it was not drink vnto them, els they had not murmured for want of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. But Chriſt is both meate and drinke.<note n="k" place="margin">Ioh. 6.35.</note> 
                  <hi>I am,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>the bread of life: He that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to me ſhall never hunger.</hi> Ye ſee that he is meate: <hi>And he that beleeveth in me ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thirſt.</hi> Ye ſee alſo that he is drinke: He is bread both to be eaten &amp; to be drunke.</p>
               <p>The inhabitants of the <hi>Maldiuian Iſles,</hi> cracke much of a tree growing every
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:14451:28"/>where amongſt them, called<note n="l" place="margin">Theuet. Coſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mograph. <hi>12</hi> booke. chap. <hi>21.</hi> Gomarra. <hi>3.</hi> booke, chap. <hi>94.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Coco,</hi> the onely fruit wherof furniſhes vnto them bread, wine, oyle, vinegar, ſugar, butter, to feed them delici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, phyſicke to heale their diſeaſes, Hemp to make Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and Sayles for Shippes, Lint to make cloths to cover their nakedneſſe: And the tree it ſelfe hath all the vſes that any other tree can haue for fewell, or for tymber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worke.<note n="m" place="margin">
                     <hi>Peyrard</hi> in his naui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations 2. booke.</note> One who did liue many yeares in thoſe Iſles, writeth that he ſaw a Shippe of two hundreth tunnes, whereof all the tymber and nayles were of that tree, all the Cables and Sayles were of the outward skin of the fruit thereof, and the whole load was of the butter, ſugar, vinegar, wine, oyle, &amp; other
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:14451:28"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities which that fruit doth afford. And indeed it is a moſt wonderfull tree, but not to be matched with<note n="n" place="margin">Rev. 2.7.</note> 
                  <hi>the tree of life which is in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of the Paradiſe of God,</hi> with our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, who is all that &amp; more then all that to our ſoules: He is here in my. Text the whole and intire food of our hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry and dryed vp ſoules: He is not onely<note n="o" place="margin">Eſa. 53.5.</note> 
                  <hi>the Phyſick.</hi> out and<note n="p" place="margin">Eſa. 61.1 Mat. 9.12.</note> 
                  <hi>the Phyſition</hi> of our ſicke and languiſhing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences. He is<note n="q" place="margin">Rom. 13.14<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>the garment</hi> wherewith our nakedneſſe is covered, and our perſons are graced: He is<note n="r" place="margin">1. Cor. 31.11.</note> 
                  <hi>the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation</hi>
                  <note n="ſ" place="margin">Eph. 2.20.</note> 
                  <hi>and chiefe corner ſtone,</hi> wherevpon we are built. He is<note n="t" place="margin">Ion. 15.1.</note> 
                  <hi>the Vine</hi> whereof we are the branches:<note n="u" place="margin">Eph. 4.15.</note> 
                  <hi>The head</hi> wherof we are the members.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:14451:29"/>
                  <note n="x" place="margin">Oſe. 2.19. Eph. 5.25.</note> 
                  <hi>The husband</hi> who hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trothed vs:<note n="y" place="margin">Heb. 7.22</note> 
                  <hi>The ſuretie</hi> who hath anſwered for vs:<note n="a" place="margin">1 Tim. 2.6</note> 
                  <hi>The ranſom</hi> which hath redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vs:<note n="b" place="margin">Zach. 13.1</note> 
                  <hi>The water</hi> which cleanſeth and<note n="c" place="margin">Ioh. 4.10.</note> refreſheth vs:<note n="d" place="margin">Ioh. 1.9.</note> 
                  <hi>The true light,</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Mal. 4.1.</note> 
                  <hi>the Sunne of righteouſneſſe,</hi> which <hi>inligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teneth vs,</hi> and bringeth vnto vs <hi>healing in his wings.</hi> He is <hi>the Prophet</hi> who teacheth ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation: <hi>The high Prieſt</hi> which hath mented it: <hi>The King</hi> fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting at the right <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Father, who keepeth it in heaven, and will giue it vnto vs.</p>
               <p>In materiall things this is one thing, that is another: And ye ſeeke this thing in one place, that in another. In ſpirituall things it is not ſo: We haue all things in Chriſt, &amp; Chriſt is all things
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:14451:29"/>vnto vs:<note n="f" place="margin">Clemens Paedag. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>6.</hi> Cuſan. Exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat. lib. <hi>6.</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerm. Reſpice Domine.</note> 
                  <hi>Father, mother, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dagogue, health, peace, loue, the daily bread of the reaſonable ſoule, and all in all.</hi> In a word, he is ſalvation it ſelfe:<note n="g" place="margin">1 Cor. 1.30.</note> 
                  <hi>For of God he is made vnto vs wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and righteouſneſſe, and ſanctification, and redemption.</hi> For this cauſe he is called <hi>Bread.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> HERE ſome aske why Ieſus Chriſt did vſe ſuch Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphoricall words of <hi>bread,</hi> &amp; of <hi>eating,</hi> ſeeing he might haue ſaid in proper &amp; cleare tearmes, that<note n="h" place="margin">Heb. 5.9.</note> 
                  <hi>he is the author of eternall ſalvation vnto all them that obey him,</hi> as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle calleth him in the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to the <hi>Hebrewes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwere firſt, O man wilt thou teach the Word and Wiſdome of God to ſpeake?<note n="i" place="margin">Exod. 4.11</note> 
                  <hi>Who hath made mans mouth?
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:14451:30"/>Or who maketh the dumbe or deafe, the ſeeing or the blind? Is it not I, ſaith the Lord?</hi> And wilt thou, to render him like for like, make his mouth?</p>
               <p>Secondly, I ſay that of all words thoſe are moſt cleare and eaſie to be vnderſtood, which haue greateſt confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie with our affections &amp; deſires. For which cauſe <hi>God</hi> framing his ſtile to our capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, by ſimilitudes of world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things which are moſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed and affected of vs, leadeth vs from the lower parts of the earth far aboue all the viſible heavens, from carnall and ſenſuall imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations to ſpirituall and godly meditations, from the vaine co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceit which we haue of our owne worthineſſe, to bungring and thirſting after
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:14451:30"/>his righteouſneſſe? Neither did he fetch ſuch ſimilitudes from a farre off, but <hi>e re natâ,</hi> as his ſervants did light on ſuch or ſuch things, he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth alluſion vnto them, and by them inſtructeth his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the knowledge of the myſteries of the Kingdome of Heaven. Becauſe men priſe gold aboue all mettall, and value precious ſtones at an high rate, he ſaith that he<note n="k" place="margin">Efa. 54.11 Rev. 21.18.</note> 
                  <hi>will lay the foundations of his Church with precious ſtones, make her gates of pearles, her wals of iaſper, her ſtreets of pure gold.</hi> Becauſe the <hi>Iewes</hi> were much given to bodily exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, and to renting their clothes in the dayes of their faſting, he ſpeaketh vnto them of a ſpirituall faſting<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which he calleth<note n="l" place="margin">Eſa. 58.6.</note> 
                  <hi>the looſing
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:14451:31"/>of the bands of wickedneſſe,</hi> &amp;c. and<note n="m" place="margin">Ioel. 2.11</note> 
                  <hi>the renting their hearts.</hi> Becauſe alſo they were ever bragging that they were <hi>Iewes,</hi> and had <hi>the Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> the Apoſtle teacheth them that the true <hi>Iew</hi>
                  <note n="n" place="margin">Rom. 2.28.29.</note> 
                  <hi>whoſe praiſe is not of men, but of God, is one inwardly,</hi> that the true Circumciſion is <hi>that of the heart, in the Spirit,</hi> that all true Chriſtians<note n="o" place="margin">Phil. 3.3.</note> 
                  <hi>are the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IV"/> CHRIST, by whoſe Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit the Prophets and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles ſpake, did delight in ſuch ſimilitudes: He exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth thoſe which are addic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to gathering of periſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and momentarie trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures,<note n="p" place="margin">Mat. 6.22.</note> 
                  <hi>to lay vp for themſelues treaſures in heaven.</hi> To them w.<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> told him when he was preaching, that<note n="q" place="margin">Mat. 10.47.50.</note> 
                  <hi>his mother
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:14451:31"/>and brethren deſired to ſpeake with him,</hi> he anſwered, <hi>who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſhall doe the will of my Father which is in heaven, the ſame is my brother, and ſiſter, and mother:</hi> When <hi>the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of Samaria</hi> which was drawing water had ſaid vnto him,<note n="r" place="margin">Ioh. 4.9.10.14.</note> 
                  <hi>How is it, that thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Iew askeſt drinke of me which am a woman of Samaria?</hi> He tooke occaſion of her ſpeech to call his doctrine, his grace, his owne ſelfe, <hi>the living water, whereof whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver drinketh ſhall never thirſt:</hi> and by ſuch ſpeeches he brought her to the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all drinking of the water of grace, whereof the well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring is in heaven. When his Diſciples prayed him to take ſome meate, he refuſed ſaying,<note n="ſ" place="margin">Ioh. 4.34</note> 
                  <hi>My meate is to doe the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:14451:32"/>will of him that ſeni me, and to finiſh his worke.</hi> In the laſt day of the feaſt of Tabernacles, ſeeing the people very buſie about drawing of water, and powring of it out before the Lord, as if that had beene the principall part of Gods ſeruice, he ſtood, and cryed,<note n="t" place="margin">Ioh 7.37.38.39.</note> 
                  <hi>If any man thirſt, let him come to me, and drinke: He that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeveth in me, as the Scripture hath ſaid, out of his belly ſhall flow rivers of living water: This ſpake he of the Spirit which they that beleeue in him ſhould receiue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> AFTER the ſame manner, perceiving that thoſe fiue thouſand men which he had miraculouſly fed and filled with fiue loaues and two ſmall fiſhes, were come to make him a King, not for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:14451:32"/>true loue vnto him, but onely becauſe they had bin fed by him, and had concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved a new hope, that follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch a wonderfull King, meate ſhould never be wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to their bellies, yea that he would make bread to raine downe vpon them, as <hi>Moſes</hi> did vpon their fathers in the Wilderneſſe, he by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion ſpeaketh to them of a farre more excellent bread, which he would giue them; even of the true bread which came downe from heaven, and endureth vnto everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting life, &amp; exhorteth them to labour for it: Shewing in all the Chapter, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly in this verſe, that he is that bread, and that the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly meane to labour for it, is to beleeue in him.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:14451:33"/>
If he had clothed them miraculouſly, as miraculouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he had fed them, and if they had followed him ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon to make him King, he would vndoubtedly adviſed them to labour for the rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which wax never old, and ſaid that he is that rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. As indeed the holy Apoſtle will haue vs to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that Chriſt is our gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, when he ſaith, that<note n="u" place="margin">Gal. 3.27</note> 
                  <hi>as many as haue beene baptized into Chriſt, haue put on Chriſt,</hi> and exhorteth vs<note n="x" place="margin">Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 13<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 14</note> 
                  <hi>to put on the Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> Which no man that is not witleſſe or beſides himſelfe, will take literally, neither alſo any of the other ſimilitudes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of there is great plentie in the Scripture, and I haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated ſome few. Let then Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:14451:33"/>tell vs, Why the words of this Chapter ſhould be taken in a literall ſence, which they ſhall never be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to doe.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IV"/> BVT to leaue Papiſts, let vs, who are to communicate this morning to the bleſſed ſeales of this doctrine, weigh in our minds how Chriſt <hi>per allegoriam neceſſariorum pabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum,</hi> by the allegory of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary food, as<note n="y" place="margin">Tertull. de Reſurrect. Carnis. cap. <hi>37.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſpeaketh, withdraweth the thoughts of his followers from the outward to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man, from the fleſh to the Spirit, from the food of the body to the food of the ſoule,<note n="a" place="margin">Aug. in Ioh. tract. <hi>25.</hi> Ille poſt miraculi Sacramentum, &amp; ſermonem infert, vt ſi fieripoteſt qui pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti ſunt paſcantur, &amp; quorum ſatiauit panibus ventres, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiet &amp; ſermonibus mentes; ſed ſi capiunt: Et ſi non capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt, ſumatur quod non capiunt, ne fragmenta percant.</note> 
                  <hi>that, if it be poſsible, thoſe which are fed may be fed
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:14451:34"/>againe, and as he had filled their bellies with bread, he may alſo fill their minds with his ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: But if they take them: And if they take them not,</hi> as indeed they tooke them not, <hi>i.e.</hi> they vnderſtood them not, <hi>let vs take them, leaſt the fragments periſh,</hi> as we are exhorted by S. <hi>Auſtin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let vs, I ſay, now, even now ponder with our ſelues that although we doe eate and drinke to maintaine this mortall and ever-dying life, and that this is the end of meate and drinke; yet the preſerving of this life ſhould not be our principall care. Doe ye not all know,<note n="b" place="margin">1. Cor. 6.13.</note> that <hi>meates are for the belly, and the belly for meats, but God ſhall deſtroy both it, and them?</hi> And therefore ye ſhould all ſigh
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:14451:34"/>and groane for a better life, not of the body, but of the ſoule, not of this world, but of the world to come. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore liſten, I pray you, to the Sonne of God, who aſſureth you both by his word which now I preach vnto you, and by his Sacrament which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this Sermon ſhall be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven vnto you, that he is the bleſſed bread of that bleſſed life, for you, and vnto you. Come then, come to the Table of the Lord, thanking him that he vouchſafeth to be your bread, and crying vnto him with a more reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious and holy deſire then the <hi>Iewes</hi> did,<note n="c" place="margin">Ioh. 6.34.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord, ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more giue vs this bread.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:14451:35"/>
               <head>FOVRTH CHAPTER.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>I.</hi> The excellency of this bread, ſhewed by the Greek word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, which ſignifieth both living and quickening.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>II.</hi> And therefore is well tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated both wayes.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>III.</hi> Chriſt as he is Mediator is living in himſelfe, &amp; quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vnto vs.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>IV.</hi> This bread is wonderfull aboue all other bread.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>V.</hi> Exhortation to labour for this bread.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> THis, deſire will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, and like a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man with childe, we will more and more long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this bread, if we know more clearely and fully <hi>the excellent vertue and vſe</hi> of it, ſet down in the word <hi>living.</hi>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:14451:35"/>For Chriſt ſaith, <hi>I am the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving bread,</hi> according to our tranſlation: Or according to the Latin tranſlation of<note n="d" place="margin">Ego ſum panis vivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficus.</note> 
                  <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za,</hi> and<note n="e" place="margin">Ie ſuis le pain vivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiant.</note> the French tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>I am the quickning bread.</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Cotton an plagiaire de Geneue.</note> The <hi>Ieſuites</hi> of <hi>France</hi> barke moſt ſpightfully againſt this laſt tranſlation, ſaying that the Greeke word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in all Greeke Authors ſignifieth <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing,</hi> and is never taken from <hi>quickening.</hi> But as we ſay in a common Proverbe, <hi>The dog that barkes much, bites but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For to diſcover to you their impudency, both in affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming too boldly that which they know not, and in deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhameleſly that which they know. I. The Greeke word hath both ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the Septuagint Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:14451:36"/>whoſe words the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangeliſts and Apoſtles fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, when ye reade in the booke of the <hi>Pſalmes;</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 41.2. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>The Lord will keepe him aliue;</hi>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 119.50. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Thy word hath quickned me;</hi>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">Ver. 40.48</note> 
                  <hi>quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken me after thy loving kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; quicken me in thy righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe;</hi>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">Pſal. 134.11. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>quicken me, O Lord for thy Names ſake;</hi> and other ſuch like places, the Greeke word is the ſame which is in this Text.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The words preceeding and following doe ſhew that <hi>living</hi> ſignifieth <hi>quickening.</hi> In the 33. verſe he ſaith, <hi>The bread of God is he which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth downe from heaven, and giveth life vnto the world.</hi> In the 35 verſe he ſaith, <hi>I am the bread of life:</hi> He is ſo called, ſaith<note n="l" place="margin">Tolet. <hi>161.</hi> Dicitur panis vitae quia a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio viuere facit.</note> 
                  <hi>Tolet, becauſe he maketh others to liue.</hi> The words fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:14451:36"/>
                  <hi>He that commeth to me ſhall never hunger, and he that beleeveth in me ſhall neuer thirſt,</hi> are an evident proofe that it is ſo. In my Text he ſaith, <hi>I am the living bread which came down from heauen,</hi> and addeth in the ſecond part of the verſe, <hi>If any man eate of this bread he ſhall liue for ever,</hi> calling this bread, <hi>Living,</hi> becauſe it maketh them that eate it liue for ever. In the 57. verſe, He ſaith in the ſame ſence, <hi>He that eateth me, even he ſhall liue by me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Many Roman Doctors, <hi>Thomas Aquinas,</hi> and <hi>Ferus,</hi> two learned Monkes; <hi>Ianſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius, Emmanuel Sa, Maldonat, Tolet,</hi> Ieſuits, writ vpon this Text, that<note n="m" place="margin">Vivus pro vivificans.</note> 
                  <hi>Living</hi> is put for <hi>Quickening.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:14451:37"/>
4. But the Ieſuites now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes feare leaft Chriſt be called <hi>quickning</hi> in this verſe, becauſe they expound it, and all the verſes following of the bodily preſence of CHRIST in the Euchariſt, wherein they confeſſe that he is not quickning, ſeeing in the Sacrament not onely many wicked men, but alſo rats, mice, wormes, dogs, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, toads often eate him, and are not quickened by him. Which ſaying is a moſt hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible blaſphemy.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/>.WHAT then? Doe I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne our own tranſlation? God forbid: The Greeke word ſignifieth <hi>living:</hi> And is not Chriſt <hi>living?</hi> If he were not living how could he giue life?<note n="n" place="margin">Cuſan Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit. lib. <hi>5.</hi> ex Serm. Nou in ſolo pane vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit bomo. Panis qui no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vivit, non vivificat.</note> 
                  <hi>For the bread which liveth not, cannot giue
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:14451:37"/>life.</hi> Therefore our tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is good, and on it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendeth the truen of the French tranſlation, as the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect on the cauſe.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> And as the firſt excludeth not the laſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the firſt, is the cauſe is included in the effect, and the word <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving,</hi> ſignifieth both, and muſt ſignifie both, that the words of our.<note place="margin">1. 1 dol</note> Sariour may be found true. For what comfort ſhould it be vnto vs, that Chriſt liveth in vs, if he did not quicken vs? And this is the drift of this whole Chapter to ſhew, that he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth in all them that eate him, and giveth eternall life to all thoſe in whom he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth, leaſt we ſhould thinke him to be like vnto<note n="o" place="margin">Iudg. 14.8</note> 
                  <hi>the ſwarme of Bees,</hi> which did
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:14451:38"/>liue and make honey in the carkaſſe of the Lyon which <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>pſon</hi> had killed, but did not giue life to the Lyon.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> War doe we fight for a word, when no Chriſtian dare deny, but that Chriſt is both living and quickning? It is ſafer for vs to conſider <hi>how</hi> Chriſt is <hi>living,</hi> &amp; <hi>where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> he is ſo called. If ye con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider him as he is<note n="p" place="margin">Ioh. 1.1.4.</note> 
                  <hi>the Word which was in the beginning, i.e.</hi> as he is true God coeſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall and coeternall to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>in him was life:</hi> He was living <hi>formally.</hi> For in God to liue and to be, are one thing. But in this ſence we are all ſtrangers from God. For what communion can car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kaſſes dead in ſin, as we are all by nature, haue with God who liveth for ever &amp; ever?
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:14451:38"/>Therefore he ſpeaketh of himſelfe as he<note n="q" place="margin">Ioh. 6.27.5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>is the Sonne of man,</hi> that is to ſay, the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator between God &amp; man, (for ſo is the Mediator cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by<note n="r" place="margin">Dan. 7.13</note> 
                  <hi>Daniel</hi>) or as<note n="ſ" place="margin">1. Tim. 3.16.</note> 
                  <hi>God made manifeſt in the fleſh.</hi> For as he is <hi>the Sonne of man,</hi> or as he is Mediator between God and man, the Father hath given him to haue life in himſelfe, not to keepe it to himſelfe, but to communicate it to all the members of his myſtical body. This is cleare by his owne words in the fiſt chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of this Goſpel, where <hi>firſt</hi> he ſheweth that he giveth life, ſaying,<note n="t" place="margin">Ioh. 5.21.25.26.</note> 
                  <hi>As the Father raiſeth vp the dead and quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth them, even ſo the Sonne quickneth them whom he will.</hi> And again, <hi>Verily, verily I ſay vnto you, the houre is comming,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:14451:39"/>and now is, when the dead ſhall heare the voice of the Sonne of God, and they that heare it, ſhall liue.</hi> Secondly, he ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth this reaſon why he gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth life to the dead, <hi>For as the Father hath life in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, ſo hath he given to the Sonne to haue life in himſelfe.</hi> As <hi>the Sunne</hi> hath light, <hi>the fire</hi> heat, <hi>a Well-ſpring</hi> water in themſelues, not for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, but for the vſe of man and beaſt: So Chriſt hath life in himſelfe, that he may giue life vnto vs.</p>
               <p>For this cauſe he is called <hi>liuing,</hi> firſt <hi>ſubiectiuè,</hi> becauſe he hath life in himſelfe: Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, <hi>effectiuè,</hi> becauſe he hath it not for himſelfe, but giveth it to all thoſe that haue him, as S. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith,<note n="u" place="margin">1 Ioh. 5.12.</note> 
                  <hi>he that hath the Sonne, hath life.</hi>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:14451:39"/>Even as the ſcripture calleth<note n="x" place="margin">Gen. 26.19.</note> 
                  <hi>a Well of living water,</hi> that which having abundance of water in it ſelfe, ſprings, and flowes, and runnes, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parts it ſelfe vnto all.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IV"/> O MOST wonderfull and powerfull bread! No other bread hath life in it ſelfe: This hath: No other bread giveth life: This doth. No o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bread is a preſervatiue againſt death: This is: All other bread<note n="y" place="margin">Ioh. 6.27.</note> 
                  <hi>periſheth:</hi> This <hi>endureth vnto euer laſting life.</hi> Not only it liveth in it ſelfe, but alſo it maketh to liue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally the ſoules of all thoſe that eate it: and ſhall at the laſt day of the world quicken the bodies of all thoſe whoſe ſoules it hath quickened in this world, as he ſaith,<note n="a" place="margin">Ioh. 6.54.</note> 
                  <hi>Who ſo eateth my
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:14451:40"/>fleſh, and drinketh my bloud, hath eternall life, and I will raiſe him vp at the last day.</hi> His fleſh and his bloud, or rather he himſelfe by tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his fleſh and renting it from his ſoule, He by ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his bloud in his death is the living bread,<note n="b" place="margin">Cuſan. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit lib. <hi>4.</hi> ex Sermone. Qui mandu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat: Ipſe est qui eſt dator vitae &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervator: Quare eſt panis vitae.</note> 
                  <hi>giuer and keeper of life,</hi> and therefore moſt worthily called, <hi>the bread of life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>RIGHT HONORABLE, Reverend, Worſhipfull, and beloved Auditours, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, I pray you,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> the exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Saviour to the <hi>Iewes</hi> of <hi>Capernaum,</hi> and<note n="c" place="margin">Ioh. 6.27.</note> 
                  <hi>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour not for the meate which periſheth, but for that meate which endureth vnto everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting life.</hi> Alas! it is a pitifull ſpectacle to behold how men labour for the meate
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:14451:40"/>which periſheth,<note n="d" place="margin">Pſ. 127.2.</note> 
                  <hi>they riſe vp early, they ſit vp late, they eate the bread of ſorrowes:</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Matth. 15.17.</note> 
                  <hi>It entreth in at the mouth, it goeth into the belly, and is cast out into the draught.</hi> If men labour exceeding hard for ſuch bread, how ſhould we labour for this living bread? Not to purchaſe it: for it groweth not in the earth, it is not ſold in the Shambles, it is not to be bought in the Shops. But to reach vnto it, where it is: but to receiue it where and when it is offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. It is offered every where, in the towne, in the fields, in our houſes, in our cloſets: But namely in the Church when the Goſpell is prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, and particularly when the bleſſed Sacrament is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, as to you, this day.
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:14451:41"/>The preaching of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell is<note n="f" place="margin">Exod. 25.23.</note> 
                  <hi>the golden Table</hi> wherevpon <hi>this ſhew bread</hi> is ſet: This holy Sacrament is as it were<note n="g" place="margin">Ve. 29.30.</note> 
                  <hi>the golden diſh,</hi> wherein it is offered vnto vs. We know what we muſt doe to receiue the outward Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament,<note n="h" place="margin">Panem do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini.</note> 
                  <hi>the bread of the Lord:</hi> If we receiue it from the hand of the Miniſter: for he is no better then<note n="i" place="margin">Ioh. 6.32.</note> 
                  <hi>Moſes,</hi> who <hi>gaue not the true bread from heaven;</hi> When we haue received it, we eat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it, we let it downe into out ſtomacks, we diſgeſt it: Nothing is more eaſie. But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> receiue<note n="k" place="margin">Panem do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum.</note> 
                  <hi>the bread which is the Lord</hi> another worke more diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult is required:<note n="l" place="margin">Ioh. 6.29.</note> 
                  <hi>This is the worke of God, that ye beleeue in him whom he hath ſent.</hi> Your ſoules muſt goe vp to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:14451:41"/>There the Table is co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered: There is the bread which is the Lord ſet vpon the Table of the Mercie of God: There <hi>God the Father</hi> giveth it by his eternall will and decree: There <hi>the Sonne</hi> giveth it by his merite, and conſent: There <hi>the holy Ghoſt</hi> taketh it, as it were, in his hands, entreth with it into your hearts, and offereth it vnto your famiſhed ſoules: The Cherubims and Sera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phims ſtand by and wonder. Send your faith thither, and there your faith ſhall receiue it. This is the worke which God commandeth. 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.23. This is the worke which God himſelfe worketh in you. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.3. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.29. This is the worke, which if ye want, all your workes are
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:14451:42"/>ſinnes. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.23. and it is impoſſible that yee ſhould pleaſe God. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.6. Which if ye haue, by it Ieſus Chriſt will dwell in you. <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.17. and liue in you, and quicken you ſo ſenſibly, that ye ſhall ſay as truely, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid,<note n="m" place="margin">Gal. 2.20</note> 
                  <hi>I liue, yet not I, but Chriſt li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth in me.</hi> And this life of Chriſt, or Chriſt living in you, ſhall be ſo powerfull in you, that as<note n="n" place="margin">1. Kings 19.20.</note> 
                  <hi>Elijah</hi> by the ſtrength of that bread and of that water which the Angel of God prepared for him, went fortie dayes and fortie nights, without hunger, without thirſt, without wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſſe, till he came <hi>vnto Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reb the Mount of God.</hi> So by the vertue of <hi>this living bread,</hi> which no Angel of God, but<note n="o" place="margin">Luk 2.31.</note> 
                  <hi>God himſelfe hath
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:14451:42"/>prepared,</hi> ye ſhall walke cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragiouſly and conſtantly all the dayes of your life, till ye come to the kingdome of heaven, where ye ſhall<note n="p" place="margin">Mat. 8.11.</note> 
                  <hi>ſit downe with Abraham, and I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaac, and Iacob,</hi> and there be abundantly ſatisfied with theſe<note n="q" place="margin">Pſ. 16.11.</note> 
                  <hi>pleaſures which are at the right hand of God for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>FIFT CHAPTER.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>I.</hi> Chriſt came not downe from heaven as man.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>II.</hi> Neither as God by a locall motion.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>III.</hi> Neither as ſent and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved of God.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>IV.</hi> But as God incarnate.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>V.</hi> Three commings of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>VI.</hi> What ſhould be the order
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:14451:43"/>of our conceptions concerning Chriſt.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> WE HAVE, yet the laſt part of my text to conſider, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the cauſe of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of this bread: For ye may aſke how any bread can be ſo excellent, that it <hi>liveth,</hi> or ſo powerfull, that <hi>quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth.</hi> And certainely no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bread can: But this can, becauſe, <hi>it came downe from heaven:</hi> What is the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of theſe words? <hi>Valen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin</hi> ſaid that he brought his body from heaven: But that is falſe: For the Scripture bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth record that<note n="r" place="margin">Heb. 2.16.</note> 
                  <hi>he tooke on him the ſeed of Abraham,</hi>
                  <note n="ſ" place="margin">Rom. 1.3.</note> 
                  <hi>was made of the ſeed of David ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the fleſh,</hi> and<note n="t" place="margin">Luk. 1.27.35.</note> 
                  <hi>was borne of the Virgin Mary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:14451:43"/>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> IF any ſay that his divine nature came from heaven by a locall motion. That alſo is falſe:<note n="u" place="margin">Iere. 23.24.</note> 
                  <hi>Doe I not fill heauen and earth ſaith the Lord?</hi> He is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite, and without going, without comming, without alteration, without generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, without corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any motion whatſoever,<note n="x" place="margin">Auguſt ad Voluſian. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. <hi>3.</hi> Nouit vbi<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> totus eſſe, &amp; nullo contine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri loco: Nouit venire, no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedendo vbi erat: Nouit abire, non de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerendo quo venerat.</note> 
                  <hi>he filleth the whole world, not as the water, not as the aire, not as the light it ſelfe, as if with the leſſer part of himſelfe he did ſill the leſſer part of the world, and with the greater part of himſelfe, the greater part thereof. He can he all eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where, and contained no where: He can come, and not leaue the place wherein he was: He can goe away, and not leaue the place wherevnto he came.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:14451:44"/>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> IF WE ſay that <hi>he came downe from heaven,</hi> becauſe he was foreordeined, ſent, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed, approved, confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of God: So were all the Apoſtles: So are all the true Miniſters of God. Yet the Scripture ſaith not of any of them, that they are come downe from heaven. Chriſt ſaith, that<note n="y" place="margin">Mat. 21.25.</note> 
                  <hi>the Baptiſme of Iohn was from heaven.</hi> And S. <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith, that<note n="a" place="margin">Iam. 1.17.</note> 
                  <hi>every good gift, and every perfect gift is from aboue, and commeth down from the Father of lights.</hi> Yet S. <hi>Iohn</hi> comparing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with Chriſt, ſaith of himſelfe: <hi>He that is of the earth, is earthly, and ſpeaketh of the earth:</hi> But of Chriſt he ſaith excluſiuely to all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, <hi>He that commeth from heaven is aboue all.</hi> All Gods
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:14451:44"/>ſervants are borne on earth, and called from heaven, but they come not downe from heaven: They receiue from heaven, but from heaven they bring not the doctrine which they teach vs. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe all the gifts of God are created on earth by God who is in heaven. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore S. <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith, that they come from him: But they are not in heaven, nor elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, before God create them on earth. Whereas Chriſt was in heaven before he came downe from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, as he ſaid to his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,<note n="b" place="margin">Ioh. 6.62</note> 
                  <hi>What, and if ye ſhall ſee the Sonne of man aſcend vp where he was before?</hi> And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on earth he feared not to ſay to <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven then<note n="c" place="margin">Ioh. 3.16.</note> 
                  <hi>he was in heaven.</hi>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:14451:45"/>Which cannot be ſaid of the gift of God, which when they are come from heaven, and are on the earth, are not in heaven: Yea the Angels themſelues when they come from heaven vnto vs, are no more in heaven, till they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne vnto it againe.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IV"/> THIS then is a particular ſpeech, and a phraſe of the Scripture appropriated to God, who is ſaid <hi>to come downe from heaven,</hi> when he maketh himſelfe knowne vnto the world by ſome ſtrange and vnaccuſtomed worke, as<note n="d" place="margin">Serm. of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous mans e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, and of the Lords delivera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces. Serm. 9. Sect. 3. &amp;. 4.</note> I haue ſhewed elſe-where.</p>
               <p>And therefore when Chriſt ſaith that <hi>he is come downe from heaven,</hi> he will haue vs to vnderſtand and beleeue 1. that he is God. 2. that he
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:14451:45"/>hath made himſelfe mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt to the world by an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary worke, even the moſt wonderfull that ever was, or ever ſhall be in the world. He meaneth <hi>his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation,</hi> whereby<note n="e" place="margin">1 Tim. 3.16.</note> 
                  <hi>God was made manifeſt in the fleſh,</hi> not by converſion of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head into the manhood, or of the manhood into the Godhead, not alſo by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of the two natures in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one: But by that moſt wonderfull vnion, whereby<note n="f" place="margin">Paul. Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leienf. contra Felicem. l. <hi>1.</hi> Totus in ſuo, Totus in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtro: Idem in vtroque: Non alter in ſuo, alter in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtro.</note> 
                  <hi>remaining whole in that which is his, and whole in that which is ours, he is the ſame in both: Not another in that which is his, and another in that which is ours.</hi> And<note n="g" place="margin">Leo in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuit. domini. ſerm. <hi>2.</hi> De coeleſti ſede deſcendens, &amp; a paterna gloriano<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedens, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming downe from the heavenly ſeat, and not departing from the glory of his Father, being inuiſible in that
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:14451:46"/>which is his, was made viſible in that which is ours; the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible was compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended; he that was before all times tooke his being in time, the Lord of all tooke the forme of a ſervant, God impaſsible diſdained not to be a paſsible man, and the immortall to be ſubiect to the Lawes of death.</hi> This is his comming downe from heaven.<note n="h" place="margin">Bernard de Aduentu de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini ſerm. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Non venit qui aberat, ſed apparuit qui late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat;</hi> He was not abſent from vs before he came: But he was hid till then, and then he appeared.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> TO MAKE this more cleare, let vs either learne, or remember, that the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture maketh mention of three commings of Chriſt, the firſt is paſt: the ſecond is: the third ſhall be:<note place="margin">Venit.</note> 
                  <hi>His first
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:14451:46"/>comming</hi> was in the infirmity of the fleſh, wherein<note n="i" place="margin">Heb. 9.26.</note> 
                  <hi>once in the end of the world, he hath appeared to put away ſinne.</hi> Of this comming Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith, that<note n="k" place="margin">Ioh 13.3.</note> 
                  <hi>Ieſus knew that he was come from God, and went to God.</hi>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">Bernard de Coenâ domini ſerm. <hi>2.</hi> A de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> exiuit, non e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um deſerens; Et ad Deum vadit, non nos derelin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>He came from God,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard, not leaving him: And he goeth to God, not leaving vs.</hi> He came from God, when being the Sonne of God in heaven without a mother, he became the ſon of a woman on earth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Father: For his Father knew not a woman: and his mother knew not a man This is a moſt wonderfull comming. And the end of it was <hi>to take away ſinne,</hi> or as S. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſpeaketh,<note n="*" place="margin">1 Ioh 3.8.</note> 
                  <hi>For this purpoſe the Sonne of God was manifeſted, that he might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:14451:47"/>the workes of the Devill,</hi> and ſo redeeme vs: He went to God when triumphing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Divell, he carried his glorified body into heaven, and ſate on the right hand of God.</p>
               <p>When he ſaid to his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,<note place="margin">Venit.</note> that<note n="m" place="margin">Ioh. 16.5.</note> 
                  <hi>he was to goe his way to him that ſent him, ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row filled their heart:</hi> But he to comfort them ſaid,<note n="n" place="margin">Ioh. 14.18.</note> 
                  <hi>I will not leaue you orphanes; I will come to you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> Speaking of <hi>his ſecond comming</hi> by the holy Spirit into our hearts: The end of which comming is, to be vnto vs<note n="o" place="margin">Ioh. 16.13.</note> 
                  <hi>a Doctor</hi> to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct vs in his truth:<note n="p" place="margin">Rom. 8.14</note> 
                  <hi>A conductor</hi> to lead vs in his wayes:<note n="q" place="margin">Ioh. 14.16 17.</note> 
                  <hi>A comforter to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide with vs for ever,</hi> and comfort vs in all our trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:14451:47"/>
He ſpake of <hi>his third com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Venturus eſt.</note> when he ſaid to his Diſciples; <hi>I will goe and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare a place for you, and I will come againe, and receiue you vnto my ſelfe, that where I am, there ye may be alſo.</hi> The end of this comming ſhall be to ſaue and glorifie vs: For<note n="x" place="margin">Col. 3.3.</note> 
                  <hi>when Chriſt who is our life ſhall appeare, then ſhall we alſo appeare with him in glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VI"/> THIS Text is of his firſt comming, and of the end thereof: He came from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, when<note n="y" place="margin">Manſit quod erat, factus eſt quod none<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat, &amp; nunc eſt vtrum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>.</note> 
                  <hi>being ſtill that which he was, he became that which he was not, and now is both:</hi> Being God, he became man, and now is both God and man in one perſon: So ye haue the conſtitution of his perſon, neceſſary to the fulfilling of the worke for
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:14451:48"/>which he came. The end of his comming was <hi>to be liuing bread</hi> vnto vs, that is, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme and ſaue vs. Ye finde in his perſon all things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite to do that for which he came. He came to be <hi>bread:</hi> Bread he could not be but by his death: die he could not for man, if he had not beene a man. Therefore in that wherein he is equall vnto vs, <hi>he is bread.</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Gerhard. Lutphan. lib. de Reformat. virium ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae. cap. <hi>28.</hi>
                  </note> And this muſt be your firſt concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of him, when ye conſider thoſe good things which ye receiue by him, and which are all comprehended in this word <hi>Bread.</hi> The breaking of the bread in the Sacrament ſheweth vs, that he was bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in his death to be our bread: And therefore we muſt ſay: He who is our bread, <hi>is man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:14451:48"/>
The ſecond conception muſt be; that he is alſo <hi>God;</hi> for this bread is called <hi>liuing,</hi> &amp; who is <hi>liuing</hi> in the ſence which I haue explaned, but God? And therefore in that wherein he is equall vnto his Father, <hi>he is liuing,</hi> as he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſaith,<note n="b" place="margin">Ioh. 6.63.</note> 
                  <hi>It is the Spirit that quickeneth: The fleſh pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiteth nothing. The fleſh</hi> is his humane nature, wherein by death he is become our bread: <hi>The Spirit</hi> in his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine nature, which maketh his fleſh to liue, and which giveth a quickening vertue to this bread.</p>
               <p>The third conception muſt be this: The excellencie &amp; vertue of this bread flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth from the dignitie of his perſon: And therefore this man &amp; this God are in him
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:14451:49"/>one perſon: otherwiſe he could neither be <hi>bread</hi> to nouriſh vs, nor <hi>liuing</hi> to quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vs. As indeed he ſaith of himſelfe; not as of two, as <hi>Neſtorius</hi> dreamed, but as of one, <hi>Ioam the liuing bread, which came downe from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven:</hi> Hence it is that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever God did in Chriſt, we beleeue that the man did it, becauſe Chriſt is a man: And whatſoever the man did in Chriſt, we beleeue that God did it, becauſe Chriſt is God. Example. When Chriſt was on earth ſpeaking to <hi>Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demus</hi> as he was a man, he ſaid that even then<note n="c" place="margin">Ioh. 3.13.</note> 
                  <hi>he was in heaven,</hi> becauſe in him man is God. Againe, the Apoſtle ſaith, that<note n="d" place="margin">Act. 20.28</note> 
                  <hi>God hath purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Church with his owne blood:</hi> becauſe in Chriſt God
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:14451:49"/>is a man: Chriſt in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment leadeth you to this conſideration, when he ſaith, <hi>This is MY body, broken for you: This is MY blood ſhed for you:</hi> meaning that it is the body and blood of him who is God, and therefore it is no wonder if the body of God be bread, if the blood of God be drinke: If I ſay, the death of ſo wonderfull and ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent a perſon be your life.<note n="e" place="margin">Luk. 1.37.</note> 
                  <hi>For with God nothing ſhall be impoſsible.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>SIXT CHAPTER.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>I.</hi> Seeing Chriſt is God, we muſt ſtand in awe of him, and obey him.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>II.</hi> We ſhould be alwayes raui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in admiration with his comming downe from heaven.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb n="74" facs="tcp:14451:50"/>
                     <hi>III.</hi> His moſt wonderfull hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation ſhould be vnto vs a patterne of humilitie.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>IV.</hi> In his comming to be our bread, we ſhould acknowledge our owne indignitie.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>V.</hi> And nevertheleſſe accept with obedience of faith the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of his Table.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>VI.</hi> Exhortation, and Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> THIS Doctrine is fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile in inſtructions &amp; comforts, which may be taken ſome from the perſon of Chriſt, ſome from the end of his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming vnto vs. When we conſider that he which came downe from heaven is the true God, we muſt with<note n="f" place="margin">Eſa. 6.2.</note> 
                  <hi>the Seraphims,</hi> and with the man of GOD<note n="g" place="margin">1 Kings. 19.13.</note> 
                  <hi>Elijah</hi> cover our faces; ſtand
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:14451:50"/>as we do this day, before his Maieſtie with feare &amp; trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling; heare his Word with reverence, receiue the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which he offereth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs with humilitie and thankeſgiving, and ſhew a cheerefull and holy readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to doe with obedience whatſoever he commandeth vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> WHEN we heare that he who was<note n="h" place="margin">Heb. 7.26.</note> 
                  <hi>higher then the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens,</hi>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">Eph. 4.9.</note> 
                  <hi>deſcended into the lower parts of the earth,</hi> &amp; was there crudled like Cheeſe, clothed with skinne and fleſh, fenced with bones &amp; ſinewes: When we are taught, that he who<note n="k" place="margin">Phil. 2.6.7</note> 
                  <hi>being the Son of God, thought it no robbery to be equall with God,</hi> &amp; yet notwithſtanding <hi>made himſelfe of no reputation, and tooke vpon him the forme of
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:14451:51"/>a ſervant,</hi> how can we chuſe but wonder and be aſtonied at his humiliation, whereat the Angels themſelues are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed,<note n="l" place="margin">Ioh. 1.51.</note> 
                  <hi>euer aſcending &amp; deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending vpon the ſonne of man,</hi>
                  <note n="m" place="margin">1. Pet. 1.12.</note> ever deſiring to looke into this myſterie, which paſſeth all knowledge. Becauſe man in his pride<note n="n" place="margin">Gen. 3.5.22.</note> would needs be like vnto God, God to make amends for that fault, by a moſt wonderfull humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation would needs be like vnto man, yea<note n="o" place="margin">Pſal. 22.6.</note> 
                  <hi>be a worme &amp; no man, the reproach of men, and the deſpiſed of the people.</hi>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">Ioh. 13.6.8.</note> 
                  <hi>Peter</hi> was aſtonied when he ſaw Chriſt comming vnto him, with water in a Baſon, and kneeling at his feete to waſh them; The Creator to waſh the feet of his creature, the Lord of his ſervant, the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:14451:51"/>maſter of his diſciple, God of man, he that made all things of nothing the feete of a worme which he had made of clay. Haue we not greater matter of aſtoniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, when we heare and ſee that the ſame Creator of all things became a creature, he who is the eternall poſſeſſor &amp; ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of heaven &amp; earth, came downe from heaven and was made man on earth, that he might be the bread of man in heaven? O wonderfull loue! O ineſtimable bounty! O new, O never heard of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, O peerleſſe humilitie!</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> WHAT preſident, what patterne of humilitie can we find in heaven or in earth ſo perfect to follow, ſo worthy to be followed as this is? I cannot teach you any better
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:14451:52"/>preparatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to come this day to the Table of the LORD, then this is. O man, the Son of God deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded ſo low that he came down from heaven, and was made the Sonne of man for thee: And wilt thou who art nothing but the fonne of a man, or rather a man of ſin, wilt thou heape vp the ſumme of thy ſinnes by taking vnto thy ſelfe the wings of pride, to ſay with the King of <hi>Aſſur,</hi>
                  <note n="q" place="margin">Eſa. 14.13.14.</note> 
                  <hi>I will aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend into heaven, I will exalt my throne aboue the ſtarres of God, I will be like the moſt high?</hi> Of whom wilt thou learne humilitie, if thou refuſeſt to learne it of the author of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie? Theſe and many moe may be our meditatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s when we conſider the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of the perſon which
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:14451:52"/>is come downe from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IV"/> WHEN we call to minde the end of his comming; When we heare now that he is come from heaven to be our bread, to be the ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our ſoules: When that truth ſhall be confirmed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs in the Sacrament, if we be not more inſenſible then ſtones and rocks, we ſhall all acknowledge our great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignitie, all cry vnto God with <hi>David,</hi>
                  <note n="r" place="margin">Pſal. 144.3.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord, what is man, that thou takeſt knowledg of him? Or the ſonne of man that thou makeſt account of him?</hi> When King <hi>David</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Mephiboſheth</hi> to eat bread at his table continually, <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiboſheth</hi> bowed himſelfe, and ſaid,<note n="ſ" place="margin">2 Sam. 9.7.8.</note> 
                  <hi>What is thy ſervant, that thou ſhouldeſt looke vpon
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:14451:53"/>a dead dog, ſuch as I am?</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing his owne vnworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, although he was a Kings ſonne. How much more ſhould we<note n="t" place="margin">Eph. 2.3.</note> 
                  <hi>who are by nature the children of wrath,</hi> acknowledge our ſelues to be worſe then dead dogs, when the King of Kings not onely calleth vs to eat bread at his table, but alſo offereth himſelfe vnto vs to be our bread? Certainly we ſhould<note n="u" place="margin">Origin ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mil <hi>6.</hi> in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſos.</note> follow the laudable cuſtom of the auncient Church on the Communion day, and ſay vnto him, as the <hi>Centuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> did,<note n="x" place="margin">Mat. 8.8.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord, I am not worthy that thou ſhouldeſt come vnder my rooffe.</hi> Thus farre ſhould goe our humilitie.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> TRVE humilitie is the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of obedience; <hi>Behold,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>I ſtand at the doore,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:14451:53"/>and knocke;</hi>
                  <note n="y" place="margin">Rev. 3.20.</note> 
                  <hi>If any man heare my voice, and open the doore, I will come to him, &amp; ſup with him, and he with me.</hi> When he knocketh, ſhall I refuſe to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen vnto him, becauſe I am not worthy that he ſhould come vnto me.<note n="z" place="margin">Ioh. 1.11.</note> 
                  <hi>He came to his owne:</hi> That was mercie: For they were not worthy that he ſhould come vnto them. <hi>And his owne received him not:</hi> That was ſinne; As he ſaid,<note n="a" place="margin">Ioh. 15.22.</note> 
                  <hi>If I had not come, and ſpoken vnto them, they had not had ſinne: but now they haue no cloake for their ſinne.</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 22.1</note> 
                  <hi>The great King</hi> made the mariage of his Sonne, and ſent his ſervants to call them that were bidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the wedding: That was favour: <hi>And they would not come:</hi> That was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude: Therefore he was
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:14451:54"/>wroth againſt them, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiroyed them: But he gaue good intertainment <hi>to the poore, blind, maimed, halt</hi> that came. For although they were not worthy to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, he was worthy to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed. We we are to day thoſe ghefts, too too vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to ſit at his Table, and to eat of his Supper. But ſeeing he ſaith this day to my ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſoule, as he ſaid once to the Publicane and great ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,<note n="c" place="margin">Luk. 19.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Zacheus, To day I must abide at thy houſe;</hi> Ile make haſt, as <hi>Zacheus</hi> did: Ile leape downe from the Sycomore of pride: Ile run home with the ſeete of faith and of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, to prepare the lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of my ſoule for the Lord of glory: Ile receiue him ioyſully into the houſe
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:14451:54"/>of mine heart. And he will ſay to my ſoule, <hi>This day ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation is to come to this houſe.</hi> O eternall wiſedome of the Father, thou cryeſt vnto vs to day,<note n="d" place="margin">Pro. 9.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Come, eat of my bread, and drinke of the wine which I haue mingled:</hi> O glorious ſpoufe of the Church, thou vouch ſafeſt to be our<note n="e" place="margin">Cant. 5.1.</note> 
                  <hi>honey combe and our honey our wine, our milke,</hi> and our <hi>bread,</hi> and thou cryeſt againe vnto vs, <hi>Eate, O friends: drinke abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly, O beloved:</hi> In this bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Sacrament thou ſayeſt the third time;<note n="f" place="margin">Mat. 26.26.27.</note> 
                  <hi>Take, eate, This is my body: drinke ye all of it: This is my bloud.</hi> And ſhall we not obey thee? Shall we not follow the example of <hi>Mephiboſheth?</hi> Shall we not accept with reverence and thankeſgiving the honour
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:14451:55"/>of thy Table, and the benefit of thy meat? Papiſts call not this pride, it is humilitie: call it not preſumption: It is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VI"/> WE WHICH are invited to day to eate of this bread, know that to obey is a moſt acceptable ſacrifice to God, and therefore let vs try our ſelues, and come and eate. The ſcripture, as I haue ſaid, maketh mention of three commings of Chriſt. Of his comming <hi>in the fleſh, in the Spirit, and in glory. The first</hi> was <hi>viſible in infirmitie,</hi> as the Prophet ſaid,<note n="g" place="margin">Eſa. 53.2.</note> 
                  <hi>When we ſee him, there is no beautie that we ſhould deſire him. The ſecond</hi> is inviſible, but yet moſt ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible in the power of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit, crying in our harts<note n="h" place="margin">Rom. 8.15</note> 
                  <hi>Abba, Father:</hi> None ſeeth
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:14451:55"/>the Spirit in another: But e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very true Chriſtian feeleth it in himſelfe.<note n="i" place="margin">2 Cor. 13.5.</note> 
                  <hi>know ye not your owne ſelues,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>how that Ieſus Chriſt is in you, except ye be reprobates?</hi> And he ſaith, that<note n="k" place="margin">Rom. 8.9.</note> 
                  <hi>if any man haue not the Spirit of Chriſt, he is none of his,</hi> becauſe <hi>Chriſt is in vs</hi> by his Spirit. <hi>The third</hi> ſhall be viſible in Maieſtie, when<note n="l" place="margin">Eſa. 52.10</note> 
                  <hi>all the ends of the earth ſhall ſee the ſalvation of the Lord.</hi> In the firſt<note n="m" place="margin">Ioh. 1.11</note> 
                  <hi>he came vnto his owne, and his owne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived him not:</hi> In the ſecond he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth<note n="n" place="margin">Verſ. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>to them that loue him, and keepe his words.</hi> In the third<note n="o" place="margin">Heb 9.28</note> 
                  <hi>he ſhall appeare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them that looke for him vnto ſalvation,</hi>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">Bernard de Adnentu do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini ſerm. <hi>5.</hi> In primo Chriſtus fuit redemptio noſtra: In vltimo appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rebit vita noſtra: In iſto requies eſt &amp; conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latio noſtra.</note> 
                  <hi>In his firſt comming he was our redemption: In the ſecond he is our reſt and conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation: In the laſt he ſhall be our
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:14451:56"/>life.</hi> O then, O let vs thanke him for his firſt comming whereby he hath redeemed vs: Let vs examine our ſelues, if we loue him and keepe his words, that thereby we may be aſſured of his ſecond co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming into our hearts by his bleſſed and holy Spirit to comfort vs. And becauſe he is to come once againe vnto ſalvation<note n="q" place="margin">2 Tim. 4.8.</note> 
                  <hi>vnto all them that loue his appearing,</hi>
                  <note n="r" place="margin">Heb. 9.28.</note> 
                  <hi>and looke for him,</hi> let vs ioyne our ſelues with <hi>the Church</hi> and with <hi>the Spirit,</hi> and cry with heart &amp; mouth,<note n="ſ" place="margin">Rev. 22.17.20.</note> 
                  <hi>Come quickly: Even ſo, come Lord Ieſus.</hi> For then if we be found having the oyle of faith and charitie in our<note n="t" place="margin">Math. 25.10.</note> Lampes, we ſhall enter with the bridegroome to the mariage, and know by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience that which now we
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:14451:56"/>know by faith, that<note n="u" place="margin">Rev. 19.7.</note> 
                  <hi>bleſſed are they which are called vnto the mariage-ſupper of the Lambe. Theſe are the true ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of God;</hi> To whom with the Sonne &amp; the holy Ghoſt be all prayſe, all glory, and all honour both now and evermore.</p>
               <closer>AMEN.</closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:14451:57"/>
            <pb n="89" facs="tcp:14451:57"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE SECOND PART.</hi> OF THE EATERS, <hi>AND</hi> OF THE EATING OF THE LIVING BREAD.</head>
            <head type="sub">Preached at <hi>Otlans</hi> before the KINGS Maieſtie the twelfth of <hi>Iuly.</hi> 1625.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>IOHN VI.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="51">
                     <hi>51.</hi> If any man eate of this bread, he ſhall liue for ever.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>I.</hi> Chriſt nouriſheth not till he be eaten.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>II.</hi> Foure parts of this Text, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the eaters, the bread, the manner, and the fruit of the eating thereof.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S BREAD, or any other food, how neceſſary, how ſweet, how excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:14451:58"/>ſoever it be, is not vſefull for the preſervation of the life of man, till he eate it; E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſo Ieſus Chriſt, although he be <hi>the living bread which came downe from heaven,</hi> as he hath ſaid in the firſt part of this verſe; although he liue a celeſtiall and divine life, and<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 45.2.</note> 
                  <hi>be fairer then all the children of men,</hi> giveth not life vnto the dead, and preſerveth not the life which he hath give<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, till he be eaten, as he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe teacheth vs in this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond part of this verſe, <hi>If any man eate of this bread, he ſhall liue for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> WHERE he ſheweth. I. What perſons may eate of this bread, in theſe words, <hi>any man.</hi> 2. Which is the bread wherof they muſt eat, if they will eate to liue: Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:14451:58"/>it muſt be <hi>of this bread</hi> which is come downe from heaven. 3. What neceſſitie there is of this eating, and what is the manner thereof, to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered in the word, <hi>Eate.</hi> 4. The fruit which he that eateth of this bread ſhall reape thereby: <hi>he ſhall liue for ever:</hi> The ſence of theſe foure parts ioyned with the foure parts of the words go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before, is as if Chriſt had ſaid;<note n="b" place="margin">Tolet. in Loc. Si ergo panis ſum, manduca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ter, paſco: Si vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vue ſum, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam praeſto: ſi viuo vitam immortalem &amp; aternam ac coeleſtem, viuere alios facio ſimili vita: Et ideo ſi quis man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducat hunc panem, viuet in aternum.</note> 
                  <hi>If I be bread, I feed him that eateth: If I be living, I giue life: If I liue an immortall, eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, and celeſtiall life, I make others to liue the ſame life: And therefore if any man eate of this bread, he ſhall liue for ever.</hi> As many words, as many myſteries, which are able of themſelues to ſtirre vp your religious attention without
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:14451:59"/>further encouraging there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto from me.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>I.</hi> Chriſt is bread common to all.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>II.</hi> To Gentiles and to Iewes according to the Prophecies,</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>III.</hi> And types of the Law.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>IV.</hi> Fulfilled by the death of Chriſt, and the preaching of the Goſpell.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>V.</hi> Exhortation to thankeſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving for this benefit.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> TO ſpeake firſt of the Gueſts which may come and eat, ye may judge by theſe words of the Text, <hi>If any man,</hi> that this bread is not like vnto<note n="c" place="margin">Exod. 12.43.</note> 
                  <hi>the Paſſeover,</hi> whereof no for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reiner nor hired ſervant might eate: Neither is it like vnto<note n="d" place="margin">Exod. 29.33.</note> 
                  <hi>the Shew bread,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:14451:59"/>it was not lawfull for any to eate, but for the Prieſts.<note place="margin">Levit. 8.31.32. Levit. 24.9. Mat. 12.4.</note> As in it there is no leaven of ſinne, ſo is it like vnto<note n="e" place="margin">Exod. 12.19.</note> 
                  <hi>the vnleavened bread</hi> of the <hi>Paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over,</hi> whereof the ſtranger did cate, as well as he that was borne in the Land. As it came downe from the third heaven, ſo is it like vnto <hi>the Manna</hi> which rained from the firſt heaven, and was<note n="f" place="margin">Exod. 16.16. Num. 12.4.</note> meat, not onely to the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but alſo <hi>to the mixed multitude</hi> which came out of <hi>Egypt</hi> with them: For <hi>any man</hi> may eate of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> FIRST <hi>any man</hi> without exception of Nation: Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly <hi>any man</hi> without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of any perſon in any Nation. <hi>The Prophets</hi> did foretell, <hi>The Types</hi> did figure, Ieſus Chriſt did affirme it
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:14451:60"/>ſhould be ſo: The calling of the Gentiles ever ſince the dayes of the Apoſtles ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that it is ſo.<note n="g" place="margin">Act. 10.43</note> 
                  <hi>All the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi> ſaith <hi>Peter, giue witneſſe vnto Chriſt, that through his Name whoſoever beleeveth in him ſhall receiue remiſsion of ſinnes.</hi> Did not God ſay to <hi>Eue,</hi> who is the mother of all living, that<note n="h" place="margin">Gen. 3.15</note> 
                  <hi>her ſeed ſhould bruiſe the head of the Serpent?</hi> Did not <hi>Noah</hi> prophecie, that<note n="i" place="margin">Gen. 9.27.</note> 
                  <hi>God ſhould enlarge (or perſwade) Iaphet, and that he ſhould dwell in the tents of Sem?</hi> Did not God promiſe to <hi>Abraham,</hi> that<note n="k" place="margin">Gen. 22.18.</note> 
                  <hi>in his feed all the<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Nations of the earth ſhould be bleſſed?</hi> He ſaith not<note n="l" place="margin">Gal. 3.16.</note> 
                  <hi>in his ſeeds, as of many, but as of one; And to thy ſeed which is Chriſt.</hi> Did not <hi>Iacob</hi> fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell, that<note n="m" place="margin">Gen. 49.60.</note> 
                  <hi>vnto Shilo ſhould
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:14451:60"/>be the gathering of the people?</hi> Did not <hi>Moſes</hi> forewarne the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> that becauſe<note n="n" place="margin">Deut. 32.21.</note> 
                  <hi>they had moved God to iealouſie with that which is not God, and provoked him to anger with their vanities, he would moue them to iealouſie with thoſe which are not people, and provoke them to anger with a fooliſh Nation.</hi> Was not that<note n="o" place="margin">Rom. 10.19.</note> Prophecie fulfilled in the Apoſtles dayes? When the Apoſtle ſaid to the <hi>Iewes</hi> at <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> that<note n="p" place="margin">Act. 22.21.22.23.</note> 
                  <hi>he was to goe vnto the Gentiles, they lift vp their voices, caſt off their clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes, threw duſt in the aire, and cryd, Away with ſuch a fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low from the earth: for it is not fit that he ſhould liue.</hi> When the <hi>Iewes</hi> of <hi>Antiochia</hi> ſaw that he preached the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell to the Gentiles,<note n="q" place="margin">Act. 13.45.</note> 
                  <hi>they
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:14451:61"/>were filled with envie.</hi> It was to the <hi>Meſsias</hi> that God ſaid by <hi>David,</hi>
                  <note n="r" place="margin">Pſal. 2.8.</note> 
                  <hi>Aske of me, and I ſhall giue thee the Heathen for thine inheritance, and the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt parts of the earth for thy poſſeſsion.</hi> It was to him alſo that he ſaid by <hi>Eſaiah;</hi>
                  <note n="ſ" place="margin">Eſa. 49.6.</note> 
                  <hi>It is a light thing that thou ſhouldeſt be my ſervant to raiſe vp the tribes of Iacob, and to reſtore the preſerued of Iſrael: I will alſo giue thee for a light to the Gentiles, that thou mayeſt be my ſalvation, vnto the end of the earth:</hi> Which words when the Apoſtle alledged to the Gentiles of <hi>Antiochia;</hi>
                  <note n="t" place="margin">Act. 13.48</note> 
                  <hi>they were glad, and glorified the word of the Lord, and as many as were ordeined to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life, beleeued:</hi> It was of the Gentiles that God ſaid;<note n="u" place="margin">Eſa. 65.1.</note> 
                  <hi>I am ſought of them that as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:14451:61"/>not for me: I am found of them that ſought me not: I ſaid vnto a nation that was not cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by my Name, Behold me, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold me.</hi> For ſo is this paſſage applyed by the<note n="x" place="margin">Rom. 10.20.</note> Apoſtle, and muſt be expounded ſo. Of them alſo God ſaid by <hi>Hoſea,</hi>
                  <note n="y" place="margin">Hoſ. 2.23.</note> 
                  <hi>I will haue mercy vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he that had not obtained mercy, and I will ſay to them which were not my people, Thou art my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and they ſhall ſay, Thou art my God.</hi> This paſſage is ſo formall and cleare, that by it both S.<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 9.26</note> 
                  <hi>Paul</hi> and S.<note n="b" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.10.</note> 
                  <hi>Peter</hi> proved the calling of the Gentiles, including them in the new covenant, and not excluding the Iewes,<note n="c" place="margin">Act. 13.48.</note> who were firſt called, and when<note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 11.25.</note> 
                  <hi>the fulneſſe of the Gentiles ſhall come in,</hi> ſhall be called a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and ſaved with vs, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:14451:62"/>to the Prophecie;<note n="e" place="margin">Eſa. 57.19.</note> 
                  <hi>Peace, peace to him that is far off, and to him that is neere, ſaith the Lord, and I will heale him,</hi> that is to ſay, according to the interpretation of the Apoſtle, peace to the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, which<note n="f" place="margin">Eph. 2.12.17.</note> 
                  <hi>were ſtrangers from the Couenants of promiſe, hauing no hope, and being with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out God in the world, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore were farre off:</hi> and peace to the <hi>Iewes</hi> which had the Covenants of promiſe, and in that reſpect had<note n="g" place="margin">Deut. 4.7.</note> 
                  <hi>God nigh vnto them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> THE one and the other was figured by the burnt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings,<note n="h" place="margin">Levit. 11.11.</note> 
                  <hi>the blood wherof was ſprinckled round about vpon the Altar;</hi> to teach the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that the bloud of the <hi>Meſsias</hi> was to be ſhed for the elect which dwell every
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:14451:62"/>where vpon the globe of the earth. As when the high Prieſt did<note n="i" place="margin">Exod. 20.24. Levit. 7.34. Levit. 10.14</note> 
                  <hi>waue the waue offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring,</hi> and ſhake it to and fro; and<note n="k" place="margin">Exod. 29.27.</note> 
                  <hi>heaue vp the heaue offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring,</hi> he figured that which Chriſt ſaid, that<note n="l" place="margin">Ioh. 12.32 33.</note> 
                  <hi>if he were lifted vp, he would draw all men vnto him: This he ſaid, ſignifying what death he ſhould die.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IV"/> WHATSOEVER was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecied and figured, hath beene punctually fulfilled. Chriſt commanded his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles<note n="m" place="margin">Mat. 28.19.</note> 
                  <hi>to teach all Nations:</hi> What he commanded they did: At his death<note n="n" place="margin">Mat. 27.51.</note> 
                  <hi>the vaile of the Temple was rent in twaine from the top to the bottome,</hi> to ſignifie that by the power of his death<note n="o" place="margin">Eph. 2.14.</note> 
                  <hi>the middle wall of partition betweene vs</hi> and the <hi>Iewes is broken downe, the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:14451:63"/>is aboliſhed, and of twain we are made in him one new man.</hi> Now the<note n="p" place="margin">Rom. 1.16.</note> 
                  <hi>Goſpell is the power of God to ſaluation to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one that beleeueth, to the Iew and to the Greeke.</hi> Now, according to the prediction of Chriſt,<note n="q" place="margin">Mat. 8.11</note> 
                  <hi>many come from the Eaſt and Weſt, &amp; ſit downe with Abraham, and Iſaac, and Iacob in the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> and theſe many are.<note n="r" place="margin">Rev. 7.4.9.</note> 
                  <hi>of all Nations, and kindred, and people, and tongues,</hi> as well as of <hi>Iewes.</hi> Now<note n="ſ" place="margin">Math. 15.26.27.</note> 
                  <hi>the dogs</hi> doe no more eate the ſcraps of the childrens bread, which fall from their Maiſters Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: But by a moſt mercifull wonder are of dogs made the children of God, and ſit with him at his Table. The <hi>Iewes</hi> were firſt called to this glorious feaſt Vpon their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſall
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:14451:63"/>
                  <note n="t" place="margin">Luk. 14.21.</note> 
                  <hi>the poore, the maimed, the halt, the blind</hi> are brought in: This was and is to the <hi>Iewes</hi> a heart-breaking ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row: S<note n="u" place="margin">Act. 10.28</note> 
                  <hi>Peter</hi> himſelfe at the firſt repined againſt it:<note n="x" place="margin">Act. 11.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.2.18.</note> The reſt of <hi>the Apoſtles, &amp; the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren that were in Iudea con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with Peter</hi> about it, and when they were better informed, they ſpake of it as of a great wonder. S. <hi>Paul</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth it<note n="y" place="margin">Rom. 16.25.26.</note> 
                  <hi>a myſterie which was kept ſecret ſince the world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan:</hi> for although that <hi>now by the Scriptures of the Prophets it is made knowne to all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> yet the manner thereof, that<note n="a" place="margin">Eph. 3.3.5.6.</note> 
                  <hi>the Gentiles ſhould be fellow-heires, and of the ſame body, and partakers of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of God in Chriſt by the Goſpell,</hi> not by the Law; by faith, not by Circumciſion,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:14451:64"/>without any obſervation of Iudaicall feaſts,<note place="margin">Ambroſ. ib.</note> faſts, abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nences, dayes, and other ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Iewiſh diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, was not revealed to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Prophets, <hi>was not made knowne in other ages to the ſonnes of men,</hi> was firſt <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed vnto the Apoſtles and Prophets</hi> of their time <hi>by the Spirit.</hi> Now our little chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ſee it and know it more clearly then <hi>Abraham</hi> the Father of the beleevers, then <hi>Dauid</hi> who ſpake ſo much of it, then all the Prophets did.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> THAT which was to the <hi>Iewes</hi> a heart-ſorrow, to the Prophets a booke ſealed, to the Apoſtles a myſterie, to the firſt Chriſtians of <hi>Iudea</hi> a wonder, is to vs our ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Shall it not alſo be our
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:14451:64"/>ioy, and the matter of our tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kſgiving?<note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 9.23.24.</note> 
                  <hi>God hath made knowne the riches of his glory on the veſſels of mercy, which he afore had prepared vnto glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: Even vs whom he hath cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, not of the Iewes onely, but alſo of the Gentiles.</hi> And ſhall not we hearken to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Apoſtle, and<note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 15.9.11. Pſal. 117.</note> 
                  <hi>glorifie God for his mercy?</hi> As it is written, <hi>O prayſe the Lord, all ye Nations: Praiſe him all ye people: For his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful kindneſſe is great toward vs: and the truth of the Lord endureth for ever.</hi> When Chriſt was borne <hi>in Bethle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hem,</hi> which is interpreted <hi>the houſe of bread,</hi> to be the living bread to the dead, the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels of heaven who for their owne particular had no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in his birth, ioyned
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:14451:65"/>themſelues in a great hoſt to praiſe God, ſaying and ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,<note n="d" place="margin">Luk. 2.14.</note> 
                  <hi>Glory to God in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, and on earth peace, good will towards men:</hi> And ſhall not we who are theſe men for whom he is come, we who feede every day on him, ſing prayſe glory, and honour to God who hath ſent him to be our bread, and hath cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vs to eate of this bread? Shall we not ſay and ſing with <hi>Dauid,</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Pſa. 18.49.</note> 
                  <hi>Therefore will I giue thanks vnto thee, O Lord, among the Heathen, and ſing prayſes vnto thy Name.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>I.</hi> All kinde of perſons in any Nation may eate of the living bread, according to the Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and types of the Law.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="105" facs="tcp:14451:65"/>
                     <hi>II.</hi> And the doctrine of the Goſpell.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>III.</hi> Three vſes of this doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/>
                  <hi>IS</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Rom: 3.29</note> 
                  <hi>GOD the God of the Iewes onely? Is he not alſo of the Gentiles? Yea of the Gentiles alſo,</hi> and of <hi>any man</hi> amongſt Iewes and Gentiles without diſtinction of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; According to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie of <hi>Eſaiah,</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">Eſa. 60.3.</note> 
                  <hi>The Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles ſhall come to thy light, and Kings to the brightneſſe of thy riſing.</hi> Not Kings onely, but Kings aſwell as men of mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſort: but men of meane condition, aſwell as Kings:<note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 22.26.29.</note> 
                  <hi>The meeke ſhall eate, and be ſatisfied: All they that be fat vpon earth ſhall eate and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</hi> Vnder the Law there were ſacrifices not onely for
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:14451:66"/>but alſo for poore men. He which had not<note n="l" place="margin">Levit. 1.3.10.14.</note> 
                  <hi>a bullocke</hi> of the heard to offer, came with <hi>a Lambe or a kid</hi> of the flocke, and was accepted. And<note n="m" place="margin">Levit. 12.6.8.</note> 
                  <hi>the woman</hi> which after her purificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was not able to bring a Lambe and a Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon for her oblation, was quit for <hi>two turtles, or two yong pigeons.</hi> For Chriſt is a propitiatorie Sacrifice for rich and poore, men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men: And as all perſons of all qualities, which were bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with the fierie Serpents in the wilderneſſe, were hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, when they looked vpon the Serpent of braſſe which <hi>Moſes</hi> had ſet vpon a pole, according to the Word of God,<note n="n" place="margin">Num. 21.8.</note> 
                  <hi>Euery one that is bitten, when he looketh vpon it, ſhall line.</hi>
                  <note n="o" place="margin">Ioh. 3.14 15.</note> 
                  <hi>Even ſo,</hi> ſaid Chriſt of
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:14451:66"/>himſelfe, <hi>muſt the Sonne of man he lifted vp, that whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver beleeveth in him, ſhould not periſh, but haue eternall life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> THE graces of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to this life are diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently and in ſeverall faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons diſtributed vnto men: to ſome in a leſſer, to ſome in a greater ſcantling: Some haue one thing, ſome haue ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Great is the glory of the King: That glory doth not belong to any of his Subiects: Some are rich, moe are poore: ſome learned, moe ignorant: ſome honourable, a great deale moe are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out honour. God will haue it to be ſo, and it is neceſſary that it ſhould be ſo, for the preſervation of the ſocietie of mankinde. It is not ſo in
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:14451:67"/>ſpirituall graces which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to ſalvation. For as the Sunne, the Moone, the ſtars, the fire, the aire, the water, the earth, which are the moſt vſefull creatures of God, are common to all, yong and old, men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Subiects and Kings, poore and rich, wiſe and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant: ſo Gods ſaving gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are enioyed in common of all his elect. For<note n="p" place="margin">1 Tim. 2.4</note> 
                  <hi>God will haue all men to be ſaved, and to come to the knowledge of the truth,</hi> that is, men of all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions and qualities; Kings, Governours, &amp; men of note, as well as other men. Not rich men only. For<note n="q" place="margin">Mat. 11.5</note> 
                  <hi>the poore haue the Goſpell preached to them:</hi> Not men by age only: For Chriſt ſaid,<note n="r" place="margin">Mat. 19.14.</note> 
                  <hi>Suffer little children, and forbid them not
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:14451:67"/>to come vnto me: For of ſuch is the kingdome of heaven.</hi> Not men only as oppoſed to wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. For S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith of women, that<note n="ſ" place="margin">1 Pet. 3.7.</note> 
                  <hi>they are heires together of the grace of life:</hi> And of all conditions <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſaith,<note n="t" place="margin">Gal. 3.28. Col. 3.11.</note> that <hi>there is neither Iew nor Greek there is neither Circumciſion nor vncircumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, there is neither bond nor free, there is neither male nor female, but we are all one in Chriſt Ieſus.</hi> All are baptized with one and the ſame wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: All heare the ſame word: All in the Lords Supper are partakers of one bread, and drinke of one cup; and when our night ſhall come, we ſhall all receiue one penny of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life.<note n="u" place="margin">Act. 10.34.35.</note> 
                  <hi>For God is no reſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of perſons, but in every Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he that feareth him, and
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:14451:68"/>worketh righteouſneſs is accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> WHEREFORE let not the great ones deſpiſe the little ones:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Vſe.</hi>
                  </note> They haue nothing more: Let not the little ones repine at the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of the great ones: They haue nothing leſſe. We are all<note n="x" place="margin">Eph. 2.19</note> 
                  <hi>fellow-Citizens with the Saints, and of the houſhold of God:</hi> We are all<note n="ſ" place="margin">Rom. 8.17</note> 
                  <hi>heires of God, and ioynt-heires with Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let vs all rather ſeeke the converſion of thoſe which as yet come not to one table with vs.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Vſe.</hi>
                  </note> For<note n="t" place="margin">Iam. 5.20.</note> 
                  <hi>he that conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth a ſinner from the errour of his way, ſhall ſaue a ſoule from death, and ſhall hide a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of ſinnes.</hi> And when God hath opened the eyes of any one, and turned him from
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:14451:68"/>darkneſſe to light, let vs giue thanks for him,<note n="u" place="margin">Gal. 1.22.23.24.</note> 
                  <hi>as the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Iudea, which were in Chriſt, glorified God in Paul, when they heard that he prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched the faith, which once he had deſtroyed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And looking for a bleſſing vpon our godly endevours &amp; carefull labours that way,<note place="margin">3. <hi>Vſe.</hi>
                  </note> let vs in the meane time bow the knees of our hearts, and open our mouthes with thankſgiving to the heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father,<note n="x" place="margin">Col. 1.12.13.</note> 
                  <hi>who hath made vs meete to be partakers of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the Saints in light, hath delivered vs from the power of darkeneſſe, hath tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated vs into the kingdome of his deare Sonne,</hi> &amp; there hath covered the Table vnto vs, that there we may eate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually of <hi>this bread.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:14451:69"/>
               <head>CHAPTER IV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>I.</hi> Chriſt is the bread whereof we muſt eate.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>II.</hi> As he is God and man in one perſon.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>III.</hi> In this ſence S. Cyrillus ſaith that we are vnited with Chriſt corporally and ſpiritual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>IV.</hi> Our vnion with him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth by his manhood.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> WHAT this bread is, Chriſt hath ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the firſt part of this Verſe, ſaying, <hi>I am the liuing bread which came down from heaven,</hi> wherevnto he addeth in this ſecond part of the Verſe, <hi>If any man eate of this bread,</hi> ſpeaking ſtill of himſelfe. And therfore<note n="y" place="margin">Eraſ. in Loc. Hunc lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum veteres interpretan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur de doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na coeleſti.</note> 
                  <hi>this bread</hi> is not <hi>this doctrine,</hi> as <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſmus</hi>
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:14451:69"/>ſaith, although he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the authoritie of the Fathers: Why Chriſt is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>bread,</hi> Why <hi>living,</hi> how it is ſaid that <hi>he came downe from heauen,</hi> I declared in the expoſition of theſe words; yet not ſo fully, but that I left a gleaning for this place.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> SEING Chriſt ſpeaketh of the eating <hi>of this bread,</hi> we muſt exactly diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <hi>the obiect</hi> of our ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and <hi>the action</hi> whereby we eate. For nature it ſelfe teacheth vs that <hi>bread</hi> is one thing, and <hi>to eate</hi> is another: <hi>Bread</hi> is a bodily ſubſtance out of vs. <hi>To eate</hi> is an action of ours, whereby <hi>bread</hi> is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed vnto vs, and changed into our ſubſtance. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we muſt firſt know <hi>what,</hi> and next <hi>how</hi> we muſt eate.
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:14451:70"/>That which we muſt care, is <hi>this bread:</hi> It is Chriſt as he is God and man: Not as he is <hi>God onely:</hi> For ſo he is not <hi>bread:</hi> But is ſo farre from vs, that we cannot come neere him. Not alſo as he <hi>is man onely:</hi> For ſo he is not <hi>living.</hi> Saith he not, that it is<note n="a" place="margin">Ioh. 6.63.</note> 
                  <hi>the Spirit that quickneth, the fleſh profiteth nothing?</hi> It is his Godhead, called <hi>the Spirit,</hi> which quickneth his man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and maketh it quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vnto vs. For<note n="b" place="margin">Heb. 9.14.</note> 
                  <hi>through the eternall Spirit, he offered himſelfe without ſpot to God:</hi> And<note n="c" place="margin">1 Pet. 3.18.</note> 
                  <hi>being put to death in the fleſh, he was quickened by the Spirit,</hi> and ſo was enabled to quicken vs.<note place="margin">Similitude</note> As wood in it ſelfe is not able to warme vs: But if fire come vnto it, it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth heat in it ſelfe, and
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:14451:70"/>by that heat warmeth all thoſe that come neere vnto it. Even ſo the manhood of Chriſt hath no quickning life of its owne ſelfe, but by the vertue of the Godhead vnited vnto it, it is able to quicken all the men of the world, if they did come neere vnto it.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> THIS was the meaning of S. <hi>Cyrillus,</hi> when diſputing againſt <hi>Neſtorius</hi> who divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Chriſt, he ſaid y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we are vnited vnto Chriſt<note n="d" place="margin">Cyrill. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſ Neſtor. lib. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>divinely and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manely:</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Idem in Ioh lib. <hi>11.</hi> cap. <hi>27.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>corporally and ſpiritual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> that is to ſay, according to his own interpretatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which <hi>Papiſts</hi> haue omitted in their tranſlations, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>intirely.</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: And <hi>corporally as he is MAN:</hi>
                  <pb n="116" facs="tcp:14451:71"/>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Spiritually alſo as he is GOD.</hi> This is worthy to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved againſt Papiſts, which will haue the words <hi>corporal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Spiritually</hi> to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded of <hi>the manner</hi> of our vnion with Chriſt: whereas S. <hi>Cyrillus</hi> expoundeth them of the <hi>obiect</hi> of this vnion, which is <hi>the body and the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; the manhood and the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head of Chriſt,</hi> for he is one with vs in both natures. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as the ſame author ſaith, that<note n="f" place="margin">Idem adv. Neſtor lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>we are ſanctified and revived ſpiritually and corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally,</hi> that is to ſay, not onely in our ſpirits, but alſo in our bodies, becauſe, ſaith he,<note n="g" place="margin">1 Cor. 15 53.</note> 
                  <hi>this corruptible muſt put on incorruption, and this mortall
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:14451:71"/>muſt put on immortalitie.</hi>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">Ex Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doreto dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logo. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> So S. <hi>Ignace</hi> ſaith, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> is ioyned to the Father, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>carually and ſpiritually, i.e.</hi> both in his humane and divine nature, and not partly by a carnall, partly by a divine manner: For the manner of the vnion of Chriſt with the Father, is wholly divine: And ſo alſo the manner of our vnion with him is altogether di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, and ſpirituall. Dare Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts ſay that we are ioyned with Chriſt <hi>naturally,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though <hi>Cyrillus</hi> ſaith that our vnion with him<note n="i" place="margin">Cyril. in Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>han. lib. <hi>11.</hi> cap. <hi>26.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>is natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall?</hi> Yet he ſpeaketh ſo, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe our nature is ioyned with his natures; as he proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth, becauſe<note n="k" place="margin">1 Cor. 10.27.</note> 
                  <hi>the Church is Chriſts body, and we are mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſt in particular.</hi>
                  <pb n="118" facs="tcp:14451:72"/>So then in regard of the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects which are vnited, this vnion is naturall, reall, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall, corporall, ſpirituall, becauſe his whole perſon is ioyned with ours: And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſay that we muſt eate Chriſt, not onely <hi>as bread,</hi> but alſo <hi>as living.</hi> And if <hi>as man</hi> he is bread, and <hi>as God</hi> is li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, we muſt eate him in both natures together: For in both natures he is our Mediatour, and the bread whereby we liue.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IV"/> YET in this eating wee muſt obſerue an order. Like<note n="l" place="margin">Gen. 28.11.</note> 
                  <hi>Iacobs ladder,</hi> by <hi>his manheed</hi> he toucheth the earth: By <hi>his God head</hi> he toucheth heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: And by both vnited toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he ioyneth the earth with heaven, reconcileth man with God, obtaineth to
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:14451:72"/>vs the ſervice of the Angels of God, which<note n="m" place="margin">Ioh. 1.51</note> 
                  <hi>aſcend and deſcend vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him,</hi> and by him vpon vs: But in ſuch ſort that by him <hi>as he is man,</hi> they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend from vs, and goto him <hi>as he is God:</hi> and from him <hi>as he is God,</hi> deſcend vnto vs by him <hi>as he is man.</hi> In the ſame order doe we cate him, and abide in him, and he in vs.<note n="n" place="margin">Aug. in Ioh. trac. <hi>42.</hi> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentus eius humanitas e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius: Manſio eius diuinit as eius. Diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas eius quo imus: Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitas eius qua imus: Niſi nobis fieret qua iremus, nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam ad il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum manente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> peruenire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</note> 
                  <hi>He commeth vnto vs,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Auſtin, by his humanitie: He abideth with vs by his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinitie. His divinitie is that wherevnto we goe: His huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie is that whereby we goe. If he were not vnto vs the way whereby we may goe, we ſhould never come vnto him, in that wherein he abideth with vs.</hi> But becauſe I haue ſpoken of <hi>this bread</hi> largely inough vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the firſt part of the Verſe,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:14451:73"/>I leaue it, to come to the third part of my diviſion, which is,</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="part">
            <head>OF THE EATING of the <hi>living Bread,</hi> and <hi>of the manner thereof.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>I.</hi> To eate Chriſt, is to be vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto him.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>II.</hi> Neceſsitie of our vnion with Chriſt.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>III.</hi> Expreſſed in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture by many ſimilitudes, and in the ſixt of S. Iohn by the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude of Eating.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>IV.</hi> All Papiſts hold that Chriſt is eaten in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with the mouth of the body.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>V.</hi> The liter all ſence is not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to be followed.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <pb n="121" facs="tcp:14451:73"/>
                     <hi>VI.</hi> When it is lawfull, when not to aske How.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>VII.</hi> Papiſts agree not among themſelues concerning divers circumſtances of the bodily ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> TO EATE, is to chew and worke the meate with our teeth, if it be ſolide and ſtrong; to ſup and ſwallow it downe, if it be li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid, to receiue it into our ſtomackes, to diſgeſt it there till it be turned into blood, and changed into the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of all the parts of our bodies, that thereby this our mortall life may be maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, which otherwiſe ſhould decay and periſh. Even ſo, ſaith Chriſt,<note n="a" place="margin">Ioh. 6.53.54.</note> 
                  <hi>Except ye eate the fleſh of the Sonne of man, and drinke his blood, ye haue no
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:14451:74"/>life in you:</hi> And of thoſe that eate him he ſaith; <hi>Who ſo ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth my ſteſh, and drinketh my blood, hath eternall life, and I will raiſe him vp at the last day.</hi> Whereby it is eaſie to be vnderſtood, that this eating and drinking is a certaine action, whereby Chriſt is v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited vnto vs ſo neere, that we ſucke life out of him, yea that he himſelfe beo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth<note n="b" place="margin">Col. 3 4.</note> 
                  <hi>our life,</hi> as the Apoſtle cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth him.<note n="c" place="margin">Aug. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſ l. <hi>7.</hi> c. <hi>10.</hi> Nec tu me in te mutabis, ſicut cibum carnis tuae, ſed tu muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beris in me.</note> It is true that the bread of the earth when we eate it, cannot feed vs, till it be changed into our bodies, becauſe we are more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent then it is: But the bread which came downe from heaven, is more excellent then we are, and therefore that we may be fed by it, we are changed into it, &amp; made
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:14451:74"/>members of his bodie, of his fleſh, and of his bones. Even as the fire turneth into fire all things that feed on it.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> THIS leadeth vs by the hand to the conſideration of <hi>the neceſsitie</hi> of the eating of this bread, that is to ſay, of our vnion and communion with Chriſt. Our felicitie is to be ioyned with GOD,<note n="d" place="margin">Pſal. 36.9</note> 
                  <hi>with whom is the fountaine of life.</hi> But<note n="e" place="margin">Eſa. 59.2.</note> 
                  <hi>ſinne ſeparateth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene vs and our God.</hi> For<note n="f" place="margin">1 Ioh. 1.1.5.</note> 
                  <hi>he is light, and in him there is no darkneſſe at all:</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">Eph. 5.8.</note> 
                  <hi>we are darkeneſſe,</hi> and in vs by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture there is no light at all<note n="h" place="margin">2 Cor. 6.15.</note> 
                  <hi>What communion hath light with darkneſſe?</hi> O Lord, thou haſt made vs for thine owne ſelfe, that ſticking faſt vnto thee, we may be bleſſed by thee: But loe by our ſinne we
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:14451:75"/>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">Eph. 2.11.12.13.</note> 
                  <hi>are far off,</hi> and<note n="k" place="margin">Pſal 73.27.28.</note> 
                  <hi>loe, they that are far from thee, ſhall periſh. But it is good for vs to draw neere vnto thee,</hi> neither is our heart at reſt till it returne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee. Tell vs then, ô Lord, how ſhall we be againe ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with thee? The Sonne, the Word, the Wiſedome of God anſwereth,<note n="l" place="margin">Ioh 14.6.</note> 
                  <hi>No man co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth vnto the Father, but by me.</hi> And <hi>S. Paul</hi> telleth vs why, and how, ſaying,<note n="m" place="margin">Eph. 2.13</note> 
                  <hi>Now in Chriſt Ieſus, ye who ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times were farre off, are made nigh by the blood of Chriſt.</hi> Aske ye why? Becauſe by the blood of his ſacrifice, he hath ſatisfied the iuſtice of God, aſſwaged the burning fire of his indignation, and made attonement for vs, as<note n="n" place="margin">Heb. 7 22.</note> 
                  <hi>Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and</hi>
                  <note n="o" place="margin">Heb. 9.15.</note> 
                  <hi>Mediatour of the new Teſtament.</hi> Aske ye <hi>how?</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:14451:75"/>we are <hi>in him.</hi> He is our<note n="p" place="margin">Exod. 28.11.12.30.</note> 
                  <hi>high Prieſt,</hi> who beareth vs vpon his ſhoulders, and vpon his heart before the Lord,<note n="q" place="margin">1 Ioh. 5.11.12.</note> 
                  <hi>who hath given to vs eternall life, and this life is in his Sonne: He that hath the Sonne, hath life: and he that hath not the Sonne, hath not life.</hi> For as<note n="r" place="margin">Math 13.44.</note> he who found a treaſure hid in a field, could not claime any right vnto it, till he bought the field: So cannot we challenge<note n="ſ" place="margin">Col. 2.3.</note> 
                  <hi>the treaſures of wiſdome &amp; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> and of that<note n="t" place="margin">Ioh. 1.16.</note> 
                  <hi>fulneſſe of graces</hi> which is in Chriſt, till he himſelfe be ours: and ſo ours, that we be <hi>in him,</hi> and <hi>one with him</hi> by a moſt reall vnion of his perſon with our perſons.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> EVEN as<note n="u" place="margin">Rom. 6.5.</note> 
                  <hi>the graffe</hi> is one tree with the ſtocke wherein
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:14451:76"/>it is graffed;<note n="x" place="margin">Ioh. 15.1.</note> 
                  <hi>the vine and the branches</hi> are one plants,<note n="y" place="margin">1 Cor. 12.12.</note> 
                  <hi>the head and the members</hi> are one body,<note n="a" place="margin">Eph. 5.31.32.</note> 
                  <hi>the husband and the wife</hi> are one fleſh,<note n="b" place="margin">Eph 2.20.21.</note> 
                  <hi>the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation and the ſtones builded vpon it,</hi> are one Temple; and to come to the ſimilitude of my Text, <hi>the bread</hi> which was no part of vs, becauſe it is without vs, when it is ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth a part of our fleſh, and of our bodies. So ye ſee, not onely by the ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude of <hi>eating,</hi> but alſo by all the reſt, that our vnion with Chriſt is ſo neceſſary, that as a man cannot liue without meate, nor a houſe ſtand without a foundation, no more can we liue, ſtand, and withſtand in the evill day, without our vnion with Chriſt, according to his own
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:14451:76"/>ſaying,<note n="c" place="margin">Ioh. 15.5.</note> 
                  <hi>I am the vine, ye are the branches: He that abideth in me, and I in him, the ſame briugeth forth much fruit: for without me</hi> (or <hi>ſevered from me</hi>) <hi>ye can doe nothing.</hi> Ye ſee alſo that he is vnited with vs in all that is his, <hi>i.</hi> in both his natures:<note n="d" place="margin">Eph. 5.30.</note> 
                  <hi>In his manhood:</hi> for <hi>we are members of his body, of his fleſh, and of his bones:</hi> And <hi>in his Godhead:</hi> For<note n="e" place="margin">1 Cor. 6.7.</note> 
                  <hi>he that is ioyned vnto the Lord, is one Spirit.</hi> Likewiſe we are vnited with him in all that is ours, <hi>i.</hi> not only in our ſoules, but alſo in our bodies, as the Apoſtle ſaith,<note n="f" place="margin">1 Cor. 6.15.</note> 
                  <hi>Know we not that your bodies are the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IV"/> IF THIS had beene dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently and religiouſly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, there ſhould not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny controverſie betweene
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:14451:77"/>Papiſts &amp; vs about the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the eating of Chriſt. for if to eate Chriſt be no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing but to vnite <hi>Chriſt</hi> vnto our ſelues; if we know how we are vnited with him, we cannot chuſe but know how we eate him. If we be one with him corporally, that is, after an outward and corporall manner, then we care him corporally: But if our vnion with him be ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, doubtleſſe the mouth wherwith we eate him, muſt be a ſpirituall mouth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Papiſts ſay that our eating of Chriſt is both ſpirituall and corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall: That out of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it is ſpirituall: And many Papiſts, as<note n="g" place="margin">Biel ſuper can. Miſſ. lect. <hi>8<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Gabriell Biel,</hi>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tan. in <hi>3</hi> part. q <hi>80.</hi> art. vlt.</note> 
                  <hi>Caietan,</hi>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">Cuſan epiſt. <hi>7.</hi> ad Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos.</note> 
                  <hi>Cuſanus,</hi>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">Ianſeni con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordant<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> c <hi>59</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Ian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenius,</hi>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">Tapper ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicat<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> art. <hi>15</hi> Lovanienſ.</note> 
                  <hi>Tapper,</hi>
                  <note n="m" place="margin">Heſſel. in lib<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> de com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mun. ſub vna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecie.</note> 
                  <hi>Heſſelius,</hi> and others, acknowledge that
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:14451:77"/>Chriſt in this whole Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſpeaketh of the ſpirituall eating only.<note n="n" place="margin">Bellarm. de Euchariſt. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Bellarmin</hi> with the reſt of the Societie, and other Popiſh Doctors grant that wee muſt take in that ſence all the words of Chriſt from the ſeven and twentith vnto the one and fiftie verſe, which now I expound. But that from henceforth begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning at the one &amp; fiftie verſe vnto the end of the Chapter, Chriſt ſpeaketh of the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt: which opinion <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanus</hi> refuteth by theſe words of Chriſt, verſ. 53. <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptye eate the fleſh of the Son of man, and drinke his blood, ye haue no life in you,</hi> ſaying that<note n="o" place="margin">Cuſan. epiſt. <hi>7.</hi> ad Bohem. Neceſſe eſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> quod ſi de<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> omnibus ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis debet<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> verificari, qui habent vitamillam divina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, quod non imelligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur de viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bili ſeu Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentali manducatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, ſed de ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituali.</note> 
                  <hi>if they muſt be verified of all the Saints which haue this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine life, they muſt not be vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der ſtood of the viſible or Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:14451:78"/>but of the ſpirituall eating.</hi> Which is true: Yet all Papiſts agree that in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament Chriſt is eaten not onely <hi>ſpiritually</hi> by faith, but alſo <hi>corporally</hi> by the mouth of the body, in ſuch ſort that the true body of Chriſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereth into their mouthes, and is received into their ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mackes. If ye aske how they can beleeue ſuch a mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrous Doctrine? They anſwere, that Chriſt affirmeth in this Chapter, that we muſt eate his fleſh, &amp; drinke his blood: And that in the Sacrament he hath commaunded vs to eate his body, ſaying, <hi>Take, eate, This is my bidy:</hi> To refuſe to eate him, were diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: To aske <hi>how,</hi> is incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulitie, like vnto that of the <hi>Iewes</hi> of <hi>Capernaum,</hi>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">Ioh 6<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>52. <hi>Rhennſta.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>who
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:14451:78"/>ſtroue amongst themſelues, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, HOW can this man giue vs his fleſh to eate?</hi> This, ſay they, is the literall ſence, and this ſence they will follow.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> BVT firſt, if the literall ſence muſt be alwayes followed, why beleeue they not, as the <hi>Anthropomorphits</hi> did, that <hi>God</hi> hath a body as we haue, ſeeing <hi>God</hi> ſaith that he hath eyes, eares, hands, feete, &amp;c? Why ſhake they not hands with <hi>the Arrians,</hi> and deny Chriſt to be God, becauſe he himſelfe ſaid,<note n="q" place="margin">Ioh. 14.28</note> 
                  <hi>My Father is greater then I?</hi> Certainely if they had been in <hi>Nicodemus</hi> his place, they would not haue asked of Chriſt,<note n="r" place="margin">Ioh. 3.4.</note> 
                  <hi>How can a man be borne when he is old?</hi> but ſaid vnto him, Lord feeing thou haſt ſaid that we muſt be borne againe, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:14451:79"/>that we ſhall enter the ſecond time into our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wombe, and be borne againe. And if they had bin ſtanding by the <hi>Samaritane</hi> Woman, they would haue naught her to beleeue that Chriſt is reall and ſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all water, becauſe he called himſelfe water: May they not alſo with as good reaſon expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d literally, that which<note n="ſ" place="margin">Pro. 9.5.</note> 
                  <hi>the Wiſdome</hi> in the <hi>Proverbs,</hi>
                  <note n="t" place="margin">Cant. 5.1.</note> 
                  <hi>the Spouſe</hi> in <hi>Salemons Song,</hi>
                  <note n="u" place="margin">Eſa. 55.1</note> 
                  <hi>God</hi> in <hi>Eſaiah</hi> ſpeaketh of the furniſhing of their Table with beaſtes, honey, milke, bread, and wine? And when God ſaith,<note n="x" place="margin">Pſal. 81.10</note> 
                  <hi>Open thy mouth wide, and I will fill it,</hi>
                  <note n="y" place="margin">Cant 5.1.</note> 
                  <hi>eate, drinke abundantly,</hi> if we muſt alwayes cleaue to the leaues of the words, we muſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare our throats &amp; our bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:14451:79"/>and drinke ſtoutly till we be drunke.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VI"/> SECONDLY, if thoſe ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches muſt be taken allegori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally of meate and drinke of another kinde then thoſe which are earthly and vſuall amongſt vs, it is no offence to aske <hi>how</hi> we may be made partakers of them. To aske <hi>how</hi> the things which GOD alone doth may be done, <hi>as how</hi> he created the world, How the Word was made fleſh, &amp;c. is a moſt horrible ſinne:<note n="a" place="margin">Auguſt. ad Voluſian. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. <hi>3.</hi> In ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libus rebus Iota ratio fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctieſt poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia facientia.</note> 
                  <hi>For in ſuch things all the reaſon of that which is don, is the power of the doer.</hi> And therefore <hi>Zacharias</hi> ſinned, when he asked,<note n="b" place="margin">Luk. 1.18.20.</note> 
                  <hi>How ſhall I knew this? for I am an old man, and my wiſe well ſtrucken in yeares.</hi> But when any thing is to be done by vs, it is not
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:14451:80"/>diffidence, is not curioſitie, it is docilitie, it is dutie to aske <hi>How</hi> we ſhould doe it, that we may doe it well, and according to the will of the commander, ſo that wee goe to him, and aske coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell at his mouth, <hi>how</hi> he will haue it to be don. The <hi>Iewes</hi> of <hi>Capernaum</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Cyrill. in Ioh. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>30.</hi> Et lib. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>14.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>through pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption and arrogancie,</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked<note n="d" place="margin">Ioh. 6.52.60.67.</note> 
                  <hi>how</hi> Chriſt might giue them his fleſh to eate, and calling his ſpeech <hi>an hard ſaying, went backe, and walked no more with him,</hi> whereas<note n="e" place="margin">Chryſoſt. in Ioh. hom. <hi>46.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>they ſhould haue remained with him, and not departed, they ſhould haue asked, and not deſpaired.</hi> O thrice and foure times happie had they been, if they had propounded to Chriſt an <hi>How of docilitie,</hi> as <hi>Nicodemus</hi> did, when having
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:14451:80"/>a good conceit of Chriſt, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeming him ſo wiſe that he ſaid nothing abſurdly, and not vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding his words, asked of him,<note n="f" place="margin">Ioh. 3.4.</note> 
                  <hi>How</hi> they ſhould be vnderſtood, &amp; was inſtructed. How more hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie had they beene, if they had come to Chriſt with an <hi>How of faith,</hi> as <hi>Maneah</hi> did to the Angel, ſaying,<note n="g" place="margin">Iudg. 13.12.</note> 
                  <hi>Now let thy words come to paſſe: How ſhall we order the childe, and how ſhall we do vnto him?</hi> And as <hi>the Virgin Mary</hi> did, when beleeving the words of the Angel <hi>Gabriel</hi> that ſhe ſhould be the mother of the Sonne of God, &amp; not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing if any action of hers ſhould concurre with the power of God in that work, ſhe asked,<note n="h" place="margin">Luk. 1.34.</note> 
                  <hi>How ſhall this be, ſeeing I know not a man?</hi> So
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:14451:81"/>we beleeue that we muſt eate Chriſt: For ſeeing he hath ſaid it, is there any Chriſtian that dare deny it? This ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting is commanded vnto vs, and to be done by vs. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to aske <hi>how</hi> we ſhould doe it, and to be carefull that we ſinne not by doing it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe, is docilitie and faith.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VII"/> THIRDLY, Papiſts them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, when they are hoarſe with crying againſt vs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we aske and teach <hi>how</hi> Chriſt is eaten, ſeeke in their owne braines the expoſition of this <hi>How,</hi> and decide the queſtion in words ſo mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous, that we could not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue it, if they were not written in their own books. NICOLAS the II. Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> and a Councell of an hundred and foureteene Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:14451:81"/>which he aſſembled at <hi>Rome</hi> in the yeare of Chriſt 1059. conſtrained <hi>Berengari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> to confeſſe, that<note n="i" place="margin">Decret. <hi>3.</hi> parte. de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrat. diſt. <hi>2.</hi> can. <hi>42.</hi> Ego Berengarius. Scilicet pane<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; vinum, quae in altari ponu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur, post confecratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, non ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſacramentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſed etiam ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum corpus &amp; ſanguine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> domini noſtri Ieſu. Chriſti eſſe, &amp; ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſualiter, non ſolum ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum, ſed in veritate manibus ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctari, frangi, &amp; fidelium dentibus at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teri.</note> 
                  <hi>not onely the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, but alſo the true body of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, is truly and ſenſibly handled and broken with the hands of the Prieſts, and is brayed with the teeth of the faithfull.</hi> This ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non is againſt the Scripture, which ſaith <hi>Ioh.</hi> 19.36. that <hi>a bone of him ſhall not be broken.</hi> And therefore the Romane Doctours, departing from their maxime, That <hi>the Pope and the Councels approved by him cannot erre,</hi> ſay that <hi>Chriſt</hi> without any ſuch bruiſing goeth down from the mouth to the ſtomacke whole and intire, but hid vnder the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents of the bread. There is in S. <hi>Bernards</hi> workes a
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:14451:82"/>Sermon <hi>de Coenadomini, of the Lords Supper,</hi> but it is none of his: In it the author ſaith, <hi>Speciem panis rodit aliquando ſorex paruiſsimus: Chriſtianus recipit etiam peſsimus: virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem gratiae ſpiritualis non niſi praedeſtinatus recipit. A little mouſe ſometimes gnaweth the ſpece of bread, &amp; a lewd Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian receiveth it alſo: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as he onely who is predeſtinated receiueth the vertue of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall grace.</hi> By the <hi>ſpeces</hi> of bread he vnderſtandeth the accidents thereof, ſuch as are the colour, the ſmell, the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, the weight, and ſuch like; but it would be a good peece of learning to tell vs how a mouſe can gnaw, and a wicked man eate acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents.</p>
               <p>THOMAS the Angelicall
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:14451:82"/>Doctor of the <hi>Roman Church</hi> maintaineth that not onely wicked men, but alſo fowles,<note place="margin">Tho. <hi>3.</hi> parte q. <hi>80.</hi> art. <hi>3.</hi> ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ni. De defecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentib circa Miſſam.</note> beaſts and wormes may eate Chriſts body in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and in all the Maſſe-bookes many inſtructions are given to the Prieſts what muſt be don with the mouſe which hath eaten Chriſts body, and with the body of Chriſt, which the Prieſt or a ſicke man hath vomited.</p>
               <p>If ye aske how long he continueth there? They an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere to that alſo. The Prieſt praying in the Maſſe that<note n="k" place="margin">Adhareat viſceribus meis.</note> 
                  <hi>it may ſticke faſt to his bowels,</hi> thinketh that he continueth for ever in his body.<note n="l" place="margin">Gloſſa in can. <hi>23</hi> Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus gradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, Certum eſt quod ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cies quam ci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to dentibus teruntur, tam cito in coelum rapitur cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus Chriſti.</note> 
                  <hi>The Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noniſts</hi> ſay, that <hi>as ſoone as the ſpecies</hi> (or viſible accidents) <hi>are bruiſed with the teeth, his body is rauiſhed into heauen,</hi> as
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:14451:83"/>if he were afraid of a ſnatch by the way.<note n="m" place="margin">Thom. <hi>3.</hi> parte. q. <hi>80.</hi> art. <hi>3.</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſ. Bellarm. de Euchariſt. lib. <hi>14.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Thomas</hi> and the moſt part of the reſt ſay, that he abideth in the ſtomacke till <hi>the ſpecies</hi> or accidents vnder which his body was hid be conſumed, that is, as long time as would be need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to the naturall heat to diſgeſt the bread whereof they are the accidents, if it were in the ſtomacke. This is their explication of the <hi>how</hi> the body of Chriſt is ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the Sacrament, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they omit to tell vs <hi>how</hi> it goeth out againe. But we ſay that this manner of the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the body of Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> is impoſſible in it ſelfe, inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and iniurious to Chriſt, and vnprofitable to the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:14451:83"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER. VI.</hi> Six reaſons why it is impoſsible to eate Chriſt with the mouth of the body.</head>
               <p>YE haue ſundry wayes <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> to know that it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible. 1.<note n="n" place="margin">Chryſoſt. <hi>1</hi> Cor. <hi>11.</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mil. <hi>27.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> S. <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome</hi> exhorteth vs <hi>to eate, to drinke, to put on Chriſt,</hi> Shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that thoſe three muſt be done by one and the ſame action. But by the mouth we cannot put him on: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by the mouth we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not eate and drinke him. Extend this argument to all the reſt of the ſimilitudes, whereby our vnion with Chriſt is expreſſed. The vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of clothes with the body, and of ſtones with the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation <hi>is artificiall and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward:</hi> The vnion of the head
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:14451:84"/>with the members, of the vine with the branches <hi>is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall and inward:</hi> The vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the husband with his wife, <hi>is ciuill,</hi> and inforceth not any proximitie or tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of bodies, as the reſt doe: For they remaine one fleſh, although they be as far ſeparated as the Eaſt is from the Weſt. If a bodily manner of coniunction with Chriſt, cannot be inforced by thoſe ſimilitudes, becauſe it ſhould be at one time outward and inward, naturall, civill, and artificiall, which is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: Let Papiſts tell why it ſhould be inforced by the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude of eating? If by the ſimilitude of eating, why not alſo by the reſt? Here they are muffled and cannot anſwer.<note n="*" place="margin">Cuſan epiſt. <hi>7.</hi> ad. Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos. Cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dere igitur, bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zari, mandu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care, &amp; bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere, et quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid ſimiliter per Chriſtum dicitur, non habet in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituali intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectu differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam, ſed v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſolum eſt, quodper om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia talia va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie exprimu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tur, ſcilicet quotquot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceperu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t eum, dedit eis po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tem fili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os dei fieri ijs qui credunt in nomine eius.</note> 
                  <hi>Cuſanus</hi> one of their owne
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:14451:84"/>confeſſeth, that <hi>all thoſe ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litudes, and whatſoever Chriſt ſaith after that manner, hath no difference in the ſpirituall vnderſtanding, but it is one thing which by all ſuch things is diverſly expreſſed, to wit, As many as received him, to them gaue the power to become the Sonnes of God, to them that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue on his Name.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>SECONDLY, in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he giveth himſelfe, not as glorified in heaven, but as dead vpon the croſſe, as he ſaid,<note n="o" place="margin">1 Cor. 11.24.</note> 
                  <hi>This is my body which is broken for you:</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">Mar. 14.24</note> 
                  <hi>This is my blood which is ſhed for many: Doe this in remembrance of me.</hi> Which commandement the Apoſtle explaineth ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,<note n="q" place="margin">1 Cor. 11 26.</note> 
                  <hi>For as often as ye eate this bread, and drinke this cup, ye doe ſhew the Lords death till
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:14451:85"/>he come.</hi> He did giue himſelfe to the Apoſtles ſo, and they received him ſo. For he was not then glorified. Should we deſire to receiue him o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwayes then they did? To receiue him ſo with the mouth of the body it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, becauſe he is not now dead, but<note n="r" place="margin">Rom. 6.10</note> 
                  <hi>liueth vnto God.</hi> This argument prevents all replyes.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> THIRDLY, if Chriſt were in the Sacrament, wicked men, yea worms, mice, dogs, aſſes, and other beaſts might eate him. But that is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſaith<note n="ſ" place="margin">Origin, in Math. <hi>15.</hi> Verus cibus quem nullus malus poteſt edere.</note> 
                  <hi>Origines,</hi> becauſe if they did eate him, they ſhould abide in him, as he ſaith, <hi>verſ.</hi> 56. <hi>He that eateth my fleſh, and drinketh my blood, dwelleth in me, and I in him:</hi> and abiding in him they
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:14451:85"/>ſhould liue for ever, as he ſaith in my Text, <hi>If any man eate of this bread he ſhall liue for ever,</hi> and ſo often in the verſes preceeding and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing: Which moved<note n="t" place="margin">De co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecrat. diſt. <hi>2.</hi> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <hi>65</hi> Qui diſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dat a Chriſto, nec carnem eius mandu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat, nec ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinem bibit, etiam ſi tantae rei Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ad iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuae prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptionis quotidiè in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differenter accipiat.</note> S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> to ſay, that <hi>he who is diſcordant from Chriſt, eateth not his fleſh, and drinketh not his blood, although he receiue daily the Sacrament of ſo great a thing to the condemnation of his owne preſumption.</hi> As like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe he ſaith of the Apoſtles, that<note n="u" place="margin">Idem in Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>han trac. <hi>59.</hi> Illi mandu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t panem dominum: Ille panem domini con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra dominu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Illi vitam, ille poenam.</note> 
                  <hi>they did eate the bread which is the Lord,</hi> and of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das,</hi> that <hi>he did eate the bread of the Lord againſt the Lord, They life, he paine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>FOVRTHLY, the Lord himſelfe ſeeing that many of his Diſciples tooke his words carnally,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IV"/> as if he had ſpoken of a corporall eating
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:14451:86"/>of his body,<note n="x" place="margin">Athan. de verb. Chriſti Qui dixerit verbum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra filiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis: Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo fieri poſſet vt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus mundus ederet de carne ipſius, quae non ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficeret paucis hominibus: Ideo dominus de carnis ſuae manducatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne loquens, ſui in coelum aſcenſus me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minit, vt a corporali eos manducatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne abſtrahe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret, &amp; vel inde diſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent carnem Chriſti eſſe cibum coele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtem, et in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limonia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritualem da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re.</note> 
                  <hi>to draw them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from bodily eating, and to teach them that his fleſh is a heavenly meate, and is given to be ſpirituall food, he maketh mention of his aſcenſion into heaven,</hi> ſaying, <hi>verſ.</hi> 61.62. <hi>Doth this offend you? What and if ye ſhall ſee the Sonne of man aſcend vp wher he was before?</hi> arguing, This is a ſtrong rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that<note n="y" place="margin">Ibide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> trac. <hi>27.</hi> Vel tunc videbitis quod non eo modo quo pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis erogat corpus ſuum. Certe vel tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c intelligetis quod gratia eius non con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumitur morfibus.</note> 
                  <hi>he giueth not his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy after the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner which they imagined.</hi> z <hi>For the heavens muſt receiue him, vntill the time of reſtitution of all things, which God hath ſpoken by the mouth of all his holy Prophets,</hi> becauſe there a <hi>he appeareth in the preſence of God,</hi> and b <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth interceſsion for vs,</hi> and cannot come out of that <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly place,</hi> till his interceſſion be ended, which will not be
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:14451:86"/>till the worlds end. For<note n="c" place="margin">Heb. 8.4.</note> 
                  <hi>if he were on earth, he ſhould not be a Prieſt.</hi> But he is a Prieſt: and therefore, ſaith he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,<note n="d" place="margin">Math. 24.23.26.</note> 
                  <hi>If any man ſay vnto you, Loe, here is Chriſt, or there, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue it not: Behold he is in the deſert, goe not forth; behold he is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>,<note n="z" place="margin">Act 3.21.</note>
                     <note n="a" place="margin">Heb 9.24.</note> in the ſecret chambers,</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Ro. 8.34.</note> (as when Papiſts ſay he is in the chappell, on the Altar in the box) <hi>beleeue it not:</hi> Beleeue rather S. <hi>Paul</hi> who ſaith, that<note n="e" place="margin">2 Cor. 5.6.16.</note> 
                  <hi>whiles we are at home in the body, we are ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent from the Lord, and hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth know him no more after the fleſh,</hi> and according to his exhortatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note n="f" place="margin">Col. 3.1 2.</note> 
                  <hi>ſeeke thoſe things which are aboue, where Chriſt ſitteth on the right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of God: ſet your affection on things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue, not on things on earth.</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">Bernard, de Aduentu do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini ſerm. <hi>1.</hi> Incaſſum la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boraret erige<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re corda no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra, niſi col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis ſalutis noſtra doce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret autorem.</note> 
                  <hi>In vaine would he labour to
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:14451:87"/>heaue vp our hearts to heaven, if the authour of our ſalvation were not in heaven.</hi> Yea moſt prepoſterouſly ſhould he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devour to withdraw our hearts from the earth, if Chriſt were on earth. For<note n="h" place="margin">Math. 6.21.</note> 
                  <hi>where your treaſure is, there will your hearts be alſo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> Fiftly, if the eating of Chriſt with the mouth of the body were poſſible, his manhood might be ſeparated from his Godhead, his ſoule from his body, and the life which is in him from his perſon. Can his Godhead which is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite be receiued in our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies? Can his ſoule which is a ſpirit enter into our ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mackes? Can his quickning life which cannot be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his Godhead, goe where the Godhead will not goe?
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:14451:87"/>Certainly, if it were poſſible to eate him, the mouth of our body could eat nothing of him but his body: And what is a body without a ſoule, but a corps? if then Chriſt<note n="i" place="margin">Rom. 6.9.</note> 
                  <hi>being raiſed from dead, he dieth no more, death hath no more dominion over him,</hi> it is impietie to thinke, it is blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemie to ſay that his body may be eaten corporally.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VI"/> AND why, I pray you, doth the Prieſt when he ſheweth the hoſte to the people, cry, <hi>Surſum corda?</hi> Why doth the people anſwer, <hi>Habemus ad dominu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> but becauſe they acknowledg that even when the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is given, Chriſt is in heaven, and is not in his body elſe-where? So all that they prattle of the poſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and realitie of his bodily
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:14451:88"/>preſence in the Euchariſt, is like a ſpiders web, which is ſwept away with the firſt blaſt of the truth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER VII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>I.</hi> The bodily eating is indecent and iniurious to Chriſt.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>II.</hi> The reply of the Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries impertinent.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>III.</hi> The ſame eating is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable to the eaters.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> CERTAINLY although it were poſſible, <hi>it is vndecent, and iniuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> Are the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents of a cruſt a conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent garment to cover the Sonne of God? Is it fit that he who vpholdeth all things by the word of his power, ſhould be borne betweene the fingers of a Prieſt, who is
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:14451:88"/>in perpetuall feare leaſt he fall? Are the ſtomackes of men, which are puddles of infection, Temples well ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Lord of glory? The Cherubims and Seraphims, all the Angels of God wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and ſerue him in heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The divels themſelues ſtoop and bow downe their heads before him from the lower hels, and men which are no better then Graſhoppes put him to an open ſhame, main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining, as I haue ſaid, that not onely wicked men, but alſo fowles, beaſts, &amp; wormes may eat him.<note n="l" place="margin">Thom. <hi>3.</hi> q. <hi>80.</hi> art. <hi>3.</hi> Quida<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dixe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt quod ſtatim cum Sacramentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tangitur a mure vel ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, deſinit ibi corpus eſſe Chriſti, quod etiam dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat veritati Sacramenti. Alexan. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenſ. part. <hi>4.</hi> ſum. q. <hi>45.</hi> in <hi>1.</hi> &amp; q. <hi>53.</hi> in <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> To let you ſee how farre the God of this world hath blinded them, they dare ſay that this blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous divinitie deroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth nothing from the glory of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="152" facs="tcp:14451:89"/>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> WHY?<note n="m" place="margin">Thom. ibi.</note> Becauſe forſooth <hi>he was crucified by ſinners without any diminution of his dignitie,</hi> yea was by<note n="n" place="margin">Math. 4.5.8.</note> 
                  <hi>the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell</hi> tranſported from one place to another. But theſe things did befall him in the dayes of his fleſh: Then he came to be tempted, to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed and crucified by wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men: Then<note n="o" place="margin">Heb. 4.15.</note> 
                  <hi>he was in all things tempted like as we are, yet without ſinne.</hi> But now<note n="p" place="margin">Eph. 1.20.21.</note> 
                  <hi>he ſitteth at the right hand of his Father in the heauenly pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, farre aboue all principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and power, and might, and dominion.</hi> Now<note n="q" place="margin">Heb. 2.7.</note> 
                  <hi>he is crowned with glory and honour.</hi> Now<note n="r" place="margin">Phil. 2 9 10.</note> 
                  <hi>God hath highly exalted him, and given him a Name which is aboue every name, that at the Name of Ieſus every knee ſhould bow, of things in heauen,
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:14451:89"/>and things in earth, and things vnder the earth.</hi> And ſhall he now, now be in a worſe caſe then he was in his greateſt infirmitie? For then he did not enter into mens bellies, and did not feare the gnaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of wormes, nor the teeth of mice, nor the intrals of beaſts.</p>
               <p>What? ſay Papiſts, is not God every where, and is not defiled? True. But the body of Chriſt is not. It is a true body: Therefore if it be in the body of a man, or of a beaſt, it muſt touch them: And it cannot touch them, but it muſt be defiled by them. They aske againe, Doth not the light of the Sunne inlighten the whole aire? Is it not ſpread over the whole earth? Shineth it not
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:14451:90"/>in the moſt infected places, and is not infected? True al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo. For the light in the Sunne and in the aire is not a body, it is an accident. But the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Chriſt is a true body. If the Sunne it ſelfe were vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a dunghill, it ſhould be ſoyled, as well as the aire wherein the light is. So the body of Chriſt if it touch our bodies muſt neceſſarily be contaminated: And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it were not, I ſay that it cannot be lodged in the ſtincking bellies of men or beaſts, but it muſt be diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured: Wherefore I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that this eating of the body of Chriſt, is not onely impoſſible, but alſo inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent &amp; outragious to Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> WHAT although it were poſſible? What although
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:14451:90"/>Chriſt were not diſhonoured by it? I aske <hi>cui bono?</hi> The leaſt of the workes of GOD hath ſome vſe: This which is thought to be one of the moſt wonderfull, hath none at all. Chriſt muſt over-turne the whol order of nature, he muſt be ſubiect to the inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Prieſt, he muſt be at once in heaven &amp; on earth, he muſt contract his body to the capacitie of a little round cruſt, and haue his head in his feete, and all the parts of his body pellemel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led: He muſt be kept in a boxe, and often tarry there till he get a white coate. To what purpoſe ſo many mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous wonders? To ſaue men? No, no. Many men ſince the beginning of the world till Chriſt haue benne
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:14451:91"/>ſaved without this eating. Many every day goe to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven without it. Many wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men are damned with it. Thoſe who communicate every day, reape no profit by it. For no meate doth good, except it ſticke to him that eateth it: Whereas the body of Chriſt doth not continue in them. But it muſt ſcoure to heaven as faſt as it came from it, having no longer leaue to ſtay then till the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents be conſumed, and giving no oddes in Paradiſe to them who are every other day ſo carefull to receiue it. For what end doe wee eate our daily bread? To ſuſtaine our liues. For what end muſt we eate the bread which came downe from heaven, muſt Ieſus Chriſt enter into
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:14451:91"/>vs? He himſelfe anſwereth ſaying,<note n="ſ" place="margin">Ioh. 6.57.</note> 
                  <hi>He that eateth me, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven he ſhall liue by me,</hi> and that <hi>for ever,</hi> as he ſaith in my Text. And yet Papiſts confeſſe that to haue his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in our bodies, bringeth no ſuch advantage to any man. <hi>The Virgin Mary</hi> had him nine moneths in her wombe, and <hi>Elizabeth</hi> ſaid vnto her,<note n="t" place="margin">Luk. 1.45.</note> 
                  <hi>Bleſſed is ſhee that beleeved.</hi> And when a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſaid vnto Chriſt,<note n="u" place="margin">Luk. 11.27.28.</note> 
                  <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed is the womb that bare thee, and the papes which thou haſt ſucked,</hi> he reiected that ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with this anſwere; <hi>Yea bleſſed are they that heare the Word of God, and keepe it,</hi> ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that it is not the having of his body in our bodies, but the having of him and of his word in our hearts by
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:14451:92"/>faith and obedience that quickeneth and bleſſeth vs. Which I will proue, decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring firſt, the true manner how CHRIST giveth this bread, and next how we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER VIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>I.</hi> Wee muſt learne of Chriſt how he giveth himſelfe, and how we receiue him.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>II.</hi> Chriſt giveth himſelfe vnto vs by his Spirit.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>III.</hi> To be in Chriſt, and to haue the Spirit of Chriſt are equivalent in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>IV.</hi> We haue no reall vnion with Chriſt in the Sacraments but by the Spirit.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>V.</hi> It is eaſie to the Spirit to vnite vs vnto Chriſt.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <pb n="159" facs="tcp:14451:92"/>
                     <hi>VI.</hi> We muſt pray for the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> WE ſhall not goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtray, if in this point, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, we follow the counſell of S.<note n="x" place="margin">Cyrill. in Ioh. lib. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>13.</hi> Quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendum enim ita ſemper eſt, vt apud cum habite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, &amp; ad alienas ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentias non defer amur.</note> 
                  <hi>Cyrillus, and make in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirie in ſuch ſort, that we dwell with God, and be not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried about with the opinions of men.</hi> Papiſts beleeue that they muſt eat Chriſt, becauſe he hath ſaid it. We beleeue it likewiſe. But when he telleth vs alſo, <hi>how</hi> he giveth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and <hi>how</hi> we muſt eate him, they ſtop their eares, and will not heare: we muſt not doe ſo: we muſt ſay vnto him as <hi>Samuel</hi> did to GOD,<note n="y" place="margin">1 Sam. 3.9.</note> 
                  <hi>Speake Lord, for thy ſervant heareth.</hi> He of all can beſt tell <hi>how</hi> he giveth himſelfe, and
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:14451:93"/>
                  <hi>how</hi> we receiue him. And what he anſwereth to both queſtions muſt be true.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> TO THE firſt he anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in the 63. verſe of this Chapter, ſaying, <hi>It is the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit that quickeneth, the fleſh profiteth nothing, the words that I ſpeake vnto you, they are Spirit and they are life, i.</hi> they muſt be vnderſtood <hi>of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> which is<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 8.2.</note> 
                  <hi>the Spirit of life,</hi> quickning the fleſh of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and<note n="b" place="margin">Aug. in Iohan. tract. <hi>27.</hi> Ergoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus eſt qui viuificat. Spiritus euim facit viua membra.</note> 
                  <hi>making all the members of his body to liue</hi> by a ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all vnion with him. He had ſaid before <hi>verſ.</hi> 56. <hi>He that eateth my fleſh and drinketh my blood, dwelleth in me, and I in him.</hi> And S. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith, that<note n="c" place="margin">1 Ioh. 4.13.</note> 
                  <hi>hereby know we, that we dwell in him, and he in vs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath given vs of his Spirit.</hi> It is then by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:14451:93"/>that he giveth himſelfe vnto vs, and dwelleth in vs. And this giving of himſelfe vnto vs by his Spirit is ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compatible with his bodily preſence, that he averred for a moſt certaine truth, that<note n="d" place="margin">Ioh. 16.7.</note> 
                  <hi>it was expedient that he ſhould goe away; For if I goe not away,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>the Cemforter will not come vnto you: but if I depart, I will ſend him vnto you:</hi> And what to doe?<note n="e" place="margin">Ioh. 14.16.17.18.</note> 
                  <hi>To abide with you for ever.</hi> And this abiding of his Spirit with vs, is his abiding with vs, as he ſaith in the next verſe, <hi>I will not leaue you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortleſſe, I will come to you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> THIS IS ſo true, that in the new Teſtament to be in Chriſt, and to haue the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Chriſt, are equivalent: The Apoſtle averreth, that
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:14451:94"/>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 8.9.10.</note> 
                  <hi>if any man haue not the Spirit of Chriſt, he is not his:</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto he addeth, <hi>If Chriſt be in you,</hi> becauſe <hi>Chriſt</hi> is not in vs, but by his Spirit. This v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Chriſt with vs exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth it ſelfe to our bodies.<note n="g" place="margin">1 Cor. 6.15.</note> 
                  <hi>Know ye not,</hi> ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>that your bodies are the members of Chriſt?</hi> If ye aske of him How? He anſwereth,<note n="h" place="margin">Verſ. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>He that is ioyned vnto the Lord, is one Spirit. i. e.</hi> he is made one with the Lord by the holy Spirit, as he ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth when he asketh againe,<note n="i" place="margin">Verſ. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>What, know you not that your body is the Temple of the Holy Ghoſt, which is in you, which ye haue of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IV"/> WE haue no other kinde of vnion with Chriſt in the Sacraments. It is written of our <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> that<note n="k" place="margin">1 Cor. 12.13.</note> 
                  <hi>by one Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:14451:94"/>we are all baptized into one body,</hi> becauſe it is <hi>the Spirit</hi> that in our Baptiſme incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porateth vs in Chriſt. It is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo written of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.13</note> that <hi>we haue bin all made to drinke into one Spirit,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that in that holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament he giveth his body vnto vs by his Spirit. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though that his body ſhould come downe from heaven, and enter into our bodies, it could not vnite vs vnto him, as I haue ſaid: <hi>for the fleſh profiteth nothing:</hi> But that which is impoſſible to his fleſh, is eaſie to his Spirit, which if he ſend from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven into our hearts, it will vnite vs vnto him more truely and neerely then our ſoules are vnited to our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="164" facs="tcp:14451:95"/>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> THIS then is the true <hi>How</hi> Chriſt giveth himſelfe to be eaten,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Vſe.</hi>
                  </note> wherevnto we muſt ſubmit our minds and cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, without any further inquirie, following the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the bleſſed <hi>Virgin,</hi> who when the Angel had inſtructed her that<note n="l" place="margin">Luk. 1.35.38.</note> 
                  <hi>the holy Ghoſt ſhould come vpon her,</hi> and make her to conceiue, brought into captivitie all her thoughts to the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the Word of GOD, and ſaid, <hi>Behold the handmaid of the Lord, be it vnto me ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thy Word.</hi> Behold, I pray you, how the Sunne budgeth not out of his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly tabernacle, and never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe darting his beames from heaven to earth, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municateth it ſelfe to all the creatures that are on earth.
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:14451:95"/>And ſhall we ſay, that<note n="m" place="margin">Mal. 4.2.</note> 
                  <hi>the Sunne of righteouſneſſe,</hi> muſt leaue his celeſtiall and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous palace to make good the word which he hath ſpoken of our communion with him? O blaſphemy? He hath ſaid that by his Spirit he will come vnto vs, and dwell with vs: He will doe it as he hath ſaid it,<note n="n" place="margin">Luk. 1.37.</note> 
                  <hi>For with God no word ſhall be impoſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VI"/> WHEREFORE fettering our curioſitie with the ſhac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kles of the word of God, let vs cry to heaven,<note n="o" place="margin">Veni crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor Spiritus, Et infunde coelitus. Lucis tuae radium.</note> 
                  <hi>Come</hi> O moſt holy and bleſſed Spirit into our hearts, aſſured that if we pray ſo earneſtly, God will heare vs:<note n="p" place="margin">Luk. 11.13.</note> 
                  <hi>For,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>if ye being evill know how to giue good gifts vnto your children, how much more ſhall
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:14451:96"/>your heavenly Father giue the holy Spirit to them that aske him?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER IX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>I.</hi> We muſt learne of Chriſt himſelfe how we eate him.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>II.</hi> Such bread, ſuch eating.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>III.</hi> Such man, ſuch eating.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>IV.</hi> Such ſences and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to apprehend him, ſuch eating.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>V.</hi> Such end of our eating, ſuch eating.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> LET Vs in the next place goe againe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt, and aske and learne of him how we muſt eate this bread, which came downe from heaven. For<note n="q" place="margin">Auguſt. in Ioh tract <hi>27</hi> Patitur enim nos non con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicentes, ſed noſſe cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientes.</note> 
                  <hi>he beareth with vs, when we aske of him, not to contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict, but to learne.</hi> O ye that
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:14451:96"/>haue an eare to heare, heare.<note n="r" place="margin">Deut. 29.29.</note> 
                  <hi>The ſecret things belong vnto the Lord our God.</hi>
                  <note n="ſ" place="margin">1 Sam. 6.19.</note> Looke not with the men of <hi>Bethſhemeſh</hi> into this Arke of the Lord:<note n="t" place="margin">Iob. 33.13</note> 
                  <hi>He giueth not account of any of his matters.</hi>
                  <note n="u" place="margin">Deut. 29.29.</note> 
                  <hi>But thoſe things which are revealed, belong vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs and to our children for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, that we may doe all the words of this Law.</hi> Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mably whervnto an ancient hath ſaid wiſely,<note n="x" place="margin">Ambroſ. de Vocat Gent. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Quae deus occulta eſſe voluit non ſunt ſcrutanda, quae aute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> manifeſta fecit non ſunt neganda: ne in illis illi citè eurioſi, iſtis dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabiliter inueniamur ingrati, that thoſe things which GOD will haue to be hid, muſt not be ſearched, and thoſe which he hath made manifeſt, muſt not be denyed, leaſt in thoſe we be found vnlawfully curious, and
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:14451:97"/>in this be condemned as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfull.</hi> Of theſe things is the manner of the eating of the bread which came down from heaven.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> FIRST, Such as the bread is, and as it is given to be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, ſo muſt it be eaten. If it be come downe from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, from heaven alſo muſt come the mouth that eateth it. If it be given vnto vs by the holy Spirit, the mouth which receiveth it muſt be a ſpirituall mouth. If Chriſt who is this bread, giveth himſelfe vnto vs as dead, haue we any mouth that can eate him ſo, but the mouth of the ſoule? This is his own doctrine. For after he had ſaid, <hi>Take ye, eate ye, This is my body,</hi> he ſhews how we muſt eate him, ſaying, <hi>doe this in
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:14451:97"/>remembrance of me.</hi> Theſe words, ſaith<note n="y" place="margin">Auguſt. de Doct. Chriſt. lib <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>15.</hi> Figura eſt ergopracipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens paſsioni domini eſſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munican<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, &amp; ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aniter at que vtiliter reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moria, quod pro nobis ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro eius cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixa &amp; vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerata eſt.</note> 
                  <hi>Auguſtin, are a figure commanding vs to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate to his paſsion, and to record profitably, that his fleſh was crucified and wounded for vs,</hi> which we cannot do but by an action of the ſoule.</p>
               <p>SECONDLY, Such man, ſuch eating. If he who eateth Chriſt be nothing but a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall man, let him eate and drinke with his naturall or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganes.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> But if Chriſt be meate for Chriſtians, if the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an be<note n="z" place="margin">Eph. 4.24.</note> 
                  <hi>a new man,</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">1 Cor. 2.1</note> 
                  <hi>a ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all man,</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 2.19. Rom. 7.22</note> 
                  <hi>an inward man,</hi> if all his organes be ſpirituall and inward, ſhall we not ſay tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with S. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> that he he alone eateth Chriſt,<note n="c" place="margin">Auguſt. in Ioh. tract. <hi>26</hi> in verba, Vt ſi quis man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducat ex ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo non me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riatur Qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> manducat in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, nonforis: qui ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ducat in corde, non qui pren it de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e</note> 
                  <hi>that eateth inwardly, not outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; who eateth in his heart, not he that thrufteth his tooth into the Sacrament.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="170" facs="tcp:14451:98"/>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IV"/> THIRDLY, to apply this to all the ſences and parts of the inward man, <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaith,<note n="d" place="margin">Math. 5.8.</note> 
                  <hi>bleſſed are they which doe hunger and thirſt after righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes.</hi> Is not he he himſelfe,<note n="e" place="margin">Ier. 23.26.</note> THE LORD OVR RIGH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TEOVSNES? Such then as is <hi>our hungring and thirſting af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him,</hi> ſuch is our eating of him: If this hunger be in our ſtomackes, if this thirſt be in our throates, then let vs ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie our gnawing ſtomacks with him, let vs drinke him with our throates: But if this hunger and thirſt be proper to the ſoule, as <hi>David</hi> ſaith,<note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 42 2.</note> 
                  <hi>As the Hart panteth after the water brookes, ſo panteth my ſcale after thee, O God: My ſoule thirſteth for God, for the living God.</hi> What can the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of his fleſh be, but as S.
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:14451:98"/>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">Cyprian. de Coena domini Eſus igitur carnis huius quaedam aui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditas eſt, &amp; quoddam de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderium ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nendi in ipſo.</note> 
                  <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaith, <hi>a certaine gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe, and eager deſire to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide in him?</hi> Such as are <hi>our eyes</hi> wherewith we ſee him, ſuch is our mouth where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with we eate him. If we ſee him with our bodily eyes, with our bodily mouth we muſt eate him. But he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poundeth our ſeeing of him, by our beleeving in him, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,<note n="h" place="margin">Ioh 6.40.</note> 
                  <hi>This is the will of him that ſent me, that every one which ſeeth the Sonne and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeveth on him, may haue ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life.</hi> Therefore I ſay that to beleeue in him, is to eate him. He ſaid to the bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-god <hi>Iewe,</hi>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">Ioh 6.27.28.29.</note> 
                  <hi>Labour not for the meate which periſheth, but for that which endureth vnto everlaſting life.</hi> O Lord we aske of thee as the <hi>Iewes</hi> did, <hi>What ſhall we doe, that we may
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:14451:99"/>worke the workes of God,</hi> for ſuch as is <hi>our labouring</hi> for this meat, ſuch is our eating thereof: And thou anſwereſt O Lord; <hi>This is the worke of God, that ye beleeue on him whom he hath ſent.</hi>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">Auguſt. in Ioh. tract. <hi>25</hi> Hoc eſt ergo manducare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ibum, qui non perit, ſed qui permanet in vitam ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternam. Vt quid paras ventrem &amp; dentes? crede &amp; manda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſti.</note> 
                  <hi>This then alſo,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Auſtin, is to eate the meate which periſheth not, but endureth vnto everlaſting life. For what vſe makeſt thou readie thy teeth and thy belly? Beleeue and thou haſt eaten him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4.<note n="l" place="margin">2 Cor. 5.16.</note> 
                  <hi>We know him no more after the ſleſh: For</hi>
                  <note n="m" place="margin">Verſ. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>we are ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent from the Lord.</hi> And ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe he ſaith,<note n="n" place="margin">Ioh. 6.37.</note> 
                  <hi>All that the Father giveth me, ſhall come to me: and him that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to me, I will in no wiſe caſt out.</hi> Such then as are <hi>our ſeete</hi> wherewith we goe vnto him, ſuch is our eating of
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:14451:99"/>him. Goe we vnto him with our bodily feete? When he was in the world many did walke with him in their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, to whom he ſaid,<note n="o" place="margin">Ioh. 5.40.</note> 
                  <hi>Ye will not come to me, that ye might haue life,</hi> ſhewing that even then when they were preſent with him in body, they were abſent from him; becauſe they beleeved not in him: For<note n="p" place="margin">2 Cor. 5.7</note> 
                  <hi>we walke by faith, not by ſight.</hi> Therefore the <hi>Centurien</hi> abiding at home in his body, went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad vnto him with his faith, and ſaid vnto him,<note n="q" place="margin">Luk. 7.6.7.8.9.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord, trouble not thy ſelfe: For I am not worthy that thou ſhouldeſt enter vnder my roofe: Wherefore neither thought I my ſelfe worthy to come vnto thee: but ſay the word, and my ſeruant ſhall be healed.</hi> And to
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:14451:100"/>that faith which did not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard the bodily preſence of the Lord, the Lord gaue this commendation, <hi>I haue not found ſo great faith, no not in Iſraell.</hi> Chriſt himſelfe ſaith, that to goe thus vnto him, is to eate him.<note n="r" place="margin">Ioh. 6.35.</note> 
                  <hi>I am,</hi> faith he, <hi>the bread of life. He that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to me ſhall neuer hunger: and he that beleeveth on me ſhall neuer thirſt.</hi> In ſtead of <hi>eating,</hi> he putteth <hi>comming:</hi> in ſtead of <hi>drinking,</hi> he put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth <hi>beleeving:</hi> becauſe the eating of him, is to come to him: &amp; the drinking of him, is to beleeue in him. And theſe two are one.<note n="ſ" place="margin">Auguſt. de verbis domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni ſerm. <hi>2.</hi> Vbi credis, ibi venis.</note> 
                  <hi>Where thou beleeveſt, there thou com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Such hands to receiue him, ſuch mouth to eate him. The hand wherewith
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:14451:100"/>we receiue him is the hand of faith, as it is written;<note n="t" place="margin">Ioh. 1.12.</note> 
                  <hi>As many as received him, to them gaue he power to become the Sonnes of God, even to them that beleeue on his Name.</hi> This ſeemeth ſtrange to fleſh and blood, which may aske,<note n="u" place="margin">Aug. in Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>han trac. <hi>50.</hi> Quem tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo? abſentem? Quo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>anum in coelu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mittam, vt ibi ſeden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eam? fidem mitte, &amp; tenuiſti.</note> 
                  <hi>Whom ſhall I hold? Is he not abſent?</hi> Is he not in heaven? <hi>How ſhall I ſend my hand into heauen that I may hold him ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting there?</hi> S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, <hi>Send thy faith, and thou haſt taken hold of him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. Such as is our palate wherwith we taſte him, ſuch is our mouth wherewith we eate him.<note n="x" place="margin">Pſal 34.8.</note> 
                  <hi>O taſte, and ſee that the Lord is good.</hi> How?<note n="y" place="margin">Iob. 34.3</note> 
                  <hi>The eare trieth words, as the mouth taſteth meat.</hi> So this bread, which is the word of God,<note n="a" place="margin">Ioh. 1.14</note> 
                  <hi>the word which was made
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:14451:101"/>fleſh,</hi> muſt be taſted <hi>with a ſpirituall taſte, breeding in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s a delight of it;</hi> as S. <hi>Baſill</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth on the 33. <hi>Pſalme:</hi> And as <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaith,<note n="b" place="margin">Tertull. de Reſurrect. carnis c. <hi>37.</hi> Proinde in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſam vitae appetendus ſermo, &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uor andus au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditu, &amp; ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectu, &amp; ſide digeren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus.</note> 
                  <hi>We muſt long after it, devoure it with our eares, ruminate it with our vnderſtanding, diſgeſt it with our faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. Chriſt ſaith,<note n="c" place="margin">loh 6.56.</note> 
                  <hi>He that eateth my fleſh, and drinketh my blood, dwelleth in me, and I in him.</hi> If then ye can know how he dwelleth in you, and you in him, ye may eaſily conclude that after the ſame manner ye eate him. Saith not S. <hi>Paul,</hi> that<note n="d" place="margin">Eph. 3.17.</note> 
                  <hi>he dwelleth in our hearts by faith?</hi> And S. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Aug. in Iohan. tract. <hi>26.</hi> Hoc eſt ergo mandu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care illam eſcam, &amp; il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham bibere potum, in Chriſto ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere, &amp; illum manentem in ſe habere.</note> that <hi>to eate him, is to dwell in him, and haue him dwelling in vs?</hi> What is that, but to beleeue in him? <hi>He that beleeueth in him,</hi> ſaith
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:14451:101"/>the ſame Doctor, <hi>eateth him:</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Ibid. Qui credit in eum manducat: Inuiſibiliter ſaginatur, quis &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſibiliter renaſcitur: Infans intus eſt, Novus intus eſt: vbi nouellatur, ibi ſatiatur.</note> 
                  <hi>He is fed inuiſibly, becauſe he is borne againe inuiſibly. He is an infant inwardly: He is new inwardly: where he is renued, there he is ſatisfied.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>FINALLY, Such as are the benefits and the ends of this eating, ſuch muſt it be. For the meanes muſt be correſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pondent vnto their end. And we may know of what kind the meane is by the end to which it is directed. If the end of our eating be to ſtrengthen our mortall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and to make them lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, tall, big, let vs open our mouthes, ſharpen our teeth, inlarge our bellies: But if this bread be, as S. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith,<note n="*" place="margin">Bernard in prologo de Coena dimini. In ea (menſa) inuenies cibu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> non ventris, ſed mentis.</note> 
                  <hi>food for our ſoules, not for our bellies;</hi> if by it our<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 15.44.</note> 
                  <hi>naturall bodies</hi> muſt be made <hi>ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all,</hi>
                  <pb n="178" facs="tcp:14451:102"/>we muſt needs ſeeke a mouth in our ſoules to eate it ſpiritually. That mouth is faith.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER X.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Three reaſons why Chriſt vſed the metaphores of bread, and of eating.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>II.</hi> Great inſtructions in both.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>III.</hi> The metaphor of eating teacheth vs what preparation muſt goe before faith.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>IV.</hi> And what is the nature of faith.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>IF THIS be ſo, ſay the Popiſh<note n="f" place="margin">Bellarm. de Euchar lib <hi>1</hi> cap. <hi>5.</hi> § <hi>8.</hi> Quis credar rem facilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam, qualis eſt credere in Chriſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luiſſe dominu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cum ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendiculo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipuloru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noluere tot abſcuriſsinus metaphoria, cum potuiſſet vno verbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem totam declarare?</note> Doctours, why did the Lord involue a moſt cleare and eaſie thing with ſo many metaphores, and giue occaſion of offence vnto his diſciples? For he might haue ſaid in one
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:14451:102"/>word, <hi>He that beleeveth on me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwere. 1. that the Lord ſpake ſo vnto them, becauſe he deſired to ſtir vp in them a ſpirituall deſire of a more excellent bread, then that was for which they followed him, as I haue ſaid in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the firſt part of this Verſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Such metaphores of eating and drinking were not vncouth vnto them; for they are frequent in the old Teſtament. But they had a loathing of heavenly meats, and therefore they tooke ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions againſt his perſon when he ſpake of them, and would not vnderſtand him, as it is written,<note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 36.3.</note> 
                  <hi>The wicked hath left off to be wiſe, and to doe good.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="180" facs="tcp:14451:103"/>
3. Metaphores and ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litudes are more popular then words which are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, becauſe that by the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of earthly things ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended by the outward ſences, they make heavenly and ſpiritual things to come into the mind, and thus are moſt fit for the inſtruction of thoſe which being more dul haue need of milke, and not of ſtrong meate.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> II. FOR EXAMPLE, when Chriſt calleth himſelfe <hi>the living bread,</hi> there is greater inſtruction and comfort in that ſimilitude, then if he had called himſelfe the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour of the world: Becauſe the vſe of bread is to nouriſh and to feed, and thereby we learne, that Chriſt is come downe from heaven to be
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:14451:103"/>the true food and life of our foules. Likewiſe, when he exhorteth vs <hi>to eate of this bread,</hi> he giveth vs a more large and full inſtruction, then we could haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, if he had onely exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vs to beleeue in him. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this one word of <hi>eating</hi> teacheth vs, how we muſt be prepared before we can be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in Chriſt, and what is the true action and nature of faith whereby we beleeue in him.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> III. As FOR the preparation, we know by daily experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that he that is to eate muſt haue an emptie belly, know and feele the need he hath of meate, and hunger and thirſt after it.<note n="h" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 27.7.</note> 
                  <hi>The full ſoule loatheth an honey-combe, but to the hungry ſoule every
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:14451:104"/>bitter thing is ſweet.</hi> Even ſo before we can beleeue in Chriſt, we muſt know and feele out owne indigence, and the need we haue of his grace, that we may be able to ſay to God,<note n="i" place="margin">Pſal. 84.2.</note> 
                  <hi>My ſoule lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth, yea even fainteth for the Courts of the Lord: My heart and my fleſh cryeth out for the living God.</hi> If this preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be in you, ye haue your comfort in theſe words of Chriſt,<note n="k" place="margin">Math. 5.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Bleſſed are they which doe hunger and thirſt after righteouſneſſe: for they ſhall be filled.</hi> For without it there is no comming vnto Chriſt, and therefore no comfort from him. Doth he not cry,<note n="l" place="margin">Ioh. 7.37.</note> 
                  <hi>If any man thirſt, let him come vnto me, and drinke.</hi> Can we go vnto him? Can we drinke of the fulneſſe of grace
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:14451:104"/>which is in him, till we thirſt after him?</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> IV. BEING thus prepared by hunger and thirſt, we muſt take the meate which we long for, worke it with our teeth, receiue it into our ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mackes, diſgeſt it there, till it be turned into our blood &amp; fleſh, and by a true tranſſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation repaire &amp; reſtore our decaying bodies. All that is contained in this word of <hi>eating,</hi> and ſheweth vnto vs the nature and true action of faith, which is to apply Chriſt vnto our ſoules ſo neerly, that every one out of the true ſence of this hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly gift in his owne heart, ſaith moſt truly, as the <hi>Spouſe</hi> doth,<note n="m" place="margin">Cant. 2.16.</note> 
                  <hi>My beloved is mine, and I am his,</hi> and as <hi>Thomas</hi> did,<note n="n" place="margin">Ioh. 20.21</note> 
                  <hi>My Lord, and my God.</hi>
                  <pb n="184" facs="tcp:14451:105"/>according to the promiſe of the new Teſtament,<note n="o" place="margin">Zach. 13.9</note> 
                  <hi>I will ſay, It is my people: and they ſhall ſay, The Lord is my God.</hi> Such was the faith of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> when he ſaid,<note n="p" place="margin">Gal. 2.20.</note> 
                  <hi>I am crucified with Chriſt: nevertheleſſe I liue, yet not I, but Chriſt liveth in me: And the life which I now liue in the fleſh, I liue by the faith of the Sonne of God, who loved ME, and gaue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe for ME.</hi> Such is the faith of every true Chriſtian, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this ſaying of S. <hi>Peter,</hi>
                  <note n="q" place="margin">2 Pet. 1.1</note> 
                  <hi>ye haue obtained like precious faith with vs.</hi> What ſeeke we by eating of our daily bread? To liue. What ſeeke we by eating of Ieſus Chriſt? To haue communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with him, that we may liue by him. The Apoſtle ſaith, that <hi>we liue by faith:</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:14451:105"/>ſaith S. <hi>Cyprian,</hi>
                  <note n="r" place="margin">Cypr. de Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na domini. Qnod eſt eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacarni, hoc animae eſt fides.</note> 
                  <hi>That which food is to the body, the ſame is faith to the ſoule.</hi> For the ſame cauſe S. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> expounding the words of my Text, ſaith, that<note n="ſ" place="margin">Aug. in Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>han. trac. <hi>26</hi> Credere enim ineum, hoc eſt manduca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re panem vivum,</note> 
                  <hi>to beleeue in Chriſt, is to eate the living bread.</hi> This is not their expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition: It is from Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, as we haue heard.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER XI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>I.</hi> To eate Chriſt by faith, it is no imagination, as Papiſts ſay.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>II.</hi> Neither is it an eaſie thing by nature.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>III.</hi> It goeth beyond the whole reach of nature.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>IV.</hi> Therefore we muſt aske it of God.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>V.</hi> And although it be weake, be aſſured that it will eate Chriſt.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <pb n="186" facs="tcp:14451:106"/>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> IF THAT be true, ſay Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, if <hi>to eate Chriſt,</hi> be no other thing, but <hi>to beleeue in him,</hi> there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more eaſie then to be ſaved. What is faith? An ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination in the braine that Chriſt hath ſaved vs. How eaſily may we imagine ſuch a thing, and ſo be ſaved by a fancie?</p>
               <p n="1">1. Indeed if we did ſpeake of eating of Chriſt, as they doe, it might be ſaid moſt truely, that there is nothing more eaſie. What ſo eaſie to any man, as to open the mouth of the body, and to ſwallow downe that which entereth into it? Is there any Papiſt that findeth any diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie in it? Yea they hold their eating of Chriſt ſo eaſie that they make it common
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:14451:106"/>not onely to bad, as well as to good men, but alſo to toades, wormes, dogs, aſſes, mice, and other beaſts.</p>
               <p n="2">2. When they ſpeake of faith as of an imagination, they teach vs what they iudge, and what they will haue vs to ſudge of their faith: They ſay that they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in God. Is their beliefe nothing but an imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? They call on God: And<note n="t" place="margin">Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 10.14.</note> 
                  <hi>how ſhall they call on him in whom they haue not beleeved?</hi>
                  <note n="u" place="margin">Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 14.23</note> 
                  <hi>For whatſoeuer is not of faith, is ſinne.</hi> What? Will they confeſſe that their prayers, and in a word, all their moſt laborious devotion is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but an imagination? Aske of them how they know that Chriſts body is in the Sacrament as big and
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:14451:107"/>as tall as it was on the croſſe, although ſuch a thing came never in Chriſts mind, they will anſwer, that Chriſt hath ſaid it, and they beleeue it. That beliefe indeed is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a moſt fond ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination: But will they call it ſo?</p>
               <p n="3">3. A great many of their Doctors confeſſe, that in the firſt part of this Chapter till the one &amp; fiftie verſe, Chriſt ſpeaketh of the ſpirituall manducation of his body, and recommendeth it vnto vs, and ſome of the moſt lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned amongſt them confirme by inſoluble arguments, that the whole Chapter is of the ſame argument. And dare they ſay that Chriſt recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended nothing vnto vs but imaginations?</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="189" facs="tcp:14451:107"/>
4. Since the beginning of the world there was never a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man ſaved but by the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Chriſt. The Apoſtle writeth of the fathers which were in the deſert, that<note n="x" place="margin">1 Cor. 10 3.4.</note> 
                  <hi>they did all eate the ſame ſpirituall meate, and did all drinke the ſame ſpirituall drinke:</hi>
                  <note n="y" place="margin">Aug. de poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit. cap. <hi>1.</hi> to. <hi>9.</hi> Eundem non inuenio quomodo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellig am, niſi cum quem &amp; nos.</note> The ſame which we eat &amp; drink, not corporall in the eleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, but ſpirituall in the ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation: <hi>For they dranke of that ſpirituall Rocke that followed them, and that Rocke was Chriſt.</hi> Was that eating and drinking of Chriſt before he came into the world no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but an imagination? How many millio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians die and are ſaved be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they can eate Chriſt in the Sacrament? And yet without eating of Chriſt ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:14451:108"/>there is no ſalvation. Are they alſo ſaved by ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination? When we ſhall be called<note n="a" place="margin">Rev. 19.7.</note> 
                  <hi>to the marriage-ſupper of the Lambe,</hi> when<note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 8.11</note> 
                  <hi>we ſhall ſit downe with Abraham and Iſaac and Iacob in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heaven,</hi> when there<note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 36.8.</note> 
                  <hi>God ſhall ſatisfie vs abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly with the fatneſſe of his houſe, and ſhall make vs drinke of the river of his pleaſures,</hi> ſhall that eating and that drinking alſo be nothing but an imagination? As we ſhall eate him then, ſo muſt we eate him now.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> AND to eate him ſo now, is not an eaſie thing, is not an imagination. To ſee our owne miſery and the mercy of God, our naughtineſſe and his goodneſſe, our emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe and his fulneſſe, our
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:14451:108"/>folly and his wiſedome, our weakeneſſe and his power, our ſhame and his glory diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>played in Ieſus Chriſt, is it an eaſie thing? Is it an imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? To know and to feele how worthy I was of his ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, and how wonderfull is that loue wherwith he hath loved me in his deare Sonne Ieſus Chriſt, is it an eaſie thing? is it an imagination? To runne vnto Chriſt, to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace him, to take hold on him, to lodge him in our hearts, to ſay vnto him as <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> did,<note n="d" place="margin">Gen. 32.26.</note> 
                  <hi>I will not let thee goe, except thou bleſſe me:</hi> Or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with <hi>David,</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Pſ. 73.28.</note> 
                  <hi>It is good for me to draw neere to God, I haue put my truſt in the Lord God.</hi> And therefore I will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver let thee goe, that thou mayeſt bleſſe me for ever;
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:14451:109"/>To ſeeke and finde grace, mercie, peace, life, and ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in him, and therevpon to ſay,<note n="f" place="margin">Pſal 118.6.14.</note> 
                  <hi>The Lord is on my ſide, I will not feare: The Lord is my ſtrength and ſong, and is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come my ſalvation,</hi> is it an ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie thing? Is it an imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> SVRELY, the eating of Chriſt by this kind of faith goeth ſo farre beyond the power and reach of nature, that<note n="g" place="margin">Math. 16.17.</note> 
                  <hi>fleſh and blood doe not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veale Chriſt to be the Sonne of the living God, but the Father which is in heauen,</hi> and it is as difficile, yea as impoſſible to beleeue in Chriſt, as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue to be a Martyr for Chriſt: Therefore the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle conioyneth them as two moſt wonderfull &amp; rare gifts of God, ſaying,<note n="h" place="margin">Phil. 1.29.</note> 
                  <hi>For vnto you
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:14451:109"/>it is given in the behalfe of Chriſt, not onely to beleeue on him, but alſo to ſuffer for his ſake.</hi> Yea he ſaith, that God diſplayeth the ſame<note n="i" place="margin">Eph. 1.19.20.</note> 
                  <hi>might of his power, which he wrought in Chriſt, when he raiſed him from the dead,</hi> to make vs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IV"/> WHEREFORE let vs all cry to God with <hi>David,</hi>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">Pſal. 119.18.</note> 
                  <hi>Open thou mine eyes, that I may beholde wondrous things out of thy law.</hi> Let vs all pray for our ſelues: as the bleſſed Apoſtle did for the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> that<note n="l" place="margin">Eph. 1.17.18.</note> 
                  <hi>the God of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, the Father of glory, may giue vnto vs the ſpirit of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and revelation, in the knowledge of him, the eyes of our vnderſtanding being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightened, that we may know what is the hope of his calling,
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:14451:110"/>and what the riches of the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his inheritance in the Saints.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> AND when we haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved this faith from aboue, let vs acknowledg the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of it, &amp; cry to the Lord with teares, as did the Father of the lunatick child,<note n="m" place="margin">Marke 9.24.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord, I beleeue, helpe thou mine vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beliefe,</hi> and with the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,<note n="n" place="margin">Luk. 17.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord, increaſe our faith;</hi> Yet reſting ſtill aſſured, that as the Pilots trembling Diall in a ſhippe toſſed to and fro with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> waues of the tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuous Sea, looketh ſtraight to the North Pole, as the ſhaking hand of a poore man ſicke of the Palſey, ſtretcheth it ſelfe forth to receiue the rich almes of a bountifull King, and as a dying man will open his wanne and wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:14451:110"/>mouth to let downe the reſtoratiue, whereby his life is reſtored; So our trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, ſhaking, and weake faith, will in the midde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the moſt tempeſtuous and bluſtery Sea of temptations, faſten her eyes vpon Chriſt, <hi>receiue</hi> him, and eate him, that in the middeſt of death, and in the belly of the graue we may be ſaved by him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER XII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>I.</hi> The eating of Chriſt by faith is poſsible.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>II.</hi> It is not hindred by the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of time;</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>III.</hi> Nor of place.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>IV.</hi> It may be fitted to all the ſimilitudes which expreſſe our vnion with Chriſt.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>V.</hi> It is decent.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <pb n="196" facs="tcp:14451:111"/>
                     <hi>VI.</hi> It is profitable.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> CHRIST ſaid to the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Lunarike child,<note n="o" place="margin">Marke 9.24.</note> 
                  <hi>If thou canst beleeue, all things are poſsible to him that beleeveth:</hi> Then, ſay I, to him that beleeveth it <hi>is poſsible</hi> to eate Chriſt by his faith. I ſay more, that to eate him ſo <hi>is decent and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious</hi> vnto Chriſt, and moſt profitable to the eater.</p>
               <p>If there were any impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility in this eating, it ſhould come either from <hi>the diſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of time,</hi> or from <hi>the diſtance of place.</hi> We eate him as dead: And wee reckon from his death 1625. yeares, which is a long time. He died <hi>in Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotha,</hi> which is far removed from vs, and we muſt goe to his croſſe, &amp; eate him there.
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:14451:111"/>From thence we muſt goe vp to heaven, where he now is, and feed vpon him there. Between the heavens where he is, and the earth where we are, the diſtance is almoſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite. Behold now how all that, is not any impediment to faith.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> To BEGIN by <hi>the diſtance of time.</hi> Between the promiſe made to <hi>Abraham</hi> and Chriſt there is 1927. yeares, and he had eyes, not in his head, but in his heart to ſee Chriſt, as Chriſt ſaid,<note n="p" place="margin">Ioh. 8.56.</note> 
                  <hi>Abraham reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to ſee my day, and he ſaw it, and was glad.</hi> From the firſt Paſſeover which was kept in Egypt till Chriſt there is 1497. yeares. At that time<note n="q" place="margin">Heb. 11.27.28.</note> 
                  <hi>Moſes by faith kept the Paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, for ſooke Egypt, and endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as ſeeing him who is inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible.</hi>
                  <pb n="198" facs="tcp:14451:112"/>At that ſame time the Fathers in the deſert<note n="r" place="margin">1. Cor. 10 3.4.</note> 
                  <hi>did eate the ſame ſpirituall bread, and drinke the ſame ſpirituall drinke,</hi> which was Chriſt. How but by faith? For Chriſt is<note n="ſ" place="margin">Rev. 13.8.</note> 
                  <hi>the Lambe ſlaine from the foundation of the world</hi> in the efficacy of his death towards all the faithfull which were from the beginning. So the Apoſtle ſaith, that<note n="t" place="margin">Gal. 3.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Chriſt is euidently ſet forth before our eyes, and is crucified among vs:</hi> Crucified certainely to the eyes of our faith, which ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the things paſt from the beginning of the world, and all thoſe that are to come till the end of the world. For<note n="u" place="margin">Heb. 11.1</note> 
                  <hi>faith is the ſubſtance of things hoped for,</hi> and <hi>the euidence of things not ſeene,</hi> it giveth a being in the heart to that
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:14451:112"/>which hath no being in the world, and maketh viſible that which is inuiſible.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> AND THEREFORE <hi>the diſtance of place</hi> alſo cannot hinder it. For although we traile theſe our mortall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies on the earth, yet<note n="x" place="margin">Phil. 3.20.</note> 
                  <hi>our converſation is in heaven,</hi> and our<note n="y" place="margin">Heb. 6.19.20.</note> 
                  <hi>hope is an anchor of the ſoule both ſure and ſteadfaſt, and which entereth into that within the vaile, whither Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, as forerunner, is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred for vs.</hi> There by faith<note n="z" place="margin">Eph. 2.6.</note> 
                  <hi>wee ſit together with him:</hi> There our faith ſeeth him, eateth him, imbraceth all the promiſes of God in him. O the moſt wonderfull effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy of faith! It ſeeth all things paſt and to come: It imbraceth the two ends of the world: It flyeth back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:14451:113"/>to <hi>Golgotha,</hi> and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſaying of Chriſt,<note n="a" place="margin">Math. 24.28.</note> 
                  <hi>Whereſoever the carkaſſe is, there will the Eagles be gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red together,</hi> like a ſpirituall Eagle it ſtoopeth vpon him hanging on the Croſſe. It faſtenth her clawes vpon his wounds, it drinketh the blood ſtreaming out of his ſide, it feedeth on him with a greedie ſtomacke, and lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth him never till it be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, and becauſe it is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatiable, and never hath e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough of him, it leaveth him never. Forthwith and at the ſame inſtant it flyeth aboue all the viſible heavens, it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treth boldly into Gods clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet, it<note n="b" place="margin">Rev. 3 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> ſitteth downe with him in his throne, and raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth with him moſt glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly in heaven.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="201" facs="tcp:14451:113"/>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IV"/> THE EATING of Papiſts cannot be ſitted to any of the other ſimilitudes, this can to them all. By what is Chriſt our head, and we his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers; He the vine, and we the members? By his Spirit, and by our faith. By what is he the foundation, and we the Temple built on him? By his Spirit, and by our faith? By what doth he giue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be our Garment? By his Spirit? By what doe we put him on? By our faith. By what is he borne in our hearts? By his Spirit. By what are we borne againe, &amp; made new creatures in him? By our faith. By what are we waſhed in his blood? By his Spirit, and by our faith. By what doth he wed vs to himſelfe, that we may be his wife? By
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:14451:114"/>his Spirit. By what doe we eſpouſe him, that he may be our husband? By our faith. By what giveth he himſelfe vnto vs to be our meate and drinke? By his Spirit. By what doe we all eate and drinke him? By our faith. So ye ſee that all the ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes doe agree, &amp; concurre in the manner of our vnion with Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> CONSIDER now how de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, yea how glorious this eating of Chriſt is. Seeing we muſt eate him, is it not more decent and comely to lodge him in our hearts, which he hath choſen to be his Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſaying,<note n="c" place="margin">Pro. 23.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>6.</note> 
                  <hi>My ſonne giue me thine heart,</hi> then in our bellies, which are puddles of infection, and ſtincking ſinkes? Is it not more glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:14451:114"/>to contemplate him in heaven, ſitting at the right hand of his Father, and to feed vpon him there, where we are certaine to find him, then to ſeeke him in a cruſt of bread, where he is not to be found?</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VI"/> AND IP, we ſpeake of the profit of this eating, is it not more comfortable to feele him living and dwelling in our hearts, and quickening them, then to haue him in our mouths, and to keepe him a ſhort ſpace in our ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mackes, who can tell for what vſe? He ſaith of them that eate him, that <hi>they ſhall liue for euer:</hi> and it is certaine that he ſpeaketh of earing by faith, becauſe he ſaid in the 47. Verſe, <hi>Verily, verily, I ſay vnto you, He that belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:14451:115"/>in me hath everlaſting life.</hi> This is the fourth and laſt head of this Text, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication wherof Ile deferre to another occaſion. I ſay onely, that he which eateth Chriſt liveth already, for <hi>he hath everlaſting life,</hi> and <hi>ſhall liue for ever,</hi> otherwayes the life which he liveth could not be called <hi>everlaſting.</hi> He liveth already, for his ſinnes are forgiven him, and<note n="d" place="margin">Pſal. 32.1. Rom. 4.6.</note> 
                  <hi>the bleſſedneſſe of man</hi> in this life, is principally in <hi>the forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his ſinnes:</hi> He liveth already. For<note n="e" place="margin">Gal. 2.20.</note> 
                  <hi>Chriſt liueth in him,</hi> and hath made him<note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 6.4.11.</note> 
                  <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue vnto GOD,</hi> that he <hi>may walke in newneſſe of life.</hi> He ſhal liue for ever, no more on earth, but in heaven, where the ſpirituall life of his ſoul which is begun here ſhall be
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:14451:115"/>perfected, where<note n="g" place="margin">Aug. in Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>han. trac. <hi>26</hi> Videbit quod adhuc no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendo credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, Mandu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabit quod eſurijt: Sati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abitur eo quod ſitit.</note> 
                  <hi>he ſhall ſee, that which now he beleeveth, ſhall eate that which now he hungreth after; ſhall be filled with that whereof now he is a thirſt,</hi> as <hi>David</hi> ſaid,<note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 36.8.</note> 
                  <hi>They ſhall be abundantly ſatisfied with the fatneſſe of thy houſe: &amp; thou ſhalt make them drink of the river of thy pleaſures.</hi> And in the bleſſed day of the Reſurrection,<note n="i" place="margin">Phil. 3.21.</note> 
                  <hi>Chriſt ſhall change his vile body, that it may be faſhioned like vnto his glorious body.</hi> So he liveth, and ſhall liue a moſt glorious and bleſſed life <hi>internally</hi> in his ſoule, <hi>externally</hi> in his body, and <hi>eternally</hi> in body and ſoule together in the kingdome of heaven.<note n="k" place="margin">Aug. in Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>han. trac. <hi>17</hi> Tunc quod viuet, no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietur: Tunc quod ſanabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aegro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabit: Tunc quod ſatiabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, non eſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riet, neque ſitiot: Tunc quod renou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitur, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on veteraſcet<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Then that which ſhall liue, ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver die: that which ſhall be healed, ſhall never be ſicke:
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:14451:116"/>that which ſhall be ſatisfied, ſhall never hunger nor thirſt: that which ſhall be renued, ſhall never waxe old.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER. XIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>I.</hi> As this bread is moſt won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull, ſo muſt we conſider the moſt wonderfull mercy of God in the giving of it.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>II.</hi> Papiſts eate not of this bread.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>III.</hi> We muſt value it at the higheſt rate, and deſire no other bread.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>IV.</hi> A prayer to God for this bread.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> O MOST wonderfull bread<note n="l" place="margin">Aug. to. <hi>10.</hi> Homil <hi>32.</hi> Vt panem Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducaret ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo, dominus Angelorum factus eſt homo.</note> This is the food of the bleſſed Angels in heaven: This is the food of all true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans on earth. l <hi>That man might
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:14451:116"/>eate the bread of Angels, the Lord of Angels was made man.</hi> Of it they, of it we eate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually, and, ô wonder,<note n="m" place="margin">Ibid. Nec deficit vnde paſcantur, nec minui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur eſca ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorum.</note> 
                  <hi>it is not diminiſhed.</hi> By it they, by it we liue for ever. O moſt wonderfull mercy of God who giveth vs ſuch wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full bread! <hi>Sion</hi> was in a pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull eſtate, when bewailing it ſhe ſaid,<note n="n" place="margin">Lam. 4.4.</note> 
                  <hi>The tongue of the ſuckling childe cleaveth to the roofe of his mouth for thirſt: The young children aske bread, and no man breaketh it vnto them.</hi> O then how bleſſed is our eſtate, whoſe crying for this bread God hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented? yea who hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared it for vs before wee were borne, who hath given it vnto vs before we ſought it?<note n="o" place="margin">1 Ioh. 4.10.</note> 
                  <hi>Herein is loue, not that we loved God, but that he loved vs,
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:14451:117"/>and ſent his Sonne to be the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiation for our ſinnes.</hi> It is a too too little &amp; ſmall thing to his bountie, yea it hath beene nothing in his eyes to feed with the bread which commeth out of the earth theſe our vile and mortall bodies, which although they ſtarue not, yet they muſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh by ſickneſſe, by age, or by ſome other miſhap. In this he hath diſplayed all the treaſures and riches of grace and mercie, that to his ſpirituall children he hath given the true, ſpirituall, and heavenly bread, whereof if any man eate, he ſhall liue for ever.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> DEPART from vs Papiſts, which know not this bread. Your going, your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming, your trotting, your running
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:14451:117"/>from one Saint to another, from one Angell to another, ſheweth that ye are ever hunger-ſtarved, ever dried vp with thirſt like a pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheard, and therefore that yee haue never eaten of this bread. For if yee did eate Chriſt, he would ſatisfie your hunger, according to his owne ſaying,<note n="p" place="margin">Ioh. 6.35.</note> 
                  <hi>I am the bread of life, he that commeth to me ſhall never hunger.</hi> O then, O abuſed Chriſtians when will ye turne your faces to him, and goe vnto him? O periſhing ſoules, liſten I pray you, to the voyce of him who onely giveth the living bread, and who cryeth vnto you;<note n="q" place="margin">Eſa. 55.1.2.</note> 
                  <hi>Hoe, every one that thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth, come ye to the waters, and he that hath no money: Come ye, buy and eate. Yea come, buy
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:14451:118"/>wine and milke without mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and without price. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doe ye ſpend money for that which is no bread? and your la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour for that which ſatisfieth not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> WHETHER they will heare, or whether they will for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare, let vs value this bread at the higheſt rate, and ſay vnto our Saviour,<note n="r" place="margin">Pſal. 73.25.26.</note> 
                  <hi>Whom haue 1 in heaven but thee? and there is none vpon earth that I deſire beſides thee. My fleſh and my heart faileth: But GOD is the ſtrength of my heart, and my portion for ever.</hi> Thoſe that are ſicke refuſe to eate bread, and <hi>David</hi> ſaith that in his ſorrow<note n="ſ" place="margin">Pſal. 102.1.</note> 
                  <hi>he did forget to eate his bread.</hi> Let vs not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to eate this bread, when it is offered vnto vs, and let let vs never forget to eate it
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:14451:118"/>when we haue it. It is<note n="t" place="margin">Aug. to. <hi>10.</hi> hom. <hi>32</hi> Hac eſt ſalus ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra, medici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na infirmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum: Cibus Sanorum.</note> Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick to thoſe which are ſicke, meate to thoſe which be whole, ſtrength to thoſe that are weake, comſort to thoſe that are diſtreſſed, life to thoſe that die.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IV"/> O EVER-LIVING and moſt loving GOD, thou haſt commanded vs<note n="u" place="margin">Eſa. 58.7.</note> 
                  <hi>to breake our bread to the hungry:</hi> doe vnto vs that which thou co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt vs to doe vnto others, and breake this thy bread vnto our hungry ſoules. The Fathers prepare bread for their children: And the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren looke that their fathers ſhall giue them the bread which they haue prepared for them.<note n="x" place="margin">Luk. 11.11.</note> 
                  <hi>If a Sonne ſhall aske bread of his Father, will he giue him a ſtone?</hi> Thou art our heavenly Father, and we are
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:14451:119"/>thy children: Thou haſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for vs the moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent bread that ever was: Even thine owne Sonne.<note n="y" place="margin">Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 8.32.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou haſt not ſpared him, but haſt delivered him vp for vs all,</hi> that he might be our bread, &amp; wilt thou not giue him vnto vs? In our bodily neceſſities, we cry vnto thee, <hi>Giue vs this day our daily bread,</hi> and thou giueſt it not onely vnto vs, out even vnto them which know not thee to be the fountaine of all good, and therefore cry not for it vnto thee. O loving Father thou keepeſt for vs thy children bread more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, more rare, and more precious: Even <hi>this living bread,</hi> which is indeed <hi>our bread,</hi> being ſent into the world, prepared, and given
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:14451:119"/>for vs, that it may be given vnto vs. This is <hi>the daily bread</hi> of our ſoules, which thou giveſt to thy children by thy holy Spirit O Father we are thy children: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſend thy holy Spirit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our hearts with this <hi>our bread,</hi> and <hi>giue vs this day cur daily bread,</hi> that eating it dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with a true &amp; liuely faith, we may by it liue with thee for ever. To thee who art the giver of this bread, To thy Sonne Ieſus who is this bread, To the holy Ghoſt, who from thee bringeth this bread into our hearts, be all prayſe, glory, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, both now and for evermore. AMEN.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
